<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Princess on uzak.github.io</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/tags/princess/</link><description>Recent content in Princess on uzak.github.io</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://uzak.github.io/tags/princess/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Odyssey (1997)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-03-odyssey/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-03-odyssey/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ll be alive like this tree around which we&amp;rsquo;ve built this world. Is there a way to avoid this war? Troy will not fall so gently. Turn Troy to dust. Return with the spoils of enemies you&amp;rsquo;ve slain and my heart will rejoice. The gods of sea and sky carried me towards Troy. The walls of Troy reach to the clouds. I did not want you to escape this journey.</description></item><item><title>Ready Player One</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-10-17-ready_player_one/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-10-17-ready_player_one/</guid><description>The year is 2045 and the reality sucks so much that practically all humanity spends most of its time in a virtual reality called OASIS. Recently its Author has passed away and he&amp;rsquo;s offered his position including the ownership of OASIS to anybody who masters his three challenges:
Win an unwinnable race. The key to this challenge is to drive backwards. Ask the Lady of the Author to dance. Easy, isn&amp;rsquo;t it?</description></item><item><title>Vivekachudamani Swami Paramarthananda 2020</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-07-26-vivekachudamani_sp_2020/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-07-26-vivekachudamani_sp_2020/</guid><description>Selected 108 Verses
Summary of first 64 Verses
Class 14: 31, 32 &amp;hellip; What is anAtmA? sat na bhavati, asat na bhavati, ubhayAtmikA na bhavati:
Maya and its product do not commander category of existent entity. But you cannot say opposite. Anirvachaynia - seemingly existent, Experientially available. On probing mysterious. Like dream world. You cannot say existent or non-existent. When we are in dream the dream world comes into &amp;ldquo;existent&amp;rdquo; category.</description></item><item><title>Bhagavad Gita Chapter 4</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-02-14-bhagavad_gita_chapter_4/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-02-14-bhagavad_gita_chapter_4/</guid><description>Notes from classes at Arsha Vidya Gurukulam.
Bhagavad Gita Chapter 4 Verse 41 discovery, intelligence vs. machinery of knowledge
Part 1 samsara = worldliness = bondage cognitive knowledge &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; accumulated knowledge (intellect - in braincells) &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; jnanam as satyam jnanam anantam brahman (intelligence; all-pervading truth). All are called jnanam even though different in nature. Intelligence is not limited to the braincells only. In is in the braincells but not of the braincells.</description></item></channel></rss>