<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>uzak.github.io</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/</link><description>Recent content on uzak.github.io</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://uzak.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Rýchlo, lacno a kvalitne</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-07-23-r%C3%BDchlo_lacno_a_kvalitne/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-07-23-r%C3%BDchlo_lacno_a_kvalitne/</guid><description>Vraj je možné mať len dve z týchto troch. K čomu to vedie?
Rýchlo, lacno a nekvalitne Výsledkom bude &amp;ldquo;šmejd&amp;rdquo;, resp. snaha vybehnúť s niekým resp. niečím. Na druhú stranu tento prístup bude budovať inteligenciu niekoho, kto sa oň snaží. A tiež funguje proti inercii - lenivosti. Rýchlosťou človek unikne zemi.
Rýchlo, draho a kvalitne Nepozerať sa na cenu a požadovať prvotriedne výsledky buduje sebadôležitosť. Z človeka stane elitista / snob / egoista &amp;hellip; indivíduum.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-07-12-15_11_43/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 15:11:43 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-07-12-15_11_43/</guid><description>Valerij Markus: Pozorovať je vždy horšie a zložitejšie, než sa toho priamo účastniť. Pretože z diaľky s tým nemôžete nič robiť.</description></item><item><title>Docker Workshop</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-07-07-docker_workshop/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-07-07-docker_workshop/</guid><description>Here</description></item><item><title>Slovenska Biblia</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-07-07-slovenska_biblia/</link><pubDate>Fri, 07 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-07-07-slovenska_biblia/</guid><description>Viac tu.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-30-05_50_45/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Jun 2023 05:50:45 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-30-05_50_45/</guid><description>Ted Gioia: Crisis of trust. If your job was to destroy access to reliable information in our society, how would you do it? 30 steps&amp;hellip;
And one more: Scarcest thing in the world</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-29-12_27_58/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2023 12:27:58 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-29-12_27_58/</guid><description>Kamil Galeev: The media and the academia are obsessed with the unimportant.
Western discourse in Russia is mostly a projection of Western intellectuals. They project their fears, of course. But also their hopes and dreams
Being the King&amp;rsquo;s Philosopher, a brain behind the tyrant, has been a wet dream of intellectuals at least since the days of Plato.
The King is in no need of a &amp;ldquo;philosopher&amp;rdquo;. What the King needs is a jester.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-29-09_52_36/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2023 09:52:36 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-29-09_52_36/</guid><description>Design for the web without Figma.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-28-06_05_31/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2023 06:05:31 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-28-06_05_31/</guid><description>&amp;ldquo;Emotional intelligence&amp;rdquo; is like &amp;ldquo;dry water&amp;rdquo;.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-27-17_01_22/</link><pubDate>Tue, 27 Jun 2023 17:01:22 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-27-17_01_22/</guid><description>Glubb: “The heroes of declining nations are always the same, the athlete, the singer or the actor”</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-25-09_44_54/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2023 09:44:54 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-25-09_44_54/</guid><description>Forbes: &amp;ldquo;it holds 65% of the world’s total arable land, 30% of the world’s mineral reserves, 8% of the world’s natural gas and 12% of the world’s oil reserves.&amp;rdquo; That includes &amp;ldquo;40% of the world’s gold&amp;rdquo; and the &amp;ldquo;largest reserves of diamonds, cobalt, platinum and uranium&amp;rdquo; on the planet. Compound that with a population of 1.4 billion people, with many people soon entering the workforce (the median age is 19)&amp;quot;</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-25-07_31_39/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Jun 2023 07:31:39 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-25-07_31_39/</guid><description>Politics is not the pursuit of the perfection, but the art of the second best.
Napoleon: There are only two powers in the world – the power of the sword and the spirit… In the long run, the sword is always beaten by the spirit.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-24-14_42_42/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2023 14:42:42 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-24-14_42_42/</guid><description>Kamil Galeev: Putin&amp;rsquo;s grandfather worked at Lenin&amp;rsquo;s canteen as a cook Kirilenko&amp;rsquo;s great-grandfather headed this canteen In a country like Russia they had the highest privilege one can have. The Access to the Body and: Serving at the table = recipe for the upward social mobility</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-24-08_40_57/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2023 08:40:57 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-24-08_40_57/</guid><description>Kamil Galeev: According to Ibn Khaldun, an assabiyah typically lives for four generations: from the conquest to the downfall. It very, very rarely outlives this span. If I remember correctly, Ibn Khaldun himself could name only one single exception to the rule.
Four generations is one human life &amp;hellip;</description></item><item><title>Cogito, ergo sum</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-06-24-cogito_ergo_sum/</link><pubDate>Sat, 24 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-06-24-cogito_ergo_sum/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;m sure many of has have pondered about the meaning of Rene Descartes&amp;rsquo; famous statement: cogito, ergo sum (&amp;ldquo;I think, therefore I am&amp;rdquo;). But what did he really mean? I&amp;rsquo;ve experienced this statement as a polarising one. Can it be, that he was suggesting something deeper that what&amp;rsquo;s immediately visible?
Option A I&amp;rsquo;ve seen spiritually inclined people lose their nerve over how can the &amp;ldquo;being&amp;rdquo; be conditioned by thinking. And I was no exception.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-23-05_53_59/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 Jun 2023 05:53:59 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-23-05_53_59/</guid><description>How People Come To Believe Something As Stupid As Male &amp;amp; Female Equality</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-22-15_25_30/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Jun 2023 15:25:30 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-22-15_25_30/</guid><description>la pornografía de indignación</description></item><item><title>The Subtle Art of Not Giving a F*ck</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-06-21-the_subtle_art_of_not_giving_a_fuck/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-06-21-the_subtle_art_of_not_giving_a_fuck/</guid><description>Don&amp;rsquo;t try Bukowski never tried to by anything other what he was. He was able to be completely, unflinchingly honest with himself - especially the worst parts of himself. Feedback loop from Hell The desire for more positive experience is itself a negative experience. Acceptance of one&amp;rsquo;s negative experience is a positive experience. Happiness Is a Problem The premise that happiness is algorithmic, that it can be worked for and earned and achieved is a problem.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-20-10_19_31/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2023 10:19:31 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-20-10_19_31/</guid><description>Sorprenderse, extrañarse, es comenzar a entender. Es el deporte y el lujo específico del intelectual. Por eso su gesto gremial consiste en mirar al mundo con los ojos dilatados por la extrañeza. Todo en el mundo es extraño y es maravilloso para unas pupilas bien abiertas. Esto, maravillarse, es la delicia vedada al futbolista, y que, en cambio, lleva al intelectual por el mundo en perpetua embriaguez de visionario. Su atributo son los ojos en pasmo.</description></item><item><title>The Mind of Napoleon</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-06-18-the_mind_of_napoleon/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-06-18-the_mind_of_napoleon/</guid><description>src
There are only two powers in the world – the power of the sword and the spirit…In the long run, the sword is always beaten by the spirit. How can there be a state without any religion? Society cannot exist without inequality of fortune, and inequality of fortune cannot exist without religion In Spinoza, each thought is a step to another thought; in Napoleon, each thought is a step to an action Luck is the ability to exploit accidents.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-06-09_39_10/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 09:39:10 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-06-09_39_10/</guid><description>Hypotéka je ve své podstatě otroctví.</description></item><item><title>Scrimba: Learn React</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-06-06-scrimba_learn_react/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-06-06-scrimba_learn_react/</guid><description>source
Intro The easiest way to learn something is the hard way learn by doing avoid &amp;ldquo;tutorial hell&amp;rdquo; by watching school: goal of learning is good grade. Here to be able to write react code. Repetition is your best friend when it comes to learn something Don&amp;rsquo;t binge the course Your brain needs rest. Take breaks often. Re-watch past lessons. Esp. when stuck. Ask community on discord, if in doubt. First thing to learn: how to think in react?</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-04-06_53_02/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Jun 2023 06:53:02 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-06-04-06_53_02/</guid><description>Don&amp;rsquo;t install copilot</description></item><item><title>Reflekcia</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-05-31-reflekcie/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-05-31-reflekcie/</guid><description>Poznámky pre seba alebo zopár úvah podmienených poslednými dňami, vysporiadajúce sa s tým, čo sa stalo niekedy dávno v TopTal-e alebo práve teraz v Hübl-i.
Hnev Odpustiť. Hnevom škodím len sám sebe. Nestojí za to sa hnevať. O nič nejde. Veď čo už môžem stratiť?
Mať pravdu Pravdu? Tá je relatívna a patri do môjho sukromného sveta. Každý svet ma inú pravdu. Len tá Pravda všetky svety spájajúca je univerzálna ale nepomenovateľná.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-05-28-coincidence/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2023 03:01:05 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-05-28-coincidence/</guid><description>The proximity is no coincidence (src)</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-05-28-dont_depend/</link><pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2023 02:45:23 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-05-28-dont_depend/</guid><description>Don&amp;rsquo;t depend too much on anyone in this world because even your own shadow leaves you when you are in darkness. — Ibn Taymiyyah</description></item><item><title>Advaita at Ramakrishna Math, Hyderbad</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-05-27-advaita_at_ramakrishna_math_hyderbad/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-05-27-advaita_at_ramakrishna_math_hyderbad/</guid><description>source
What is advaita? Do you want a definition so you need not to think? Better approach? What is not advaita. You discover what it is. You&amp;rsquo;re supposed to think. Advaita is not a vada = intellectual gymnastics. Great scholarship and ability to speak well. Vada is a product of intellect. Advaita is not religion. Religion is a belief. Thinking and belief don&amp;rsquo;t go together. Beliefs get inherited Religion divides people Advaita is a vision, darsanam.</description></item><item><title>EDX: Exercising Leadership: Foundational Principles</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-05-26-edx_exercising_leadership_foundational_principles/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-05-26-edx_exercising_leadership_foundational_principles/</guid><description>source
Introduction: Get on the Balcony People learn best from experience. Doing things enables people to learn, not theory (reading/seeing). Lessons from your own experience stick with you best. The balcony is the place from which you can step back and observe. So that you can get back on the floor and make your next move. In leadership, the most common sources of problem are diagnostics. If you get the problem wrong, generally the action will be wrong.</description></item><item><title>EDX: Becoming a Successful Leader (Inclusive Leadership)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-05-26-edx_becoming_a_successful_leader/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-05-26-edx_becoming_a_successful_leader/</guid><description>source
Week 1: 21st Century Leaders - vision Lone Nut TED: How to start a movement: Leadership is over-glorified. It is really the first follower that transforms the &amp;ldquo;Lone Nut&amp;rdquo; into a leader. Ursula Burns on Leading &amp;amp; Following There is a lot of times when I&amp;rsquo;m the leader, yet overall I follow a bit more. Leader is not a person. I expect every single person when called on, to step on and take charge.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-05-18-overkill/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 11:08:13 -0600</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-05-18-overkill/</guid><description>Overkill is the dust that settles on the stuff that took a lot of energy to build or buy, but turned out not to be necessary.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-04-30-buena_educacion/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 11:37:17 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-04-30-buena_educacion/</guid><description>Que es la buena educacion? Toda buena educación parte necesariamente del reconocimiento de que el hombre es una criatura caída—pero redimible</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-04-30-iphicrates/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 08:24:12 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-04-30-iphicrates/</guid><description>Iphicrates: Personal benefits have to be earned through personal action. Money gained without fighting should not be conferred directly on specific persons.
Also:
Coordination and organization is paramount. If any part of this body [army] was deficient, the army could not function to its potential. But if it lacked a “head” (i.e., a proper general), then it could be capable of nothing at all. Continuous innovation is necessary. Present a more formidable appearance than the enemy.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-04-28-ariadnes_thread/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Apr 2023 12:05:45 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-04-28-ariadnes_thread/</guid><description>Most people prefer to suffer with interpretations that give their world meaning than to relax in the cave without an Ariadne&amp;rsquo;s thread. &amp;ndash; David Riesman in &amp;ldquo;The Lonely Crowd&amp;rdquo;</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-04-27-bzuceni_mouchy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 23:10:12 +0200</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-04-27-bzuceni_mouchy/</guid><description>Sinuhet říkal: Tvoje řeč je bzučení mouchy v mých uších</description></item><item><title>AI and the Illusion of Intelligence</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-04-27-ai_and_the_illusion_of_intelligence/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-04-27-ai_and_the_illusion_of_intelligence/</guid><description>src
Week 1 Some Curious Experiments In early 1600 William Harvey examined the heart and understood it&amp;rsquo;s a pump. A few years after Rene Descartes this concluded that machines cannot think - arrange it&amp;rsquo;s speech so it makes sense - what even the lowest type of man can do. Alan Turing and the Imitation Game Illusion of Intelligence Explosion of Big Data Week 2 The Chomskyan Revolution Generative Gramar. Descarte&amp;rsquo;s Miracle The Fatal Flaw of the Chomskyan Revolution Doing Violence to Language: the Ngram Week 3 Moore&amp;rsquo;s Law Does Not Make the Singularity Likely in the film 2001, the main character was the computer HAL, solution to all the main (AI) challenges.</description></item><item><title>learnprompting.org</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-04-27-learnprompting.org/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-04-27-learnprompting.org/</guid><description>src
Basics Introduction Often AIs are like very smart 5-years old. They can do a lot of things, but need careful instructions to do them well. AI can automate tasks that cost you countless hours now. Prompting Giving Instructions Role Prompting Assign a role to a the AI. E.g.: &amp;ldquo;You&amp;rsquo;re a lawyer&amp;rdquo;. Awesome ChatGPT prompts Few shot prompting shot: result shot: result shot: other_result shot Present sample, present expected output, let it do more.</description></item><item><title>Satsang Swami TV</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-04-09-satsang_swami_tv/</link><pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-04-09-satsang_swami_tv/</guid><description>src
Understanding is action only. Follow-by actions means effort only. You understand and act, that simple it is. That is how understanding operates. You know the movement of your mind. Mind is the object. Don&amp;rsquo;t make it a subject. If you make the mind subject: one part of the mind knows the other part of the mind. But then who knows that one part is known by the other? The witness, the true self.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/just_the_two_of_us/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 08:13:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/just_the_two_of_us/</guid><description>Ideal team size is two</description></item><item><title>Science</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-03-10-science/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-03-10-science/</guid><description>What does &amp;ldquo;science&amp;rdquo; actually mean? What does it encompass?
Slavic Slovak or Czech word &amp;ldquo;veda&amp;rdquo; refers to the ancient Vedas. These are the holy scriptures of ancient India. The name probably means &amp;ldquo;giving (da) knowledge (ve)&amp;rdquo;. The Vedas consist of two parts. The first is about the worldly knowledge and the later part (Upanishads) are about the sacred knowledge of the non-changing God.
The original meaning refers to the compendium of knowledge known as Vedas.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/simplest_thing/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 18:19:27 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/simplest_thing/</guid><description>The simplest thing that could possibly work.</description></item><item><title>Dhamma Padam</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-02-20-dhamma_padam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-02-20-dhamma_padam/</guid><description>01 src
Buddha was a upanishadah. Buddha&amp;rsquo;s fear: people will go after speculative religious practices by giving up the search for the truth. Swami Vivekananda: Buddha was a great vedantist. Shankara was a hidden buddhist. Swami TV: Buddha is an open buddhist. Buddha dismissed cast and gender distinctions. All are human being. That was most unpalatable for the orthodox ritualists. When you hate something, you invent (folklore) stories. Human society wants a villain.</description></item><item><title>Janaka and Ashtavakra</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-02-02-janaka_and_ashtavakra/</link><pubDate>Thu, 02 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-02-02-janaka_and_ashtavakra/</guid><description>Swami Sarvapriyananda presents two stories about King Janaka and Sage Ashtavakra. He explains that while both dreams and waking experiences are not true, the experiencer (the consciousness) is always there. He states that neither the dream nor the experience is the truth, but rather the experiencer is the truth.
That is not true. Dream is not true. But did you experience it? So you the experiencer was there. This is also not true.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-01-28-freedom_vs._centralization/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-01-28-freedom_vs._centralization/</guid><description>Freedom of speech can provide enough feedback for a system to be continually improved, thus enabling it to outdo rigid, centralized state models.</description></item><item><title>Review whole codebase easily</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-26-review_whole_codebase/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-26-review_whole_codebase/</guid><description>Recently, a student asked me to review a small project hosted on GitHub. Initially, I assumed I would use the Pull Request/Code Review functionality of GitHub to do so. I found an easy way to perform it on the whole codebase.
However, I eventually decided that I wanted to have a broader view, rather than just looking at a small portion of the changes through the Code Review&amp;rsquo;s microscope. Utilizing an IDE that could visualize the connections in the code and show how things were being used and defined also helped me a lot.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-01-23-historia_sa_rymuje/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2023-01-23-historia_sa_rymuje/</guid><description>Mr.Tomas 19:35 23.01.2023 @ armadninoviny.cz
Maďarsko a Turecko sú dnes posledné krajiny ktoré neschválili vstup Švédska a Fínska do NATO.
V 15. storočí Turci obliehali byzantský Konštantínopol. Svoje služby vtedy Byzantíncom ponúkol maďarský zbrojár a odlievač kovu. Ponúkol im, že vytvorí delo aké svet nevidel. Byzantský cisár si však nemohli dovoliť sumu ktorú požadoval. Svoje služby tak ponúkol ich nepriateľom- Turkom. Pre sultána vytvoril vyše 8 metrov dlhé delo vrhajúce pol tonové kamenné gule, ktoré malo najväčší podiel na prelomení konštantínopolských hradieb a páde Byzancie.</description></item><item><title>Questions vol. 1</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-23-questions_vol._1/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-23-questions_vol._1/</guid><description>An ode to logic.
Difference between knowing and believing? Knowing is based on experience, examination and effort in general. Contrary to this, believing is based on, well, belief. Belief is blind, it is indoctrination, it is cheap.
Interestingly belief is connected to emotions. So when it is attacked, it is defended emotionally. Knowledge doesn&amp;rsquo;t need to be defended. It&amp;rsquo;s validity doesn&amp;rsquo;t rely on wishful thinking.
What is reality? What does &amp;ldquo;real&amp;rdquo; mean?</description></item><item><title>Slobodná vôľa</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-06-slobodna_vola/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-06-slobodna_vola/</guid><description>Existuje, či neexistuje? Čo to vlastne je?
Slobodná vôľa hovorí, že agent, napr. človek sa môže slobodne rozhodnúť. Teda, že nie je determinovaný, ale sám sebe pánom svojho osudu. Na základe čoho si ale vyberá?
Existuje? Aby slobodná vôľa existovala musí platiť, že pri rozhodovaní v presne tej situácii, sa NE-rozhodneme presne rovnako. Lebo ináč by platilo, že voľba je podmienená situáciou a nie v rukách agentom. Situáciou chápem celý stav vesmíru.</description></item><item><title>pra-vda: Reflexia inšpirovaná Murlim</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-03-pravda/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-03-pravda/</guid><description>Pravda Čo je pravda? Aby niečo mohlo byť pravdou, nesmie sa to meniť. Ináč by to po zmene prestalo byť pravdou. Takže pravda je to, čo je stále tým istým.
Vnímanie Ako funguje vnímanie? Vnímame na základe rozdielu. Vnímame iba veci premenlivé. Nemôžem vnímať veci konštantné, pretože by sme sme stratili rozdiel medzi teraz a vtedy/potom a tu a tam. Všetko by to bolo jedno.
Hľadanie pravdy Čo je aktivita? Aktivitou sa snažím docieliť niečoho.</description></item><item><title>CS50 React Native</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-11-09-cs50_react_native/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-11-09-cs50_react_native/</guid><description>Youtube
Lecture 0: JS slides
Introduction Course information Syntax Types dynamic types primitive types (no methods, immutable) undefined null boolean number string (symbol) objects Typecasting explicit implicit == (coerces the types) vs === (requires equivalent types) falsy undefined null false +0, -0, NaN &amp;quot;&amp;quot; truthy {} [] everything else Type demo typeof operator Objects const o = new Object() OR const o2 = {}; o2.firstName = '' OR const o3 = { firstName: '', greet(): function() {} } Arrays, Functions - are objects Everything but primitive datatypes are objects Anything between [] when indexing will be coerced to a string.</description></item><item><title>Upadesa Saram</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-10-21-upadesa_saram/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-10-21-upadesa_saram/</guid><description>src
40 - Verse 10 4 ways of spirituality: karma, bhakti, yoga, jnana. Temple provides facility for all of these. People do all four. Nothing happens, because the mind is compulsive - hyperactive. Karma becomes mechanical, jnana becomes ideation, bhakti becomes a show - you&amp;rsquo;ll need outer symbols of love. Yoga - should be conscious, lose the eyes, be aware of every single movement the body is doing. How to feel brahman?</description></item><item><title>CS50's Introduction to Artificial Intelligence with Python</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-10-17-harvardx_cs50ai/</link><pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-10-17-harvardx_cs50ai/</guid><description>src
Search general pattern:
begin correct sequence of actions goal agent - perceives the environment and acts upon the environment
state - configuration of the environment
initial state
actions - choices taken in any given state. fuctions. ACTIONS(s) -&amp;gt; set of actions that can be done in given state.
transition model. RESULT(s, a) -&amp;gt; state after performing action a in state s
state space. graph
goal state. determines whether a state is a goal state.</description></item><item><title>Nididdhyasanam</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-10-05-nididdhyasanam/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-10-05-nididdhyasanam/</guid><description>As long as this &amp;ldquo;how&amp;rdquo; is with you, you&amp;rsquo;ll not understand what is meditation. It is not a process, not a technique, not a method. You&amp;rsquo;ve to drop the question &amp;ldquo;how to meditate?&amp;rdquo; and ask &amp;ldquo;what is meditation?&amp;rdquo;. Going to a dark room, isolating from the world around you, family, daily life. And you self-enclose yourself in a movement of the mind determined by the (dvaita) school of meditation you attend.</description></item><item><title>Karma Yoga</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-09-30-karma_yoga/</link><pubDate>Fri, 30 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-09-30-karma_yoga/</guid><description>source
When Gita was started, there was dharma, not religions. In the context of a dharmic civilization worship of Ishvara is called karma. 500 CE something like religious ID started. Before there Christ&amp;rsquo;s teaching were there. Action is different than work. All natures works. Only humans act. Action is work performed by a human being with a motive. Vivekananda. Humans are slaves. They don&amp;rsquo;t work like masters. They are slaves to the motives behind their acts.</description></item><item><title>Bhagavad Gita Chapter 6</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-09-21-bhagavad_gita_chapter_6/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-09-21-bhagavad_gita_chapter_6/</guid><description>Class 1 The self is as it is not as it is imagined. The self remains veiled by the vasanas. And it reveals itself when there are no vasanas. That is called self-realization that leads to moksha. Desirelessness is godliness. A brashtah is one who doesn&amp;rsquo;t stay on the course. The loss is not total. Whatever ground you&amp;rsquo;ve gained, you&amp;rsquo;ll not lose it. All worldly accomplishments (wealth, power, knowledge) will be lost.</description></item><item><title>Bhakta &amp; Bhakti</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-09-19-bhakta__bhakti/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-09-19-bhakta__bhakti/</guid><description>playlist
Part 1, 2 Teaching from the Gita is more practical as that of Upanishad. Closer to the ordinary life. The body is the chariot. Arjuna is the master of the chariot. You&amp;rsquo;re Arjuna. Be clean. Be frank. Be like an open book. One who&amp;rsquo;s like that is Arjuna. No crookedness, no crafty-ness, innocence. The tree is called Arjuna because it soars straight into the sky. If you keep a distance between you and the teaching, you&amp;rsquo;ll be quoting Gita, not living Gita.</description></item><item><title>Drig Drishya Viveka</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-09-09-drig_drishya_viveka/</link><pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-09-09-drig_drishya_viveka/</guid><description>Satsang 2022-09-02 the same vision, depth, as an Upanishad. If you have already studied Vedanta it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to have an open mind. What can I teach you? You already know. Listen without judging, with open mind, that&amp;rsquo;s meditation. It&amp;rsquo;s up to you to take all this to the level of meditation. If you live a life of karma yoga you&amp;rsquo;re already a liberated soul. You see the snake instead of a garment because you&amp;rsquo;re insecure.</description></item><item><title>Upadesha Sahasri - Chapter 19</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-04-27-upadesha_sahasri/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-04-27-upadesha_sahasri/</guid><description>Class 1 Upadesha is instruction. In jnanam there is only instruction, no handing over. Like there is in religion - handing over a mantra. The one instructing you can call instructor. You need not instruct nobody to go to a physician when he&amp;rsquo;s ill. But when the psyche is ill, nobody will even acknowledge that he&amp;rsquo;s sick. And when somebody points out that you&amp;rsquo;re sick in the mind, you become angry.</description></item><item><title/><link>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2022-04-25-systems_de-engineering/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/micro/2022-04-25-systems_de-engineering/</guid><description>https://meduza.io/feature/2022/04/24/ukraintsev-v-mire-vstrechayut-kak-bogov-spustivshihsya-na-zemlyu Byť autentický a rezonovať so prostredím. Nebyť len ambiciózny &amp;ldquo;remeselník&amp;rdquo;. Naše povedomie je uspôsobené na boj so divokými šelmami. Potrebujeme skúšky, vzostupy a pády. Námahu. Potom sa cítim normálne. Nemôžeme jazdiť na F1 na odpadky. Sú ľudia, čo sa cítia uzemnený, len ak majú vážne výzvy. Ináč sa strašne nudia. Ja som vo vojne vo svojom živle. Chápem mieru zodpovednosti. Bojový duch sa udržuje automaticky keď ľudia počujú pravdu.</description></item><item><title>Remote</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-04-24-remote/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-04-24-remote/</guid><description>The Time Is Right for Remote Work Office during the day has become the last place where people get their work done. Required: ability to be alone with your thoughts. Stop commuting your life away - commutes make you fat, stressed and miserable. Escaping 9am-5pm: synchronous -&amp;gt; asynchronous End of city monopoly Industrialism (factories): gather a large number of people into small area. life need not be divided into arbitrary phases: work and retirement Talent isn&amp;rsquo;t bound by the hubs It&amp;rsquo;s not about the money - promote quality of life, getting best people available Dealing with Excuses If you&amp;rsquo;re struggling with trust issues, you&amp;rsquo;ve made a poor hiring decision.</description></item><item><title>It doesn't have to be crazy at work</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-03-29-it_doesnt_have_to_be_crazy_at_work/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-03-29-it_doesnt_have_to_be_crazy_at_work/</guid><description>Here are some notes from the marvelous book &amp;ldquo;It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be crazy at work&amp;rdquo;. If you like the notes, please consider buying the book.
First It&amp;rsquo;s Crazy at Work Workday is being sliced into tiny moments by an onslaught of distractions. Unhealthy obsession with growth. Sustained exhaustion is not a badge of honor, it&amp;rsquo;s a mark of stupidity. The answer isn&amp;rsquo;t more hours, it&amp;rsquo;s less bullshit. Less waste, not more production.</description></item><item><title>Sanskrit a Slovenčina</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-03-26-sask/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-03-26-sask/</guid><description>Viac tu.</description></item><item><title>Vaakya Vritti</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-08-08-vaakya_vritti/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-08-08-vaakya_vritti/</guid><description>Satsang 2021-08-03 The right way to listen to a speaker is to set aside your knowledge. Knowledge - accumulation. You neither agree nor disagree with the speaker. The idea is to think about it and that is how we learn Most of meditations can be classified as fancy or imaginations. Sometimes this fancy or imaginations acquires a status of tradition. Law of repetition: whenever there is repetition it is bound to become a cult.</description></item><item><title>Kashi Pancakam</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-07-07-kashi_pancakam/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-07-07-kashi_pancakam/</guid><description>Class 1 Small prakarana by Shankaracarya pravaha - flow, activity, current. When it comes to knowledge, there no division between east and west. Nature of work is grow, until it occupies all free time you have. It is the means that shapes the end. You won&amp;rsquo;t get the end independent of the means If bhakti is separates from philosophy, it becomes superstitious. Religion loses its transforming power. Society comes into focus, not individual liberation.</description></item><item><title>Isavasyam Idam Sarvam</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-06-28-isavasyam_idam_sarvam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-06-28-isavasyam_idam_sarvam/</guid><description>Class 1 Message of hindu dharma to the entire humanity can be summarised by this single verse. IshAvAsyaM idaM sarvaM - all this is pervaded by God. anta - essence, end. Vedanta - essence of Veda. Essence comes at the end, just like dessert. pramA - correct knowledge, correct understanding. Vedanta - means of knowledge. Veda is a body of knowledge, collections of words that help us to know. Thus it is a means of knowledge.</description></item><item><title>Bhagavatam: Kapila devahuti samvadam</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-06-12-bhagavatam/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-06-12-bhagavatam/</guid><description>Recorded in August 2008 in Canada.
Class 1 Yoga: communion with God means god consciousness. Because it is like communion with space. It means you feel the presence of Ishwara at all times, everywhere. kamukha = lover, horny All manifestation is in the form of opposites. You cannot have a world without contradiction. You cannot have any manifestation without the dharma adharma opposites. If a person is pursuing sukha trying to avoid dukha, he is not trying to transcend.</description></item><item><title>Sivananda Lahari by Swami TV</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-06-03-sivananda_lahari_by_swami_tv/</link><pubDate>Thu, 03 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-06-03-sivananda_lahari_by_swami_tv/</guid><description>source
Mind is a movement. It has to flow either towards samsara or towards Ishvara. There is no 3rd flow. As it contemplates upon Ishvara there is a reasonless joy. Mind becomes what it things upon. When mind contemplates upon Shiva that is enough to bring out inherent joy as wave after wave. Bhakti is an emotion. It is not knowledge, it is emotion. It prepares the mind for higher knowledge by purifying.</description></item><item><title>Narayana Suktam</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-06-01-narayana_suktam/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-06-01-narayana_suktam/</guid><description>source
deva - shining. The one light that is always shining: consciousness. Happiness flowing from (coffee) cup into heart -&amp;gt; revert. By conditioning gold as neckless you have not made its value lesser. Gold is the origin of necklace and gold abides in the necklace. Existence has an opposite - non existence. Being has none. Being is the foundation of the entire universe. Being is atma, the essence of entire universe of forms.</description></item><item><title>Do not let anyone overpay you</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-22-do_not_let_anyone_overpay_you/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-22-do_not_let_anyone_overpay_you/</guid><description>source
The moment one customer pays you a lot more than any other customer, you&amp;rsquo;re no longer a product but a consulting company working for the big payers. You&amp;rsquo;ll do what they say. Self-sufficient. We would never allow a customer to pay more than top-tier price. If you&amp;rsquo;re a bit company with special demands, we don&amp;rsquo;t want your money. We wanted to build a self-service software company. Not need an army of key account managers keeping the whales happy.</description></item><item><title>Amor veneno</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-21-amor_veneno/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-21-amor_veneno/</guid><description>Dealema, álbum: Arvorada da Alma.
source
Depois da tempestade vem a bonança
Depois da calamidade vem a esperança
Como a fénix, renascemos das cinzas com a arte de viver
Depois de um expresso que navegou o submundo
Depois da noite escura da alma e da grande tribulação
Acordamos para a primavera da vida
E através das trevas chegamos sem tempo nem hora marcada
À alvorada da alma
Ainda não partiste e eu já tenho saudades</description></item><item><title>Brahmasutras (1-4)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-17-brahmasutras/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-17-brahmasutras/</guid><description>notes, summary
01 INTRODUCTION Sutra - small statement with lot of ideas packed in it. Aphorism. Audio/oral tradition, not visual. Writing was not there and even when it came, it was not used very much. A huge book can be compressed into few sutras which are memorized. Sutra method has been devised because of memory. Sutra method - putting all the ideas in metrical verse form. Poetry form. It is easier to remember a verse form.</description></item><item><title>Sivananda Lahari</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-08-shivananda_lahari/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-08-shivananda_lahari/</guid><description>source
Snl-01 = Introduction Work which deals with Siva-bhakti. Devotion is nothing but love devoted to something higher, nobler, sacred. E.g. lord, guru, parents, desha (janma bhumi). Love towards a child is called vAtsalya (affection). We have got three stages from the standpoint of devata: Ekarupa bhakti. When the Lord is presented as a person, devotee can have a relationship. Good for maturity. Every person requires a trustworthy, reliable, stable and permanent relationship.</description></item><item><title>Odyssey (1997)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-03-odyssey/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-03-odyssey/</guid><description>I&amp;rsquo;ll be alive like this tree around which we&amp;rsquo;ve built this world. Is there a way to avoid this war? Troy will not fall so gently. Turn Troy to dust. Return with the spoils of enemies you&amp;rsquo;ve slain and my heart will rejoice. The gods of sea and sky carried me towards Troy. The walls of Troy reach to the clouds. I did not want you to escape this journey.</description></item><item><title>Clean Code</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-02-clean_code/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-02-clean_code/</guid><description>NOTE: TOC and these notes do not strictly correspond to the order used in the book itself.
Clean Code Code is really the language in which we ultimately express the requirements. It is unprofessional for programmers to bend to the will of managers who don&amp;rsquo;t understand the risks of making messes. We are authors. Ratio of time spent reading vs. writing is well over 10:1. Making it easy to read actually makes it easier to write.</description></item><item><title>Dakshinamurti Stotra</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-03-25-dakshinamurti_stotra/</link><pubDate>Thu, 25 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-03-25-dakshinamurti_stotra/</guid><description>Summary,
Text and translation,
BGUSA/dakshinamurti
Table of contents:
TOC {:toc} DMS-01 = Introduction Dakshinamurti as an aspect of Lord Shiva as brahmavidya guru. Same as Hayagriva in vaishnava sampradaya. Another name for Lord Shiva as Dakshinamurti is Sadashiva. Shiva is the laya karta, one who resolves the universe, the dvaita prapanca. That destruction is relative, not ultimate destruction, because during pralaya the duality goes only to unmanifested condition. Duality and samsara very much remain.</description></item><item><title>Prusa Link Architecture</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-03-01-prusa_link_architecture/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-03-01-prusa_link_architecture/</guid><description>Main Driver parse CLI args setup logging instantiate main class and run logging log = logging.getLogger(__name__) # -l on CLI for setting debug levels for module, level in log_levels: logging.getLogger(module).setLevel(level) config Uses extendparser in config.py
MVC MainClass.__init__(config) as Controller:
instantiate Model instantiate components in proper order bind signals start threads There is MainClass.stop() for controlled shutdown.
signals Uses blinker module. Usage: signal.connect(handler).</description></item><item><title>Kubernetes</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-02-22-kubernetes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-02-22-kubernetes/</guid><description>source
Install and Deploy install kubectl install minikube Commands:
minikube start minikube status kubectl get node kubectl get pods kubectl create deployment hello-minikube --image=k8s.gcr.io/echoserver:1.4 kubectl expose deployment hello-minikube --type=NodePort --port=8080 minikube service hello-minikube --url curl http://192.168.49.2:31223 kubectl delete deployments.apps hello-minikube minikube pause minikube unpause minikube stop Namespaces for organization and resource separation kubectl --namespace=mystuff or kubectl -n=mystuff kubectl --all-namespaces Default namespaces for new clusters:
$ kubectl get ns NAME STATUS AGE default Active 13m # k8s resources are crated here by default kube-node-lease Active 13m # storage for node lease information kube-public Active 13m # world-readable kube-system Active 13m # infrastructure pods Commands:</description></item><item><title>Rudram</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-01-18-rudram/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-01-18-rudram/</guid><description>Summary
SA/EN anuvAka 1 - 11
Class 1 (2021-01-16) Primary aspect of Rg Veda is upasana. Mental worship. In Yajur Veda focus is karma. Veda is divided into samhita (collection of mantras, hymns) and brahmana, which is dos and donts, rituals. Brahmana is subdivided into 1) brahmana 2) aranjaka 3) last portion is upanishad. We&amp;rsquo;re all devotes of supreme will. Rshih - the one who sees the truth. In Vedic times the vedic seers worshiped the same supreme will in the form of natural forces.</description></item><item><title>SvetAshvatara Upanishad</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-01-16-svetaashvataraupanishad/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-01-16-svetaashvataraupanishad/</guid><description>Summary
Svetasvatara_Upanishad SA-EN 1949
Class 1: 1 / 1, 2 Compilation, thus not a systematic teaching, yet covers all the important vedantic ideas.
Highlights isvara jnanam as the only means of moksha. Purna isvara jnanam - both saguna and nirguna version.
Svetaashvataraupanishad: you can attain moksha through other methods other than jnanam if you fulfill this condition: you&amp;rsquo;ve to roll the sky from one side to the other just like a carpet and present it to god, god will give moksha without jnanam.</description></item><item><title>Vivekacudamani Meditations</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-11-20-vivekachudamani_meditations/</link><pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-11-20-vivekachudamani_meditations/</guid><description>[Previous Vivekacudamani classes]({% post_url 2020-07-26-vivekachudamani_sp_2020 %})
40 meditation verses, Vivekacudamani translation
Class 1: Introduction niddhhai - deep meditation An informed seeker rejects moksha, artha, kama and goes for the only permanent goal - moksha. What is permanent (nityam) must be available in all three periods in time. If it is available in present, it must be already accomplished (siddhah). Moksha is always already accomplished fact - it can never be a goal to be accomplished in the future (sadhyah).</description></item><item><title>Preciso Me Encontrar</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-11-07-preciso_me_encontrar/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-11-07-preciso_me_encontrar/</guid><description>by Cartola
Deixe-me ir
Nechaj ma ísť
Preciso andar
Potrebujem ísť
Vou por aí a procurar
Idem hľadať
Rir pra não chorar
Smiať sa aby som neplakal
Deixe-me ir
Preciso andar
Vou por aí a procurar
Rir pra não chorar
Quero assistir ao Sol nascer
Chcem pozerať ako sa slnko narodí
Ver as águas dos rios correr
Vidieť vody riek tiecť
Ouvir os pássaros cantar
Počuť vtáči spev
Eu quero nascer</description></item><item><title>Ready Player One</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-10-17-ready_player_one/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-10-17-ready_player_one/</guid><description>The year is 2045 and the reality sucks so much that practically all humanity spends most of its time in a virtual reality called OASIS. Recently its Author has passed away and he&amp;rsquo;s offered his position including the ownership of OASIS to anybody who masters his three challenges:
Win an unwinnable race. The key to this challenge is to drive backwards. Ask the Lady of the Author to dance. Easy, isn&amp;rsquo;t it?</description></item><item><title>Pancadasi - Chapter 2</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-10-12-pancadasi_2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-10-12-pancadasi_2/</guid><description>source notes from vedantastudents.com Class 1: 1, 2 2nd chapter - Mahabhuta viveka. Between elements, elementals and Atma. This world, before it was created, was sat alone. sat eva somya idam agra asit ekam eva advitiyam (Chandogya). It is difficult to see the all-pervasivnes of consciousness and ananda because it gets not manifested everywhere. That&amp;rsquo;s why here sat that is obvious everywhere is discussed. Consciousness is the invariable factor in all the experiences of all the three states and therefore consciousness is sat and beyond time.</description></item><item><title>Pancadasi - Chapter 1</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-08-02-pancadasi_1/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-08-02-pancadasi_1/</guid><description>source
01: Introduction Like nobody can take your medicine, nobody but you can help you with moksha. Artha, kama, dharma one cat get through a proxy. Not moksha. First three can be attained by karma. Moksha only through jnanam. Everything in the three periods of time but you exists conditionally. Three obstacles: 1) lack of preparedness 2) obstacle pertaining to the interpretation of the sastra itself (different schools) 3) logical problems.</description></item><item><title>Vivekachudamani Swami Paramarthananda 2020</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-07-26-vivekachudamani_sp_2020/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-07-26-vivekachudamani_sp_2020/</guid><description>Selected 108 Verses
Summary of first 64 Verses
Class 14: 31, 32 &amp;hellip; What is anAtmA? sat na bhavati, asat na bhavati, ubhayAtmikA na bhavati:
Maya and its product do not commander category of existent entity. But you cannot say opposite. Anirvachaynia - seemingly existent, Experientially available. On probing mysterious. Like dream world. You cannot say existent or non-existent. When we are in dream the dream world comes into &amp;ldquo;existent&amp;rdquo; category.</description></item><item><title>Rework</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-07-05-rework/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-07-05-rework/</guid><description>by Jason Fried.
Takedown Ignore the real world The real world isn&amp;rsquo;t a place, it&amp;rsquo;s an excuse. It&amp;rsquo;s a justification for not trying. It has nothing to do with you.
Learning from mistakes is overrated Failure is not a prerequisite for success.
People who failed have the same amount of success as people who have never tried at all.
Long term business planing is fantasy.
Start referring to any of your plans as guesses.</description></item><item><title>Prahlada Charitra - Swami TV</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-06-01-prahlada_charitra/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-06-01-prahlada_charitra/</guid><description>Recorded in September 2012, source.
1: imagination vs. acceptance, mechanical vs. wonder(full) Your attachment to the name and form acts like a shield to cover up the reality. Even while seeing the name and form you see through the name and form and then you&amp;rsquo;re in communion with reality. You&amp;rsquo;re awareness of the waking state. Not the world and person that shines through it. Samsara is put in place by identification with the gunas because of ignorance.</description></item><item><title>Saddarshanam - Swami TV</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-05-08-saddarshanam/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-05-08-saddarshanam/</guid><description>source classes
source satsang
1 &amp;amp; 2: Seeing. Exploration vs. Accumulation Outward simplicity with inward fragmentary thinking (caste, creed, lingam&amp;hellip;) -&amp;gt; obstacle to the truth. If mind is the origin, it isn&amp;rsquo;t truth, only concept/idea. Products of the hand (objects) and of the mind (ideas) have taken over our reality. Give up all of those. (3) Always open, always learning, no conclusion. Conclusion means the truth is truncated, no longer infinite.</description></item><item><title>The Pragmatic Programmer</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-03-16-the_pragmatic_programmer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-03-16-the_pragmatic_programmer/</guid><description>From Journeyman to Master
Preface core process: taking a requirement and producing working, maintainable code that delights the user. QWAN - quality without a name. Don&amp;rsquo;t preach, just tell/do what works. pragmatic -&amp;gt; lat. (pragmaticus) -&amp;gt; greek &amp;ldquo;to do&amp;rdquo;. There are no easy answers There is no such thing as best solution, tool language or OS. You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be weeded to any particular technology but have broad enough background and experience base to allow to choose good solution in any particular situation.</description></item><item><title>Sinfonia Agridoce</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-03-01-sinfonia_agridoce/</link><pubDate>Sun, 01 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-03-01-sinfonia_agridoce/</guid><description>text (PT) by Dealema:
Eu quero chegar &amp;hellip; onde ninguém chegou
Quero-me encontrar &amp;hellip; ser quem no fundo eu sei que eu sou
Nesta estrada a direção certa é em linha reta
Mas na encruzilhada qual a opção correta?
Não é fácil a decisão na bifurcação
Transversais e paralelas, eu sou um milhão
S&amp;rsquo;esta vida não fosse uma sinfonia agridoce
E a inocência não voasse depois dos doze
Numa viagem na montanha russa de emoções</description></item><item><title>Bhagavad Gita Chapter 4</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-02-14-bhagavad_gita_chapter_4/</link><pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-02-14-bhagavad_gita_chapter_4/</guid><description>Notes from classes at Arsha Vidya Gurukulam.
Bhagavad Gita Chapter 4 Verse 41 discovery, intelligence vs. machinery of knowledge
Part 1 samsara = worldliness = bondage cognitive knowledge &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; accumulated knowledge (intellect - in braincells) &amp;lt;-&amp;gt; jnanam as satyam jnanam anantam brahman (intelligence; all-pervading truth). All are called jnanam even though different in nature. Intelligence is not limited to the braincells only. In is in the braincells but not of the braincells.</description></item><item><title>The Edge</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-02-02-the_edge/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-02-02-the_edge/</guid><description>Formidable Vegetable: The Edge
Some people tell me that I&amp;rsquo;m crazy
&amp;lsquo;cos I do things that don&amp;rsquo;t fit in
with rest of society.
Like my love of small places
my room ain&amp;rsquo;t too large
in fact it&amp;rsquo;s a box
underneath the house
of the corner of my garage.
But the edge is where it&amp;rsquo;s at
and it&amp;rsquo;s easy to create
and my mama always said
if you&amp;rsquo;re not living on the edge</description></item><item><title>American Beauty (1999)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-01-25-american_beauty/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-01-25-american_beauty/</guid><description>Initial song name from OST: Dead already
I&amp;rsquo;ve lost something. I&amp;rsquo;m not exactly sure what it is but I know didn&amp;rsquo;t always feel this sedated. But you know what? It&amp;rsquo;s never too late to get it back.
It&amp;rsquo;s the weirdest thing. I feel like I&amp;rsquo;ve been in a coma for about 20 years and I&amp;rsquo;m just now waking up.
&amp;hellip; retiring to the men&amp;rsquo;s room so I can jerk off while I fantasize about a life that doesn&amp;rsquo;t so closely remember hell.</description></item><item><title>Questions with Swamiji (TV)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-29-questions_with_swamiji_tv/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-29-questions_with_swamiji_tv/</guid><description>link
Goal: knowledge. Quality: simplicity. Have self-confidence. Be punctual, it shows you are earnest about it. Life is relationships. Try to enrich every relationship with love. Don&amp;rsquo;t put reciprocity, expectations in place. Seek love which is God. Seek freedom (psychological freedom from expectations, from seeking advantage) so you can discover that love. Love is unity in diversity. If diversity is real, there is no love. In non-duality the truth is one but appears as many.</description></item><item><title>Fight Club (1999)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-14-fight_club/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-14-fight_club/</guid><description>Losing all hope is freedom. Illusion of safety. Without pain, without sacrifice, we would have nothing. It&amp;rsquo;s only after we&amp;rsquo;ve lost everything that we&amp;rsquo;re free to do anything. Advertising has chasing us cars and clothes. Working jobs we hate so we can buy shit we don&amp;rsquo;t need. Our Great War is a spiritual war, our Great Depression is our lives. Stop trying to control everything and just let go. Condom is the glass slipper of our generation.</description></item><item><title>Testing Python</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-13-python__testing/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-13-python__testing/</guid><description>Chapter 1 Writing code without tests in general is going to lead to problems down the line. Choreographing One of the worst traps a developer can fall into is writing a bunch of code and then going back and testing it all at the end. With the advent of social networks and the ever-increasing pressure of media attention, defects in your code could be costly to both you and your reputation or that of any company you may represent.</description></item><item><title>Carlos Castaneda: 3. Cesta do Ixtlanu</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-02-castaneda/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-02-castaneda/</guid><description>1 - Pritakanie sveta okolo nás nahnať strach synovi (dať mu lekciu) musí niekto iný ako otec, ktorý ho má ochraňovať (Iron John: kráľovi muži). od malička sa učíme popisu sveta, až si ho osvojíme a v ňom žijeme (matrix) a stratíme pojem o čare reality. rád hodne chodím. mentor: budeš mi platiť za môj čas tvojím časom. nikdy nič nepije, ani pivo. pre všetko, čo robíme, je nezbytná iba jedna vec - Duch!</description></item><item><title>Yoga Vasistha - Swami TV</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-11-29-yoga_vasistha_sara_-_swami_tv/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-11-29-yoga_vasistha_sara_-_swami_tv/</guid><description>Source (search for &amp;ldquo;Vasistha&amp;rdquo;). Recordings are from the end of 2011.
Class 1 considered highest text of Vedanta. Something like Mandukya. Generally not taught to beginners. requires an open mind. When you have an open mind, you will not be there. Only the faculty of cognition will be there. If you are a person, then you are not open. Keep aside satyatvabuddhi about the world - an agenda in the world and dehAbhimAna Pot is vAcAramabhaNaM - born from speech -&amp;gt; mind -&amp;gt; nama (mouth), rupa (mind).</description></item><item><title>Upadesha Sahasri - Swami TV</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-11-19-swami_tv_-_upadesha_sahasri/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-11-19-swami_tv_-_upadesha_sahasri/</guid><description>Upadesha Sahasri (2019) Talks by Swami Tattvavidananda Saraswati
Class 1, 2 Life - infinite, vast, mystery, not just an occupation. Family people, society believes life means securing livelihood. Thinking like this we miss the whole point of life. The same life in you is in a bird, sun, stars, rivers, everywhere. Hiranyagarbha. Job, marry, children and become more and more like a machine. Example: wet grinder. Remain fearful, anxious, afraid of life and death.</description></item><item><title>Ashtavakra Gita - Swami TV</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-11-02-ashtavakra_gita_-_swami_tv/</link><pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-11-02-ashtavakra_gita_-_swami_tv/</guid><description>Ashtavakra Gita - Swami Tattvavidananda
Class 1 Yoga, gym&amp;hellip; Don&amp;rsquo;t neglect the body. Practical Vedanta with impact on life, not academical. Not sub-serving a system, method, formula. You can&amp;rsquo;t have both. No prioritization, just one goal. Intellect - tool for knowing - pair of tongs. Self-enquiry instead of self-knowledge. Tongs cannot catch themselves. You can only be yourself. Who are you? You are not looking for the answer but staying with the question.</description></item><item><title>Kingdom of God (2005)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-10-07-kingdom_of_god/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-10-07-kingdom_of_god/</guid><description>A king might move a man, a father may claim a son, but that man can also move himself, and only then does that man truly begin his own game. Remember that howsoever you are played or by whom, your soul is in your keeping alone, even though those who presume to play you be kings or men of power. When you stand before God, you cannot say, &amp;ldquo;But I was told by others to do thus,&amp;rdquo; or that virtue was not convenient at the time.</description></item><item><title>Carlos Castaneda (1, 2)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-09-15-castaneda/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-09-15-castaneda/</guid><description>Poznámky z prvých dvoch kníh od Carlosa Castanedu:
1. Učení Dona Juana &amp;hellip; u nekonečne dlhej cesty sa nedá pokúsiť o nič viac, ako nájsť jej začiatok a stanoviť jej smer. Predstieranie, že cesta je pochopená a dokončená, je prinajmenšom klamaním samého seba. Jednotlivý študent na nej môže dosiahnuť dokonalosti iba v subjektívnom slova zmysle a vyprávať o nej môže iba tak, že povie všetko, čo bol schopný zhliadnuť. &amp;ndash; Georg Simmel</description></item><item><title>Zorba the Greek (1964)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-09-14-zorba_the_greek/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-09-14-zorba_the_greek/</guid><description>I went for it all. Wife, house, children. The full catastrophe.
Life is trouble. To be alive is to undo your belt and look for trouble.
Good or bad, what is the difference? They all end up the same way.
A man needs a little madness or else he never dares to cut the rope and be free.
“This is true happiness: to have no ambition and to work like a horse as if you had every ambition.</description></item><item><title>Awareness: Wake Up to Life</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-09-03-de_mello_awareness/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-09-03-de_mello_awareness/</guid><description>Here is some notes from Anthony de Mello&amp;rsquo;s program Awareness: Wake Up To Life, New York, 1986.
CD 1 On waking up All mystics agree: all is well. If you don&amp;rsquo;t see it, you are asleep. People don&amp;rsquo;t want to be cured, they want relief. Cure (waking up) is painful. Wise guru will never attempt to wake people up. Will I be able to help you I don&amp;rsquo;t expect neither to help nor to damage you.</description></item><item><title>The Greatest Escape - Adventures in the History of Solitude</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-08-16-adventures_of_solitude/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-08-16-adventures_of_solitude/</guid><description>Highlights from the book The Greatest Escape: Adventures in the History of Solitude (c) 2004 by David Stimpson - a kind of a Bible and eulogy on Solitude and Silence.
Prologue life of solitude - either through periodic retreats or continuing inner solitude in society - may be the best answer to cries that modern world is inevitably a &amp;ldquo;lonely crowd.&amp;rdquo; your lonely quietude may be bothered by demons of lust, vainglory, or melancholy.</description></item><item><title>About</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/about/</guid><description>Hello I&amp;rsquo;m Martin Uzak and welcome to my blog!
In the micro section I share short ideas that caught my attention. Consider it something like my private twitter.
The next section is called blog. There I post longer articles. What mostly interests me at the time of writing is related vedantic philosophy or IT. Quite often you&amp;rsquo;ll find there a summary of some longer articles/classes/books. Here is a full list of the tags used.</description></item><item><title>Wikis</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/wikis/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/wikis/</guid><description> IT Vedanta Lang Cooking Body</description></item></channel></rss>