<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Boundaries on uzak.github.io</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/tags/boundaries/</link><description>Recent content in Boundaries on uzak.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://uzak.github.io/tags/boundaries/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Communication and Boundary Principles</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2025-10-25-communication_and_boundary_principles/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2025-10-25-communication_and_boundary_principles/</guid><description>Communication and Boundary Principles JADE Don&amp;rsquo;t Justify, Argue, Defend, or Explain The more you explain, the more ammunition you give manipulators DEAR MAN (Dialectic Behaviour Therapy) Describe the situation objectively Express your feelings/thoughts Assert what you want clearly Reinforce (explain positive effects of getting what you want) Stay Mindful (don&amp;rsquo;t get distracted) Appear Assertive (confident tone) Negotiate if needed The Broken Record Repeat your boundary calmly, like broken record Don&amp;rsquo;t vary your language, don&amp;rsquo;t elaborate &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m not available that day&amp;rdquo; -&amp;gt; &amp;ldquo;As I said, I&amp;rsquo;m not available&amp;rdquo; -&amp;gt; &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve answered this - I&amp;rsquo;m not available.</description></item><item><title>Boundary Setting Framework</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2025-10-22-boundary_setting_framework/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2025-10-22-boundary_setting_framework/</guid><description>STEP 1: Assess the situation What&amp;rsquo;s actually happening? What is the observable behaviour (not intent, just actions)? Is this a pattern or isolated incident? What tactics are they using (guilt, threats, triangulation, playing victim,&amp;hellip; )? What&amp;rsquo;s my objective? maintain this relationship? end this relationship? Do I want specific behaviour change? Am I trying to &amp;ldquo;win&amp;rdquo; or find resolution? What are the stakes? High stakes: family, partner, boss (can&amp;rsquo;t easily exit; strategic patience needed) Medium stakes: friends, coworkers, neighbours Low stakes: Acquaintances, service providers What&amp;rsquo;s their intent?</description></item><item><title>Nedra Glover Tawwab: Set Boundaries Find Peace</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2025-10-03-set_boundaries_find_peace/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2025-10-03-set_boundaries_find_peace/</guid><description>Preface people will not guess my needs. They went all about their day while I suffered in silence. I feared that standing up for myself would cost me my relationships. All the while, the personal cost was much higher Introduction Family systems have unspoken rules of engagement. If you want to feel guilty, set a limit within your family. It is not my job to save people. It is not my job to fix people.</description></item></channel></rss>