<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Movies on uzak.github.io</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/tags/movies/</link><description>Recent content in Movies on uzak.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://uzak.github.io/tags/movies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Odyssey (1997)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-03-odyssey/</link><pubDate>Sat, 03 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2021-04-03-odyssey/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>I&amp;rsquo;ll be alive like this tree around which we&amp;rsquo;ve built this world.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Is there a way to avoid this war?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Troy will not fall so gently.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Turn Troy to dust. Return with the spoils of enemies you&amp;rsquo;ve slain and my heart will rejoice.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The gods of sea and sky carried me towards Troy.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The walls of Troy reach to the clouds.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I did not want you to escape this journey. Because I want you to go. I want you, my brave Odysseus to defeat the Trojans.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Your destiny is to do battle, to become immortal. To have your name on the lips of endless generations.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Giant Polites. He&amp;rsquo;s stubborn beyond words.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Eyrolochus lies more than you. O: He&amp;rsquo;s the best blacksmith in all Greece.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Achilles hear me, it is I Hector, defender of Troy, who challenge you.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In the 7th year of blood, Achilles the god amongst man, was slain. Our hope was lost. Troy had taken the best of us and still remained locked.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mighty Priam, give me life and I&amp;rsquo;ll be your slave.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You see, you gods of sea and sky. I conquered Troy. Me, Odysseus! A mortal man of flesh and blood and bone and mind. I do not need you now. I can anything.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It was my serpent who silenced Lacoon, or your horse was doomed. Yet you refuse to give thanks. You will suffer for this offence. You suffer for this offence. For your arrogance, you will drift on my sea for eternity. Never again you&amp;rsquo;ll reach the shores of Ithaca. You will suffer.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>No one will stop me from seeing Ithaca.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He&amp;rsquo;s just a boy. He&amp;rsquo;s not ready for man&amp;rsquo;s work. A: Because you will not let him grow. P: It is my son, not yours. A: My son was ready for all things. P: Yes, your son had his father.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You must live for your son. You must raise a king.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The wine. We&amp;rsquo;ll trade it for water.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I&amp;rsquo;m the youngest, Polyphemes. What did you bring?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Take me next. Of course, if you do, you&amp;rsquo;ll eat all your magic inside my head.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>My name is nobody.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Your hear Poseidon? Odysseus is alive and you cannot stop me.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>O: Why are you helping me? A: because you&amp;rsquo;re the first mortal ever to use his mind. And you understand that there is always something to learn!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Polites: I don&amp;rsquo;t care. I want my share.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You betrayed me. You fools.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>She offered food and wine in her honeyed voice. The witch waved her hands and each one of our brothers was turned into an animal before our eyes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Careful, you&amp;rsquo;re about to lose your sword and you need it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Please cake care of my sword. H: I&amp;rsquo;m not allowed to touch.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You cannot refuse a goddess. Only then she will surrender your men.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The only way I will turn your soldier into man is if you take me into bed. Brave Odysseus. Are you still a man?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>But it is mine. If I&amp;rsquo;m old enough to keep my father&amp;rsquo;s flocks and kill his game, then I am old enough to use his bow. P: If you can string it. If you cannot, you&amp;rsquo;ll place it into your father&amp;rsquo;s treasury until I give it to you.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>P-&amp;gt;A: You&amp;rsquo;re my mother. You&amp;rsquo;re my father. You&amp;rsquo;re my strength.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You&amp;rsquo;ve given me much Circe, but no bare enough flesh could make me forget Penelope.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>O: No! You, open your eyes and you see who I am!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you still wish to go home, you must first enter the underworld. Only there you will find the answers you seek.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You must cross a river of fire and sacrifice a ram. And you must enter the fire.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>And what of my son? He&amp;rsquo;d be 15 by now and still without his father.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mother, men are in the hall. They say they&amp;rsquo;re here for you. Men who say my father is dead.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I will receive these men and that is all. They will have nothing that belongs to Odysseus. Not his fortunes, and not his wife.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The river of fire. Let me come with you. O: No. I must cross it myself.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>P: Your soul will burn away.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It is I, am lost.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stay back, this ram is not for you.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>T (blind prophet): You&amp;rsquo;re a clever man, Odysseus of Ithaca, but not a very wise one. You keep your eyes only on your home. Blinded, you do not see that it is the journey itself that makes up your life. Only when you understand this you will understand the meaning of wisdom. O: No, the wisdom, I will find alone. Help me find my way! T: &lt;strong>The answer has been before your eyes, every night at sea.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A (in the underworld): You must hurry. Men are trying to steal your world.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Men would stop at nothing to steal my kingdom.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I hope my father died a hero. If he&amp;rsquo;s alive, he&amp;rsquo;s forgotten me.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The day the gods gave you to us, they took your father from me. But he promised me, with you lying here in my arms, that he would return alive, as this tree around which we built our world, is alive. T: If he&amp;rsquo;s alive, why hasn&amp;rsquo;t he come? P: I know your father. He&amp;rsquo;s alive.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Guests leave when asked.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Alone, my men lost before my eyes. I float endlessly in Poseidon&amp;rsquo;s sea. Wondering when he&amp;rsquo;ll take my life.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>C: It is only a dream. O: No, it is real. My men, my brothers, they&amp;rsquo;re all lost.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Telemachus! What are you doing here in the dark (trying to string Odysseus&amp;rsquo; bow)?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I&amp;rsquo;m mentor. Keeper of the staff.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Give me a ship. I will sail from Ithaca and find my father.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>From a wild boar. I was 15. And my mother cried tears of happiness.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Don&amp;rsquo;t you see? No one leaves my island. And all that lives here exist to serve me&amp;hellip; Forget Ithaca. You&amp;rsquo;re home now.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do not worry. The gods are watching you with favour.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Remember. The gods will not do for man, what man must do for himself. You must make this journey.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For two more years, Calypso&amp;rsquo;s island was my prison. Forgotten by the outside world, abandoned by Athena. My hopes of reaching the Penelope began to fade.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I saw you on the day you were born. It was the proudest and most painful day of your father&amp;rsquo;s life.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You Telemachus must return and fight for what is his, and yours.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>My goal is not to kill you. You must understand. That without gods, man is nothing.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>I was alive. Broken by Poseidon&amp;rsquo;s waves.&lt;/strong> But I was alive. I was led to the palace of their ruler, the powerful king, Alcinous.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I understood that I was only one man in the world. Nothing more and nothing less.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pontonous. Blend a sleeping potion.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>My cheese. My wine. My bread.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I am alive.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Please, look at me. Do you see yourself In my face.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I know what your head asks your heart. You&amp;rsquo;re afraid your Penelope has been untrue to you.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He went for his father and found a filthy beggar.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>I did not find him. But I know my father is alive.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He&amp;rsquo;s alive. He&amp;rsquo;s alive Odysseus. He knows your sorrow. Your pain. And he longs to touch your hand, hold you in his eyes, kiss your lips. He&amp;rsquo;ll come to defend you. He&amp;rsquo;ll come to defend you. You&amp;rsquo;ll see.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Tomorrow, I&amp;rsquo;ll take my world back.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If I cannot do it, no man alive can. O: And what about a man who was dead?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Your crime is that you tried to steal my world. The world I built with my hands and my sweat. The world I shared with a woman who bore me my son and no one will ever that that from me! Now you&amp;rsquo;ll die to a man in a river of blood.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I will never leave you.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It&amp;rsquo;s 20 years since you held me in your eyes. O: That was only one day. P: And in one day you&amp;rsquo;ve seen all the world? O: Yes. So much that is sacred and beautiful, but nothing as beautiful as a man&amp;rsquo;s own world. That he can take in his hands and always be his. You are my world.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Also see &lt;a href="http://www.noologie.de/quer.htm#_Toc25566870">noologie.de&lt;/a>:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ready Player One</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-10-17-ready_player_one/</link><pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-10-17-ready_player_one/</guid><description>&lt;p>The year is 2045 and the reality sucks so much that practically all humanity spends most of its time in a virtual reality called OASIS. Recently its Author has passed away and he&amp;rsquo;s offered his position including the ownership of OASIS to anybody who masters his three challenges:&lt;/p>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Win an unwinnable race. The key to this challenge is to drive backwards.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ask the Lady of the Author to dance. Easy, isn&amp;rsquo;t it? Well, the Lady is trapped in the &amp;ldquo;Overlook Hotel&amp;rdquo; from the horror movie &amp;ldquo;The Shinning&amp;rdquo; (sa:deva) and she&amp;rsquo;s dancing with dead people. On the way to the Lady, one has to go through all the zombies. Lady is source of life itself, in the form of a woman. And key to it is through suffering. Hint from the 2nd challenge: &amp;ldquo;Ultimate answer will be found in the Fortress Tragic&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The final challenge takes place on the planet Doom. But this is not the challenge. It is to win an unknown game while playing it! How to do? Just like life, really. &amp;ldquo;The key is to play without going for the win. Everyone who wins loses. Keys are invisible and hidden in a dark room that&amp;rsquo;s the center of the maze. Found by wandering about until you get to the invisible dot - it&amp;rsquo;s pretty easy if you know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo; And the name of the first game? &amp;ldquo;Adventure&amp;rdquo;. And the prize obtained is the first easter egg ever - the name of the Author of the game.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;p>After mastering the three challenges the winner - Parzival - is presented with a huge golden &amp;ldquo;easter egg&amp;rdquo;. And what does the winner gain? Well, the usual - the world with the princess and his new identity as the ruler of it - of course.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>American Beauty (1999)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-01-25-american_beauty/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-01-25-american_beauty/</guid><description>&lt;p>Initial song name from OST: &lt;em>Dead already&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve lost something. I&amp;rsquo;m not exactly sure what it is but I know didn&amp;rsquo;t always feel this sedated. But you know what? It&amp;rsquo;s never too late to get it back.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s the weirdest thing. I feel like I&amp;rsquo;ve been in a coma for about 20 years and I&amp;rsquo;m just now waking up.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&amp;hellip; retiring to the men&amp;rsquo;s room so I can jerk off while I fantasize about a life that doesn&amp;rsquo;t so closely remember hell.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Fight Club (1999)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-14-fight_club/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-14-fight_club/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Losing all hope is freedom.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Illusion of safety.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Without pain, without sacrifice, we would have nothing.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It&amp;rsquo;s only after we&amp;rsquo;ve lost everything that we&amp;rsquo;re free to do anything.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Advertising has chasing us cars and clothes. Working jobs we hate so we can buy shit we don&amp;rsquo;t need.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Our Great War is a spiritual war, our Great Depression is our lives.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stop trying to control everything and just let go.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Condom is the glass slipper of our generation. You slip one on when you meet a stranger. You dance all night and then throw it away.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We are a generation of men raised by women. I&amp;rsquo;m wondering if another woman is the thing we need.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Self-improvement is masturbation. Now, self-destruction is the answer.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Feel the pain. That&amp;rsquo;s what makes life challenging.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Kingdom of God (2005)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-10-07-kingdom_of_god/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-10-07-kingdom_of_god/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A king might move a man, a father may claim a son, but that man can also move himself, and only then does that man truly begin his own game. Remember that howsoever you are played or by whom, your soul is in your keeping alone, even though those who presume to play you be kings or men of power. When you stand before God, you cannot say, &amp;ldquo;But I was told by others to do thus,&amp;rdquo; or that virtue was not convenient at the time.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Balian: &amp;ldquo;You go to certain death.&amp;rdquo; Hospitaler knight: &amp;ldquo;All death is certain.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Be brave in the face of your enemies. Be upright so that God may love thee. Speak the truth always, even if it leads to your death. This is your oath and this (a slap in the face) is so that you remember it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A better world than has even been seen. A kingdom of conscience. A kingdom of heaven.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What is Jerusalem worth? Nothing. Everything.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Zorba the Greek (1964)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-09-14-zorba_the_greek/</link><pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-09-14-zorba_the_greek/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>I went for it all. Wife, house, children. The full catastrophe.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Life is trouble. To be alive is to undo your belt and look for trouble.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>Good or bad, what is the difference? They all end up the same way.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>A man needs a little madness or else he never dares to cut the rope and be free.&lt;/p>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>“This is true happiness: to have no ambition and to work like a horse as if you had every ambition. To live far from men, not to need them and yet to love them. To have the stars above, the land to your left and the sea to your right and to realize of a sudden that in your heart, life has accomplished its final miracle: it has become a fairy tale.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>