<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>John Butler on uzak.github.io</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/tags/john-butler/</link><description>Recent content in John Butler on uzak.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://uzak.github.io/tags/john-butler/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>What does love see?</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-15-what_does_love_see/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-15-what_does_love_see/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=apy9_l0GA8g">src&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Prayer is raising of consciousness where you transcend this world of death&lt;/li>
&lt;li>prayer is reaching up into this (points higher)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>one day it will become more real to you than the world of death down here&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It&amp;rsquo;s no use to save the world if we are the cause of the trouble&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The hope is that in spirit you realize the existence of greater life where is no death.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do you meet a lot of realized people? I&amp;rsquo;ve never met anybody. I would not claim that myself fully, partially at times.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Once you start working with spirit there is no need for audience.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Spirit doesn&amp;rsquo;t need public acclaim, his work are unseen, unknown. He&amp;rsquo;s the real invisible power behind the scenes. It&amp;rsquo;s the life, the life force. Who&amp;rsquo;s ever seen it? Who&amp;rsquo;s ever seen electricity? It&amp;rsquo;s recognized by its effects.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>John the baptist: Behold, the lamb of god that takes away the sin of the world.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When the heart is melted, what comes out of it? Love. No glorification, no I love you.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What does love see? Love sees perfection in the bellowed? Love see no ill. Nothing but loveliness. Love sees purity. The pure in heart see god.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is no need to go to India to look for gurus. Look at the lamb, let your heart be melted, let your tears run and you&amp;rsquo;ll be as close to god as you ever be. You don&amp;rsquo;t need a teacher. Teacher is in-front of your nose.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>My entire life has expressed not what I&amp;rsquo;m, but what I&amp;rsquo;m not.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You want peace? Stillness? Earth is still, rocks are still. Put your feet on the ground. But the mind likes its own restlessness.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you want to bring the world to peace, star with yourself. That&amp;rsquo;s the essence of prayer. Heal yourself.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The destiny of the world of sin is to rot away. Sin is death. Duality is on death row, duality is death.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Real life is in spirit.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you&amp;rsquo;re serious about helping yourself or even better helping others, put prayer into practice. Practice what you preach. To make whole be whole.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Humanism - worship of the body. We think we&amp;rsquo;re so clever. We completely turn away from the point of life. We miss the true destiny of man - which is spirit, which is the kingdom of heaven.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --></description></item><item><title>Redemption</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-08-redemption/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-08-redemption/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ainBMrXfqMc">src&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>redemption is that which I cannot do myself. It compels one to look beyond my own failure.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What are we going to do about the world my dears? God knows, I don&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Humanity is a lesson in the consequence of pride.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pride is thinking that we can live without God, without that which is greater than ourselves.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If we&amp;rsquo;re convinced that we know we close the door to anybody else. We thing we&amp;rsquo;re right.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To make whole, be whole. Yet we feel we need to do.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Redemption is the return to God&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Living by grace makes life bearable.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It is so easy to focus on the negatives but there is so much good, beauty and love in the world.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Life goes on. When man dies another is born. Redemption.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --></description></item><item><title>Is sin just ignorance?</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-06-is_sin_just_ignorance/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-06-is_sin_just_ignorance/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=maOEMPNoVaE">src&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Why do we fall from this blessed state of freedom into this imprisonment we call life. Death by self-imprisonment. We take it as normal. We look down, we don&amp;rsquo;t look up. The unlimited sky is always there.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>View from airplane offers best contrast. Problems dissolved - unlimited expansion.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sin is when things go wrong.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mistaken identity. All problems of the world arise from it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Repentance is turning back to freedom again.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Unselfishness, you think less about me.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We&amp;rsquo;re all mini Christs. We have to take our cross.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>It seems I would not say reasonable, but wonderful.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Where is that end where spirit, freedom begins?&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Whatever is happening is contained in this unchanging, ever present, presence of God.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>You and me and this, what is called the third point. Three - basic building components of all religions. Duality contained in the third.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The only problem with duality is that it is in conflict.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The duality is only problematic when we forget the third point.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Come back to simplicity. Distrust of complexity. Common sense.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>This present is asking nothing of us, it accepts you as we are. Forgiveness - prime feature of this presence. Most merciful. Forgiving.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Where do all these judgements come from? Not coming from user selves?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sin is mistaken identity. Sin is ignorance.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Perhaps duality is ignorance of the one.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --></description></item><item><title>Judge not</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-05-judge_not/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-05-judge_not/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uVECV4PmyDw">src&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>When you worry about it these things are only get bigger. You don&amp;rsquo;t really get rid of ego. Is part of your machinery as man.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Get on with life. Attend what is there to attend and forget about your ego. When you do what you love you forget about yourself in the process.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What do I do about highs and lows? Just like weather, nothing.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;em>Little bed, early to rise, makes the man healthy, wealthy and wise.&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When I was a little boy &amp;ldquo;psychology&amp;rdquo; was not even invented. We&amp;rsquo;ve lost touch with common sense. We&amp;rsquo;ve become so unnatural.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>How to make the world a better place? With 20 years old I tried to do physically, now I pray.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Father: mother knows man. As young man: nature knows man. Now: &lt;strong>God knows best. Prayer is aligning myself with that. Jesus: into thy hands, oh Lord.&lt;/strong> I try to surrender not only myself but everything which is contained in my consciousness. There is no better way in which I can serve the world. God knows and I do not but I have faith that this is the best thing I can do.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>One of the most damaging aspects of the ego - judging and critizising others. Jesus: judge not! Judging puts our selves in prison. &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m right and he&amp;rsquo;s wrong&amp;rdquo;. Let God be the judge.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Wars are like futball matches. You support one side and cheer when your side makes a goal.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ego builds up subsitute reality and the idea that &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m separate&amp;rdquo;. &lt;strong>In the beginning the one man - Adam, the spiritual man, lived in paradise. Yet his wife stole what they were told not to steal. They stole like we&amp;rsquo;re stealing from the world. So they got cast out and divided.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To be one - not to be divided at all. Come back to that primal state of being in paradise.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>regular daily practice of turning to god. Meditation and prayer. This will lead the way and the ego falls behind. You simply grow out of it, of this childish selfishness.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Quote from Johns book &amp;ldquo;Wonders of Spiritual Enfoldment&amp;rdquo;: &lt;strong>there is no more expectation of comfort or reliability in man, nor desire for the things of creation.&lt;/strong> World - a marvelous order of things including the disorder of man. But I feel ever less moved to participate.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Constant longing for god has become reality now.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>You don&amp;rsquo;t lose it, you can&amp;rsquo;t find it.&lt;/strong> It&amp;rsquo;s just part of you, you merge into it. God&amp;rsquo;s no longer something separate and you&amp;rsquo;re fine. &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Know I&amp;rsquo;m with you always&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>This is a billion times more effective than psychologists.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When you find this infinite presence there are no more questions, not more problems. Completion. Wonderful.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is nothing, nothing that isn&amp;rsquo;t loved in this world. Even terrorists.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ego is separate and makes everything else separate. We end up in living in a world of names.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Life of separation, life of name and form. Melt them.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Demonstrate my confidence in silence and not speaking. Show my disinterest in all that talking. Greater value mediate. Less talking&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --></description></item></channel></rss>