<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>John Butler on uzak.github.io</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/tags/john-butler/</link><description>Recent content in John Butler on uzak.github.io</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://uzak.github.io/tags/john-butler/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Redemption</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-08-redemption/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-08-redemption/</guid><description>src
redemption is that which I cannot do myself. It compels one to look beyond my own failure. What are we going to do about the world my dears? God knows, I don&amp;rsquo;t. Humanity is a lesson in the consequence of pride. Pride is thinking that we can live without God, without that which is greater than ourselves. If we&amp;rsquo;re convinced that we know we close the door to anybody else.</description></item><item><title>Is sin just ignorance?</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-06-is_sin_just_ignorance/</link><pubDate>Tue, 06 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-06-is_sin_just_ignorance/</guid><description>src
Why do we fall from this blessed state of freedom into this imprisonment we call life. Death by self-imprisonment. We take it as normal. We look down, we don&amp;rsquo;t look up. The unlimited sky is always there. View from airplane offers best contrast. Problems dissolved - unlimited expansion. Sin is when things go wrong. Mistaken identity. All problems of the world arise from it. Repentance is turning back to freedom again.</description></item><item><title>Judge not</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-05-judge_not/</link><pubDate>Mon, 05 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-05-judge_not/</guid><description>src:
When you worry about it these things are only get bigger. You don&amp;rsquo;t really get rid of ego. Is part of your machinery as man. Get on with life. Attend what is there to attend and forget about your ego. When you do what you love you forget about yourself in the process. What do I do about highs and lows? Just like weather, nothing. Little bed, early to rise, makes the man healthy, wealthy and wise.</description></item></channel></rss>