<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Books on uzak.github.io</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/tags/books/</link><description>Recent content in Books on uzak.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://uzak.github.io/tags/books/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Cesar's Rules</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2025-02-23-cesar_rules/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2025-02-23-cesar_rules/</guid><description>Those Magical American Dogs The Basics of Balance Dogs are hardwired to understand us. It&amp;rsquo;s in their genes to know how to read our facial expressions, body language, and changes of mood and energy. A dog in distress needs for you to stand strong and show leadership, not to melt into sympathy because you&amp;rsquo;re feeling sorry for her. I would never put up with some of the many things other dog owners thing are just fine - such as jumping on anyone who walks in the door, barking excessively or monopolizing the owner&amp;rsquo;s bed at night.</description></item><item><title>Balck Hermann: Order in Chaos</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2025-01-01-balck_hermann_order_in_chaos/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2025-01-01-balck_hermann_order_in_chaos/</guid><description>As so often when an incompetent government is facing internal problems it cannot solve, it seeks to overcome domestic failures through foreign policy A successful attack is less costly than a failed defense. Russian general Mikhail Skobelev once told his chief of staff, Alexei Kuropatkin, &amp;ldquo;You will always accomplish great things as the second in charge; God help Russia if you are ever put in charge.&amp;rdquo; Wisdom always comes after the fact.</description></item><item><title>Iron John</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-21-iron_john/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-21-iron_john/</guid><description>The Pillow and the Key In The Odyssey, Hermes instructs Odysseus when he approaches Circe, who stands for certain kind of matriarchal energy, he is to lift or show his sword. Showing a sword doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily mean fighting. It can also suggest a joyful decisiveness. Finding Iron John &amp;ldquo;What can I do? Anything dangerous to do around here?&amp;rdquo; When he approaches what I&amp;rsquo;ll call the &amp;ldquo;deep male&amp;rdquo;, he feels risk. The Loss of the Golden Ball King&amp;rsquo;s eight year old son&amp;rsquo;s golden ball rolls into Wild Man&amp;rsquo;s cage.</description></item><item><title>James Hollis: Finding Meaning in the Second Half of Life</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-15-james_hollis_finding_meaning_in_the_second_half_of_life/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-15-james_hollis_finding_meaning_in_the_second_half_of_life/</guid><description>Introduction: The Dark Wood Dante began his famous, fabulous descent into the underworld with the recognition that midway in life he found himself in a dark wood, having lost his way. Aeschylus, the first great tragedian, observed that gods ordained a solemn decree that from suffering alone comes wisdom. Using the words soul and psyche interchangeably. Mystery in which our journey plays out: the immense cosmos through which we are flung at warp velocity, ambient nature, which is our home and our context, each proximate other who brings the challenge of relationship, and our own elusive, insurgent Self, forever asking, insisting, not to be forgotten.</description></item><item><title>El regresso de Quetzalcóatl</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-02-25-el_regresso_de_quetzalcoatl/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-02-25-el_regresso_de_quetzalcoatl/</guid><description>src
Te presento a mi Quetzalcóatl Una grandeza que se deriva de nuestras dos grandes raíces: Mesoamérica y España. Nuestras raíces no tienen por que pelear quinientos anos después de su violento encuentro. El trauma de la conquista no se deriva de que recordemos un evento que, evidentemente, nadie en el mundo de hoy vivió&amp;hellip; deliberadamente nos inyectamos odio en el corazón. El 13 de agosto de 1521 decenas de pueblos sometidos se liberaron del mas terrible y sanguinario yugo opresor, y junto a sus aliados castellanos comenzaron a construir México, un país surgido de la unidad y del triunfo, pero a cuyo pueblo le han narrado una versión de los hechos muy equivocada.</description></item><item><title>Empire of Hatred: A Study of the Revolution</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-12-28-empire_of_hatred_a_study_of_the_revolution/</link><pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-12-28-empire_of_hatred_a_study_of_the_revolution/</guid><description>The Revolution is not Synonymous with Communism The goal of the intellect is to discover what is True, what is definite, even if it is painful - especially if it is painful - and to live according to the Truth as best as we are able. Attempting a Definition of Liberalism doctrine of change for change&amp;rsquo;s sake, in which case we must concede that liberalism is but another name for chaos, or the desire for chaos.</description></item><item><title>The Subtle Art of Not Giving a F*ck</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-06-21-the_subtle_art_of_not_giving_a_fuck/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-06-21-the_subtle_art_of_not_giving_a_fuck/</guid><description>Don&amp;rsquo;t try Bukowski never tried to by anything other what he was. He was able to be completely, unflinchingly honest with himself - especially the worst parts of himself. Feedback loop from Hell The desire for more positive experience is itself a negative experience. Acceptance of one&amp;rsquo;s negative experience is a positive experience. Happiness Is a Problem The premise that happiness is algorithmic, that it can be worked for and earned and achieved is a problem.</description></item><item><title>Remote</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-04-24-remote/</link><pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-04-24-remote/</guid><description>The Time Is Right for Remote Work Office during the day has become the last place where people get their work done. Required: ability to be alone with your thoughts. Stop commuting your life away - commutes make you fat, stressed and miserable. Escaping 9am-5pm: synchronous -&amp;gt; asynchronous End of city monopoly Industrialism (factories): gather a large number of people into small area. life need not be divided into arbitrary phases: work and retirement Talent isn&amp;rsquo;t bound by the hubs It&amp;rsquo;s not about the money - promote quality of life, getting best people available Dealing with Excuses If you&amp;rsquo;re struggling with trust issues, you&amp;rsquo;ve made a poor hiring decision.</description></item><item><title>It doesn't have to be crazy at work</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-03-29-it_doesnt_have_to_be_crazy_at_work/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2022-03-29-it_doesnt_have_to_be_crazy_at_work/</guid><description>Here are some notes from the marvelous book &amp;ldquo;It doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be crazy at work&amp;rdquo;. If you like the notes, please consider buying the book.
First It&amp;rsquo;s Crazy at Work Workday is being sliced into tiny moments by an onslaught of distractions. Unhealthy obsession with growth. Sustained exhaustion is not a badge of honor, it&amp;rsquo;s a mark of stupidity. The answer isn&amp;rsquo;t more hours, it&amp;rsquo;s less bullshit. Less waste, not more production.</description></item><item><title>Rework</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-07-05-rework/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-07-05-rework/</guid><description>by Jason Fried.
Takedown Ignore the real world The real world isn&amp;rsquo;t a place, it&amp;rsquo;s an excuse. It&amp;rsquo;s a justification for not trying. It has nothing to do with you.
Learning from mistakes is overrated Failure is not a prerequisite for success.
People who failed have the same amount of success as people who have never tried at all.
Long term business planing is fantasy.
Start referring to any of your plans as guesses.</description></item><item><title>The Pragmatic Programmer</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-03-16-the_pragmatic_programmer/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2020-03-16-the_pragmatic_programmer/</guid><description>From Journeyman to Master
Preface core process: taking a requirement and producing working, maintainable code that delights the user. QWAN - quality without a name. Don&amp;rsquo;t preach, just tell/do what works. pragmatic -&amp;gt; lat. (pragmaticus) -&amp;gt; greek &amp;ldquo;to do&amp;rdquo;. There are no easy answers There is no such thing as best solution, tool language or OS. You shouldn&amp;rsquo;t be weeded to any particular technology but have broad enough background and experience base to allow to choose good solution in any particular situation.</description></item><item><title>Testing Python</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-13-python__testing/</link><pubDate>Fri, 13 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-13-python__testing/</guid><description>Chapter 1 Writing code without tests in general is going to lead to problems down the line. Choreographing One of the worst traps a developer can fall into is writing a bunch of code and then going back and testing it all at the end. With the advent of social networks and the ever-increasing pressure of media attention, defects in your code could be costly to both you and your reputation or that of any company you may represent.</description></item><item><title>Carlos Castaneda: 3. Cesta do Ixtlanu</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-02-castaneda/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-12-02-castaneda/</guid><description>1 - Pritakanie sveta okolo nás nahnať strach synovi (dať mu lekciu) musí niekto iný ako otec, ktorý ho má ochraňovať (Iron John: kráľovi muži). od malička sa učíme popisu sveta, až si ho osvojíme a v ňom žijeme (matrix) a stratíme pojem o čare reality. rád hodne chodím. mentor: budeš mi platiť za môj čas tvojím časom. nikdy nič nepije, ani pivo. pre všetko, čo robíme, je nezbytná iba jedna vec - Duch!</description></item><item><title>Carlos Castaneda (1, 2)</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-09-15-castaneda/</link><pubDate>Sun, 15 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-09-15-castaneda/</guid><description>Poznámky z prvých dvoch kníh od Carlosa Castanedu:
1. Učení Dona Juana &amp;hellip; u nekonečne dlhej cesty sa nedá pokúsiť o nič viac, ako nájsť jej začiatok a stanoviť jej smer. Predstieranie, že cesta je pochopená a dokončená, je prinajmenšom klamaním samého seba. Jednotlivý študent na nej môže dosiahnuť dokonalosti iba v subjektívnom slova zmysle a vyprávať o nej môže iba tak, že povie všetko, čo bol schopný zhliadnuť. &amp;ndash; Georg Simmel</description></item><item><title>The Greatest Escape - Adventures in the History of Solitude</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-08-16-adventures_of_solitude/</link><pubDate>Fri, 16 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2019-08-16-adventures_of_solitude/</guid><description>Highlights from the book The Greatest Escape: Adventures in the History of Solitude (c) 2004 by David Stimpson - a kind of a Bible and eulogy on Solitude and Silence.
Prologue life of solitude - either through periodic retreats or continuing inner solitude in society - may be the best answer to cries that modern world is inevitably a &amp;ldquo;lonely crowd.&amp;rdquo; your lonely quietude may be bothered by demons of lust, vainglory, or melancholy.</description></item></channel></rss>