<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Swami Paramarthananda on अहो अहं </title>
    <link>https://uzak.github.io/tags/swami-paramarthananda/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Swami Paramarthananda on अहो अहं </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>me</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 17 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://uzak.github.io/tags/swami-paramarthananda/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Brahmasutras (1-4)</title>
      <link>https://uzak.github.io/posts/2021-04-17-brahmasutras/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://uzak.github.io/posts/2021-04-17-brahmasutras/</guid>
      <description>notes, summary
01 INTRODUCTION  Sutra - small statement with lot of ideas packed in it. Aphorism. Audio/oral tradition, not visual. Writing was not there and even when it came, it was not used very much. A huge book can be compressed into few sutras which are memorized. Sutra method has been devised because of memory. Sutra method - putting all the ideas in metrical verse form. Poetry form. It is easier to remember a verse form.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SvetAshvatara Upanishad</title>
      <link>https://uzak.github.io/posts/2021-01-16-svetaashvataraupanishad/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://uzak.github.io/posts/2021-01-16-svetaashvataraupanishad/</guid>
      <description>Summary
Svetasvatara_Upanishad SA-EN 1949
Class 1: 1 / 1, 2   Compilation, thus not a systematic teaching, yet covers all the important vedantic ideas.
  Highlights isvara jnanam as the only means of moksha. Purna isvara jnanam - both saguna and nirguna version.
  Svetaashvataraupanishad: you can attain moksha through other methods other than jnanam if you fulfill this condition: you&amp;rsquo;ve to roll the sky from one side to the other just like a carpet and present it to god, god will give moksha without jnanam.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vivekacudamani Meditations</title>
      <link>https://uzak.github.io/posts/2020-11-20-vivekachudamani_meditations/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://uzak.github.io/posts/2020-11-20-vivekachudamani_meditations/</guid>
      <description>[Previous Vivekacudamani classes]({% post_url 2020-07-26-vivekachudamani_sp_2020 %})
40 meditation verses, Vivekacudamani translation
Class 1: Introduction  niddhhai - deep meditation An informed seeker rejects moksha, artha, kama and goes for the only permanent goal - moksha. What is permanent (nityam) must be available in all three periods in time. If it is available in present, it must be already accomplished (siddhah). Moksha is always already accomplished fact - it can never be a goal to be accomplished in the future (sadhyah).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vivekachudamani Swami Paramarthananda 2020</title>
      <link>https://uzak.github.io/posts/2020-07-26-vivekachudamani_sp_2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://uzak.github.io/posts/2020-07-26-vivekachudamani_sp_2020/</guid>
      <description>Selected 108 Verses
Summary of first 64 Verses
Class 14: 31, 32 &amp;hellip; What is anAtmA? sat na bhavati, asat na bhavati, ubhayAtmikA na bhavati:
 Maya and its product do not commander category of existent entity. But you cannot say opposite. Anirvachaynia - seemingly existent, Experientially available. On probing mysterious. Like dream world. You cannot say existent or non-existent. When we are in dream the dream world comes into &amp;ldquo;existent&amp;rdquo; category.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
