<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Psychology on uzak.github.io</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/tags/psychology/</link><description>Recent content in Psychology on uzak.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://uzak.github.io/tags/psychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Iron John</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-21-iron_john/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-21-iron_john/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-pillow-and-the-key">The Pillow and the Key&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>In The Odyssey, Hermes instructs Odysseus when he approaches Circe, who stands for certain kind of matriarchal energy, he is to lift or show his sword. Showing a sword doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily mean fighting. It can also suggest a joyful decisiveness.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="finding-iron-john">Finding Iron John&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;What can I do? Anything dangerous to do around here?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When he approaches what I&amp;rsquo;ll call the &amp;ldquo;deep male&amp;rdquo;, he feels risk.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-loss-of-the-golden-ball">The Loss of the Golden Ball&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>King&amp;rsquo;s eight year old son&amp;rsquo;s golden ball rolls into Wild Man&amp;rsquo;s cage. If he wants the ball back, he&amp;rsquo;s going to have to ask him for it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Freud: &amp;ldquo;What a distressing contrast there is between the radiant intelligence of the child and the feeble mentality of the average adult.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Iron John story says that a man can&amp;rsquo;t expect to find the golden ball in the feminine realm, because that&amp;rsquo;s not where the ball is. The story proposes it lies within the magnetic field of the Wild Man.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Wild Man energy, by contrast, leads to &lt;strong>forceful action undertaken, not with cruelty, but with resolve.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>[Bucket work implies] much more discipline that most men realize.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The key is under your mother&amp;rsquo;s pillow. Michael Maede: &lt;strong>the pillow is also the place where the mother stores all her expectations for you.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The king gives the key into the keeping of the Queen. &lt;strong>A mother&amp;rsquo;s job is, after all, to civilize the boy.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The key has to be stolen.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="what-does-the-boy-do">What Does the Boy Do?&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Exuberance in a child is bad, and at the first sign of it, parents should be severe. Exuberance implies that the wild boy or girl is no longer locked up.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="going-off-on-the-wild-mans-shoulders">Going Off on the Wild Man&amp;rsquo;s Shoulders&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The fault of the nuclear family today isn&amp;rsquo;t so much that it&amp;rsquo;s crazy and full of double binds, it is that old men outside the nuclear family no longer offer an effective way for the son to break his link with his parents without doing harm to himself.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Women can change the embryo to a boy, but only men can change the boy to a man.&lt;/strong> Initiators say that boys need a second birth, this time a birth from men.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Classical solution in many traditional cultures, which send the boy to his father when he is twelve.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When office work and the &amp;ldquo;information revolution&amp;rdquo; begin to dominate, the father-son bond disintegrates. One could say that the father now loses his son five minutes after birth.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-remote-father">The Remote Father&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Zeus energy is male authority accepted for the sake of community.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The father in contemporary TV ads never knows what cold medicine to take.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>revenge on remote father.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung: when the son is introduced primarily by the mother to feeling, he will learn the female attitude towards masculinity and take a female view of his own father and his own masculinity. Since the father and the mother are in competition for the affection of the son, you&amp;rsquo;re not going to get a straight picture of your father out of your mother.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Somewhere around forty, forty-five a movement toward the father takes place naturally.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>In the Greek myths, Apollo is visualized as a golden man standing on an enormous accumulation of the dark, alert, dangerous energy called Dionysus. The Wild Man in our story includes some of both kinds of energy.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="when-one-hair-turns-gold">When One Hair Turns Gold&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Initiation experience begins with two events. 1. clean break with the parents after which the novice goes to the forest, &lt;strong>desert,&lt;/strong> or wilderness. 2. wound that the older men give the boy, which could be scarring of the skin, a cut with a knife, a brushing with nettles, a tooth knocked out.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Something in the adolescent male wants risk, courts danger, goes out to the edge - even to the edge of death.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-story-the-first-day-at-the-pond">The Story: The First Day at the Pond&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Initiation, then, for young men amounts to helping them remember the wound, and by that we mean the soul wounds, or the injuries to the emotional body.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Robert Moore: If you&amp;rsquo;re a young man and you&amp;rsquo;re not being admired by an older man, you&amp;rsquo;re being hurt.&amp;quot;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Having a critical, judgemental father amounts to being one of Cronos&amp;rsquo; sons, whom Cronos ate.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Father gives a blow, and the son gets it. And it&amp;rsquo;s a wound the boy remembers for years.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mother makes sure the son receives a baptism of shame.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gang members try desperately to learn courage, family loyalty, and discipline from each other.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Having no soul union with other men can be the most damaging would of all.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>All wounds threaten our princehood.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The initiation tells the young man what to do with wounds, the new (by men) and the old.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When people identify themselves with their wounded child, or remain children, the whole culture goes to pieces.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ecstasy too early - or generalized excitement - may be, as James Hillman has remarked, just another way the Great Mother has of keeping the man from developing any discipline.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Wild man is not &amp;ldquo;inside&amp;rdquo; of us.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the water of soul life&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>willingness to be a fish in the holy water, to be fished for by Dionysus or one of the other fishermen. Being a fish is to be active, not with cars or footballs, but with soul.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Denial mean we live for years in trance.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Being brought by the water by a mentor means the end of enchantment.&lt;/strong> The Wild Man&amp;rsquo;s water does not itself heal the wound that led to the escape or ascension, but it gives strength to the part of us that wants to continue the effort to gain courage and be human.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Wild Man here amounts to an invisible presence &amp;hellip; The physicist working with his mentor at Princeton suddenly writes an equation on the board with his golden chalk.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>therapy, when it good - waiting by the pond.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Where a man&amp;rsquo;s wound is, that is where his genius will be.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Water in symbolic systems does not stand for spiritual or metaphysical impulses (which are better suggested by air or fire), but by earthly and natural life.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-story-the-second-day">The Story: The Second Day&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>we know from shaman stories that their wounds were impersonal. Wounds need to be expanded into air and lifted on the ideas our ancestors new, so that the wound ascents through the roof of our parent&amp;rsquo;s house and we suddenly know how our wound (seemingly so private) fits into a greater and impersonal story.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Without the weight given by a wound consciously realized, the man will lead a provisional life.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>hair represents sexual energy, animal life, passionate flaring nature peculiar to mammals and excess.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the amount of hair suggest how far the instincts are curtailed and the spontaneity curbed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>hair suggest thoughts. Even when the conscious system is shut down at night, thoughts keep coming out: some of them are called dreams.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>hair stands for intuitions that appear out of nowhere&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If a human being takes an action, the soul takes an action.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>the generous response made by the sacred pond spring depends on a serious decisive effort made by a man or woman.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-story-the-third-day">The Story: The Third Day&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://allpoetry.com/I-Am-Not-I">https://allpoetry.com/I-Am-Not-I&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Narcissus has already become separated from his male hunting companions as the story opens. It turns out that Hera is also angry at him, and has sent a nymph called Echo who repeats each of his words as soon as he speaks them. Narcissus is bottled up inside his own circuits.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="going-out-into-the-world">Going Out into the World&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Accepting an initiatory task is more important than succeeding or failing at it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Wild Man&amp;rsquo;s job is to teach the young man how abundant, various and many-sided his manhood is.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A man or a woman is not a machine only for protecting, hunting, and reproduction, but each carries desires far beyond what is needed for physical survival.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A young man is asked to descend into his own wounds, to climb up into the ream of &amp;ldquo;the twin&amp;rdquo;, and to expand sideways into the consciousness that is in tress, water, animals and &amp;ldquo;the ten thousand things&amp;rdquo;. Upon achieving these three realizations, the hair turns gold. This doesn&amp;rsquo;t solve all his problems, but brings new ones. The golden head is going to be a problem.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="the-road-of-ashes-descent-and-grief">The Road of Ashes, Descent, and Grief&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>He learned that the whole world is on fire. &amp;ldquo;Everything is intelligent!&amp;rdquo; All of his hair turns gold.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A bit of gold can send us into high altitudes, from which we don&amp;rsquo;t want to descend.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="what-happens">What Happens&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>When I was twenty-eight I still had the &lt;strong>longing for purity, &amp;ldquo;to be above it all,&amp;rdquo; not to be involved.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When Jung established a training center in Zurich, he would not accept a person who was not already a success in some other career. It was a way of saying thirty-five or older.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ascenders &amp;hellip; passivity, naivete, and numbness.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>For hundreds of thousands of years men have admired each other, and been admired by women, in particular for their activity.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>During last thirty (sixty ATM) years men have been asked to learn how to go with the flow, follow rather than lead, live in a non hierarchical way, how to be vulnerable, how to adopt to consensus decision-making.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Passivity increases exponentially as the education system turns out &amp;ldquo;products&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When a man sulks, he becomes passive to his own hurts. When no old men appear to break the hold of the sulking infant, the habit of passivity spreads to other parts of his life.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The passive man may not say what he wants, and the wife has to guess it.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The passive man may ask his wife to do the loving for him; his children to do his loving for him.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A woman does not want a man to tell her what to do, but other forces may have turned her away from a fruitful action or act. If her husband sees this happening, he should tell her about it. A man hopes a woman will tell him as well, if she sees him accepting the direction of invisible forces.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>adolescent &amp;ldquo;in trouble&amp;rdquo; who is &amp;ldquo;acting out&amp;rdquo; may in fact be transferring some of the anxiety between mother and father to himself, and in that sense carrying it. Children are active in loving to the point of sacrificing themselves&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="naivete">Naivete&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>the naive man feels pride in being attacked.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The naive will be also proud that he can pick up the pain of others, particularly women&amp;rsquo;s pain.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sincerity is a big thing with him.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The naive man will lose what is most precious to him because of a lack of boundaries.&lt;/strong> Unaware of boundaries, he does not develop a good container for his soul, nor a good container for two people. There is a leak in it somewhere.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The naive man tends to have an &lt;strong>inappropriate relation to ecstasy. He longs for ecstasy at the wrong time or in the wrong place, and ignores all masculine sources of it. He wants it through the feminine, through Great Mother, through the goddess, even though what may be grounding for the woman ungrounds him.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The man without limitations may also &lt;strong>specialize in not telling.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He doesn&amp;rsquo;t know that there is a being in him that wants to remain sick.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>His timing is off.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is something in naivete that &lt;strong>demands betrayal.&lt;/strong> The naive man will have curious link to betrayal, deceit and lies. Not only he will betray others easily, but when a woman lives with a truly naive man for a while, she feels impersonally impelled to betray him. When there is too much naivete around, the universe has no choice but to crystallize out some betrayal.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="numbness">Numbness&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A spiritual man may love light, and yet be entirely numb in the chest area.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A mother&amp;rsquo;s protection, no matter how well intentioned, will not do as a substitute for the father&amp;rsquo;s protection.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-story-taking-kitchen-work">The Story: Taking Kitchen Work&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Go out into the world now and there you&amp;rsquo;ll learn what poverty is.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="katabasis">Katabasis&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>lowliness, associated with water and soul, as height is associated with spirit.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Drop - ancient Greek called katabasis. Our ego doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to do it and even if we drop, the ego doesn&amp;rsquo;t want to see it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>When &amp;ldquo;katabasis&amp;rdquo; happens, a man no longer feels like a special person.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>These days katabasis comes through addiction - alcohol, cocaine, crack.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Life somewhoe &amp;ldquo;discharges&amp;rdquo; him. There are many ways: a serious accident, the loss of a job, the breaking of a long-standing friendship, a divorce, or a &amp;ldquo;break-down&amp;rdquo;, an illness.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;ve just been promoted&amp;rdquo; Jung would say: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m very sorry to hear that; but if we all stick together, I think we will get through it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Kitchen work means intensification of the dipping (into the wound). This is the time to live it out.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He does not exist, as the hero does, through his heroism, nor through his invincibility, as the warrior does, but he exists through his would.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The way down and out doesn&amp;rsquo;t require poverty, homelessness, physical deprivation, dishwasher work, necessarily, but it does seem to require a fall from status, from a human being to a spider, from a middle-class person to a derelict. The emphasis is on the consciousness of the fall.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In a divorce, man&amp;rsquo;s emotional safety may disintegrate.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Marriage&amp;rsquo;s breakup or breakdown revives the wound.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Divorce feels for most men like a discharge, as if one had been fired from a task taken on the day of the wedding.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If the man refuses to be cheered up, and considers all the discomforts to be cunning expression of an isolating would received in early childhood, then the man can use the divorce - like any other serious collapse - as an invitation to go through the door, accept katabasis, immerse himself in the wound, and exit from his old life through it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Christ: &amp;ldquo;You shall not get out until have paid the last penny.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Some power in the psyche arranges a severe katabasis if the man does not know enough to go down on his own.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Some Sufi groups begin their night-work with a repeated word reminding them of the grief of what they have not done the past year.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Seeing the dark side of a person close to us is a discipline the descender accepts.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>It is said that in the marriage, the man and women give each other &amp;ldquo;his or her nethermost beast&amp;rdquo; to hold. Each holds the leash for the &amp;ldquo;nethermost beast&amp;rdquo; of the other.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>dark side of Great Mother, one with boar tusks coming from her lips. Angry woman. Compensation for earlier life &amp;ldquo;above the ground&amp;rdquo;, being fed with fish and fowl.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When we are betrayed the toothed side of the universe shows its mouth.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Kali. Only Shiva, one of the forms of Wild Man, can stand up to her.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pwyll, Prince of Dyved, whose story appears in The Mabinogion, does not become king until he has exchanged places for a year with the King of the Underworld.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>We reach the bottom when Baba Yaga&amp;rsquo;s hostile boar energy has completely replaces - for a time - the childlike eros which each of us felt when our mother set a breast to our mouth, or later set a cup of milk down for us at the table, or when our first marvelous girlfriend beckoned us to bed.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The only solution to the power of the witch is for young man to develop energy as great as hers, as harsh, as wild, as shred, as clear in its desire.&lt;/strong> When a young man arrives at her house, proves himself to be up her level of intensity, purpose, and respect for the truth, she will sometimes say, &amp;ldquo;Okay, what do you want know?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="taking-the-road-of-ashes">Taking the Road of Ashes&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ashes do not belong to the sunlit crown of the tree, nor to its strong roots. Ash is literally the death of the trunk.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>life of ashes is very different form dropping into katabasis. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t require a fall in social status. It is not so explosive; there is something about ashes that is &lt;strong>steady, even lethargic.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Young men in Viking times were allowed sometimes two or three years of ashes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Some kind of hibernation or ritual lethargy&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>before a boy can become a man, some infantile being in him must die.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The gold-obsessed man, whether New Age man or a Dow Jones, can be said to be the man who hasn&amp;rsquo;t yet handled ashes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>At thirty-five his inner stove begins to produce ashes as well. It&amp;rsquo;s time for him to by a small black shovel in the hardware store and get down on his knees.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Some habitual error we keep making in our relationships produces more ash than heat.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ashes present a great diminishment away from the living tree with its huge crown and abundant shade. Proper experience for men who are over thirty.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A man may keep his job and family and still experience ashes if he knows hat he is doing.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Somewhere in our past life there is a dead body. Could be a career mislaid, relationship gone into the river, or the corpse of ashamed boy.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="learning-to-shudder">Learning to Shudder&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>it is Dionysus, the last of the Greek gods to be developed, who guides that secret process in which the young man or woman learns to shudder.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Cruel titans.&lt;/strong> The horror at what these can do makes one shudder.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gaining the ability to shudder means feeling how frail human beings are, and how awful it is to be a Titan.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Just as Hermes helps &amp;ldquo;through the lines&amp;rdquo; on the road to retain the corpse, he is helped to shudder by the god Dionysus, the grandson of Titans.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="going-from-the-mothers-house-to-the-fathers-house">Going from the Mother&amp;rsquo;s House to the Father&amp;rsquo;s House&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Boys have lived happily since the birth in the mother&amp;rsquo;s world, and the father&amp;rsquo;s would naturally seem dangerous, unsteady, and full of unknowns.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Until eight to twelve boys lived exclusively with women.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A young man cannot make the move to the father&amp;rsquo;s world alone without taking on the dark side of the Trickster. Learn to &lt;em>rob the robbers&lt;/em>.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A man&amp;rsquo;s effort to move to father&amp;rsquo;s house takes a long time; it&amp;rsquo;s difficult, and each man has to do it for himself.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Convincing the naive boy or the comfort-loving boy, to die.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Beneath Father, being a snake, associates with the spinal cord.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>when a man accepts the Descent as a way to move to the father&amp;rsquo;s house, he learns to look at the death side of things, he glaces down to the rat&amp;rsquo;s hole, and he accepts the &lt;strong>snake rather than the bird as his animal.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Initiation asks the son to move his love energy away from the attractive mother to the relatively unattractive serpent father.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>he regards Descent as a holy thing, he increases his tolerance for ashes, eats dust as snakes do, increases his stomach for terrifying insights, deepens his ability to digest the evil facts of history, accepts the job of working seven years under the ground, leaves granary at will through the rat&amp;rsquo;s hole, follows the voice of old mole below the ground.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Apollo was present at the spring, Saturn,&lt;/strong> natural container of restraint, melancholy, fast systems, disciplined repetition, mentor standards and heavy grieving &lt;strong>is concealed in the ashes work.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Saturn, helps men to get heavy with the full weight of their wound, and the full power of their failures. After Saturn introduces a man to Lord of Melancholy, that man begins the black courtship of the soul which eventually leads the man to the Garden.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="the-hunger-for-the-king-in-a-time-with-no-father">The Hunger for the King in a Time with No Father&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="disturbances-in-sonhood">Disturbances in Sonhood&lt;/h3>
&lt;h4 id="too-little-father">Too Little Father&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>traditional cultures seem to have plenty of father&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In most tribal cultures fathers and son live in an amused tolerance of each other.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Both male and female cells carry marvelous music, but the son needs to resonate to the masculine frequency as well as to the female frequency.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Women cannot replace that particular missing substance.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="distrust-of-older-men">Distrust of Older Men&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The so, having used up much of his critical, cynical energy suspecting old men, may compensate by being naive about women - or men - his own age.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A contemporary man often assumes that a woman knows more about a relationship than he does, allows a woman&amp;rsquo;s moods to run the house, assumes that when she attacks him , she is doing it &amp;ldquo;for his own good.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="temperament-without-teaching">Temperament Without Teaching&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>in most families today, the sons and daughters receive, when the father returns home at six, only his disposition, or his temperament, which is usually irritable and remote.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>father as a living force in the home disappeared when those forces demanding industry sent him on various railroads out of his various villages.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="the-darkened-father">The Darkened Father&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>as political and mythological kings die, the father loses the radiance he once absorbed from the sun&lt;/li>
&lt;li>eternal boy, understands his flight upward as a revolt against the earthly, conservative, possessive, clinging part of the maternal feminine.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>many contemporary sons, do not fight the father as in earlier eras, or figure out strategies to defeat him, but instead ascend above him, beyond him, determined to have a higher consciousness than their father. That is not wrong at all, but it is flying.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I count myself among the sons who have endured years of deprivation, disconnection from earth, thin air, the loneliness of the long-distance runner, in order to go high in the air and be seen. Such a son attempts to redeem the &amp;ldquo;endarkened father&amp;rdquo; by becoming &amp;ldquo;enlightened&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A man may of course pursue spirituality too early in his life. The ascension, then, I add to our list of imbalances brought about by the diminishment and belittlement of the father.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Society without father produces this birdlike men, so intense, so charming, so open to addiction, so sincere&amp;hellip;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-story-visiting-the-king">The Story: Visiting the King&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Wild man carried him off his shoulders. Then he went down along with his damaged finger into the water, then rose steeply when his whole head turned gold, then descended again and experienced his &lt;strong>Ashes Time in the kitchen.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There are two kings. Father - first king. And a new king. After some time in the kitchen, the cook gives him an order to take the food to the king.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>why, in our twenties and thirties, are the visits so short.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>we long for that oceanic feeling we felt in the womb, when we were divine and fed by ambrosia. Addiction amounts to an attempt to escape limitations and stay in the King&amp;rsquo;s room.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Many of us go up the stairs even before he cook asks us to and through alcohol, sex, or cocaine, extend the visit beyond moments allotted for it.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Singles bar -fantastic alchemical ovens where attempts to fuse crude metals go on day after day, night after night - resemble King&amp;rsquo;s room.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>even though we&amp;rsquo;ve done good ashes work, the soul is still contaminated with infantile angers, unrealistic hopes, and rage at our parents or at ourselves.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Our soul, when it is in the kitchen, resembles some sort of crude or mixed rock. &lt;strong>The king, who lives in his room high in the castle among air and sunlight, has arrived at unity;&lt;/strong> undistorted, unmingled, as compared to the boy of ashes, he looks on matters differently.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The lesser wedding is a union or fusion of substances not yet thoroughly separated or discriminated. It is always followed by a death&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Those who ignore &amp;ldquo;the cook&amp;rdquo; may become stuck in the kitchen stage for years, identified with the victim child, who knows only ashes.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-king-in-his-three-realms">The King in His Three Realms&lt;/h3>
&lt;h4 id="the-sacred-king">The Sacred King&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>King in the imaginative or invisible world, in the sacred space. From there he acts as a magnet and rearranges human molecules.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The King and the Queen send their energy down. Solar King and Lunar Queen.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lord of the Four Quarters.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>overarching inner heaven.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>estimate that people in the West lost their ability to think mythologically around the year 1000. Perhaps because Christianity would not allow any new stories, gods or perhaps because after the Renaissance the pursuit of science absorbed more and more imaginative energy. European men and women gradually stopped feeding the abundant gods and goddesses with their imaginative energy - their heaven collapsed.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sacred or Solar King is the principle of order and space.&lt;/strong> When he is present, there is a sacred space free of chaos. He does not create order, simply where he is, there is order.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sacred King blesses. He encourages creativity as his realm.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="the-earthly-king">The Earthly King&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The political king meres heavenly sun power and earthly authority.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sun King and his Moon queen held societies for about 4000 years together. They began to fail in the 18th and 19th centuries in Europe.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>When the political king disappears from the lanes, we find it difficult to &amp;ldquo;see&amp;rdquo; or feel the Eternal King.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He derives his energy and authority from his ability to be transparent or receptive to the King above him. Few actual kings are that good, but the three-tiered world depends on his trying.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>We need to see the Sacred King not &amp;ldquo;with but through the eyes&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>, and to see our radiant inner King uncontaminated by the images of fallen Herods or dead Stalins.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="the-inner-king">The Inner King&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>One who knows what we want to do for the rest of our lives, rest of the month, rest of the day.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>He can make clear what we want without being contaminated in his choice by the opinions of others around us.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vigorous when were were one or two years old. For most of was was killed early on. Inner warriors were not strong enough to protect the King.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>When my King is weak, I ask my wife or children what is the right thing to do.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If the younger men have no public man to whom they can give their King, how can they develop the King inside?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When the outward flesh-and-blood king falls, his plunge downward entangles the fail Kings in the other two layers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The inner King, once recovered, required feeding and honoring if he is to remain alive.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="the-double-stream-inside-the-sacred-king">The Double Stream Inside the Sacred King&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>A second, darker side of the king, who will curse young men, discourage creativity, establish - by his presence alone - disorder.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Devil to be the brother of Christ.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="the-double-stream-inside-the-father">The Double Stream Inside the Father&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>We are now looking at a mentor in this world, or a Scared King in the other world.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>father contains both Kings at once.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>An apparently weak father can control the entire family from beneath with his silence.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The Destructive Father does not give energy to those in his family but draws it out of them into some black hole he shelter in himself.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stories of no guidance, no support, no affection, and in their place sarcasm, brutality, coldness.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>James Hillman: &amp;ldquo;If you&amp;rsquo;re still being hurt by an event that happened to you at twelve, it is the thought that is hurting you now.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>There is no father who will be good all the way, either.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If we insist he was an evil person, who shamed us all the time, we fall into victimhood and there is no longer a place for us in the story.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h4 id="the-longing-to-live-with-the-king">The Longing to Live with the King&lt;/h4>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>We cannot move to Sacred or Blessing King, until we&amp;rsquo;ve dealt with the ax-father.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Children visit the King, but adults make a place where the King can visit them.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Son&amp;rsquo;s first job is to redo the room, clean it, widen it, refurnish it, honor the father&amp;rsquo;s clear and helpful side.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Add a room onto the apartment to house the Destructive King and his relatives.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you haven&amp;rsquo;t made two rooms, furnished them we can&amp;rsquo;t expect our father, living or dead, to move in. &lt;strong>Then you can think of inviting a mentor in. He&amp;rsquo;ll also need two rooms.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Same for king. The King is a &amp;ldquo;man of the world&amp;rdquo; and he will never come to live in these cheap one-room apartments we have available.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>After the mentor has come, we might think of inviting the King to the refurbished rooms where the mentor has lived.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-male-as-a-set-apart-being">The Male As a Set-Apart Being&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>each child begins in the womb as female, and the fetus chosen to be male goes through hundreds of changes before he is born.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>a stone, while attached to the mountainside or the bedrock, is female. It becomes a male stone when it is moved away from its quarry place and set up by itself.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There are no good fathers in the major stories of Greek mythology, and very few in the Old Testament.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Whatever the father gives us, it will not be the same of closeness that our mother offered.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In many traditional cultures the men older than the father give and teach nurturing.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mother -&amp;gt; Earth -&amp;gt; old men.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Father&amp;rsquo;s birth gift is one thing, and old men&amp;rsquo;s gift another.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Father contributes to the love of knowledge, love of action, and the ways to honor the world of things. He gave and gives a sheathing, or envelope, or coating around the soul made of intensity, shrewdness, desire to penetrate, liveliness, impulse, daring. His gift cannot be quantified.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The perceived absence of the father is actually the absence of the King.&lt;/strong> Addiction does not have to do with Colombian drug logs, but with the absence of the King.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="the-meeting-with-the-god-woman-in-the-garden">The Meeting with the God-Woman in the Garden&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="the-maternal-feminine-and-the-private-feminine">The Maternal Feminine and the Private Feminine&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The boy, after he left with the Wild Man, has been introduced well to soul.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The boy is about to meet the feminine in a non maternal form, in its powerful, blossoming, savvy, wild, investigating, erotic, playful form.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Celts do a great deal of work in distinguishing two forms of feminine energy, or &amp;ldquo;yin&amp;rdquo;, an earthly form and a starry, moonlike or sunlike form.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The moon is attractive to the sun, and draws light from the sun.&lt;/strong> So the call her the &amp;ldquo;Silver Woman&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;The Woman Who Loves Gold&amp;rdquo; is not contradictory.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-story-meeting-the-kings-daughter">The Story: Meeting the King&amp;rsquo;s Daughter&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Meeting with the feminine woman after the ashes. &lt;strong>Fruitful meeting of that sort can only happen after the man has left the cellar and gone into &amp;ldquo;the garden&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The cook took pity on the boy and exchanged him for the gardener boy.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>kairos: the right moment for what was lying hidden in one&amp;rsquo;s fate to be revealed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>sunlight hits the gold hair, bounce of the wall to princess&amp;rsquo; chamber, from there into her eyes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mercury or Hermes watches over the process of alchemy.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="entering-the-garden">Entering the Garden&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>European walled garden of the Middle Ages contains &lt;em>fons mercurialis&lt;/em>, Mercury&amp;rsquo;s Well, or the Well of Hermes.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Hermes guides the forming of containers, the establishment of boundaried places.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Entering the garden we escape the rain of blowers offered by &amp;ldquo;the world&amp;rdquo; and find a temporary shelter.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Where springs not fail&amp;rdquo; is a quality of garden.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The walled garden also is a place to develop introversion.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>gr:Pluto = &amp;ldquo;wealth&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>For men an unnamed god of duty holds down the surface of the earth. There a man makes a stand, makes an empire, but sooner or later, if he&amp;rsquo;s lucky, the time comes to go inward, and to live in &amp;ldquo;the garden&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>It is in the garden that a man finds the wealth of psyche.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>In the walled garden, as in the alchemical vessel, new metals get formed and the old ones melt. The lead of depression melts and becomes grief. The drive for success, an insistent tin, joins with Aphrodite&amp;rsquo;s copper, and makes bronze, which is good to make both shields and images of the gods.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>This new work in the garden means a coming out of basement space into wind and weather.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>In the garden we&amp;rsquo;re still doing work &amp;ldquo;in the darkness&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In the garden the soul and nature marry. &lt;strong>When we love cultivation more then excitement we are ready to start a garden.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The most important events in the lives of the great lovers take place in the Garden Not Open to Everyone.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The enclosed garden encourages true desire for the infinite more than the greed for objects.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Renaissance accounts: it was not unusual for a young man to take two or three years off, and spend it learning to be a lover. Learn to play a musical instrument, learn poems &amp;ldquo;by heart&amp;rdquo;, practice setting them to his own music, and then sing them to introverted women sitting behind iron window bars.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>To lovers everything looks better&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Lovers are full of praise&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Making a garden, and living in it, means attention to boundaries.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Addiction to perfection amounts to having no garden. Shame keeps us from cultivating a garden.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-woman-with-golden-hair-and-delicious-confusion">The Woman with Golden Hair and Delicious Confusion&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>they saw the Track of the Moon on the Water and were deliciously confused (teenage boys upon seeing a teenage beauty).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>One man about 35 told me: After a few months, everything collapses; she becomes an ordinary woman.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The glory of the Woman with Golden Hair drifts down from its eternal luminous space onto a public figure.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>During the 12th and 13th centuries all this was understood.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Wild flowers would please here more.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>We&amp;rsquo;re on the way from overly obedient man to wildness.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>We move from Saint George toward the dragon.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When a man is ready to make a decisive move towards &amp;ldquo;The Legends&amp;rdquo;, a feminine figure whose face &amp;ldquo;looks both ways&amp;rdquo; may appear in his dreams. One looks toward the world of rule and laws, the other toward wildness, adult manhood, moistness, desire. She is the Woman with the Golden Hair.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>She resembles Shakti, erect, instigating, fiery, outrageous.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="hermes-and-the-god-woman">Hermes and the God-Woman&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Hermes is the god if the interior nervous system. His energy is also called Odin, Mercury.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>True learning doesn&amp;rsquo;t take place unless Hermes is present.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The whole Ph.D. system was created by Germanic Hermes-killers. Hermes is magical, detail-loving, obscene, dancelike, goofy, and not on a career track.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>What people call a Freudian slip is really a Hermes precision.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mercury is the nearest of all planets to the sun, so so he is the sun&amp;rsquo;s closest relative.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mercury has the ability to liquefy gold and silver. In the presence of Hermes, a flow between the masculine and feminine in our story has begun to happen.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Hermes and Aphrodite go very well together.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Whatever one receives in the garden is to be given away. And the head covering needs to remain on. In the general the public wants artists to show their gold immediately. Iron John story implies be cautious about showing paintings at the twenties or publishing a book too early.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Once the garden - which may take ten years to develop - has been experienced, then we could say the young man has begun to honor his own soul, has learned to become a lover, and has learned to dance.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="to-bring-the-interior-warriors-back-to-life">To Bring the Interior Warriors Back to Life&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>warriorhood follows the garden - Celts: &amp;ldquo;Never give a sword to a man who can&amp;rsquo;t dance.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-warriors-inside">The Warriors Inside&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>warriors, mythologically, lift their swords to defend the king.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The inner warriors do not cross boundary aggressively&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>when our parents do not respect our territory at all, their disrespect seems overwhelming proof of our inadequacy.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the child, stiffens with shock, and falls into &lt;strong>timeless fossilized confusion of shame.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-outer-or-disciplined-warrior">The Outer, or Disciplined, Warrior&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Indo-European civilizations: the King, the Warrior, the Farmer. There are three sorts of ceremonies, three sorts of living life, three world views, three gods and goddesses for each way.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Romans: Jupiter, Mars, Quirinus&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Greeks: Zeus and Hera, Ares, Dionysus and Ariande&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Northern Europe: Odin, Thor, Frey and Freya&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>quality of a true warrior is that he is in service to a purpose greater than himself - to a transcendent cause.&lt;/strong> Mythologically, he&amp;rsquo;s in service to a True King. If the King he serves is corrupt, or there is no King and all, and he&amp;rsquo;s serving greed, or power, then he&amp;rsquo;s no longer a warrior, but a solder.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Japanese story: pond has lost its King; uncertain what to do, the pond&amp;rsquo;s inhabitants finally elect a heron (who&amp;rsquo;s in Japan is associated with the warrior) to be King. The heron eats up everyone in the pond.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>When the warrior is in service to a True King - to a transcendent cause - he does well and his body becomes a hardworking servant, which he requires to endure cold, heat, pain, wounds, scarring, hunger, lack of sleep, hardship of all kings.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A clawed hand takes the comfort-loving baby away, and an adult warrior inhabits the body.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Strategy as an essential quality of true warrior. Includes cunning, worldliness, intelligence.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-eternal-or-sacred-warrior">The Eternal, or Sacred, Warrior&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The physical warrior loves the battlefield. The Holy Warrior loves the field of good and evil. Light vs. Darkness.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A Sacred King and Queen live in the Luminous Realm, but the Holy Warrior also lives there.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Sacred Warrior has a blessed side and a poisoned side.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When the Holy Warrior falls, he entangles the warriors in the two other places in his fall.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Lover and warrior mingles. Nowadays that mingling is mostly gone. The physical warrior disintegrated into solder when mechanized warfare come on. Ares it not present on the contemporary battlefield.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The disciplined warrior, made irrelevant by mechanizes war, disdained and abandoned by high-tech culture, is fading in American men. The fading of the warrior contributes to the collapse of civilized society.&lt;/strong> A man who cannot defend his own space cannot defend women and children. The poisoned warriors called drug lords prey primarily for recruits on kingless, warriorless boys.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Our story goes back to a time when the warrior was still honored.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-story-the-battle-scene">The Story: The Battle Scene&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>it is our own psyche (Kingdom) that has been invaded.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The invasion is more than a distraction, the story says that the King is losing the battle.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Time for the warrior in us to learn to fight. We notice that in the story the warrior pursues the battle to the end - no halfway measures in mind, no pulling back.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mithraic cave: &amp;ldquo;Just as the God kills the bull, I kill my own passions.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The battle we are discussing happens in a ritual space, and we expect that some sort of wheat, or corn, or honey will come from these &amp;ldquo;bodies&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/strong> Bible: bees make honey inside the dead body of the hostile lion.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Being passive, hiring an expert to fight our enemy, won&amp;rsquo;t do.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The enemy in our story is never named.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="gaining-a-four-legged-horse">Gaining a Four-legged Horse&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Four&amp;rdquo; is complete - four-gated city, four directions, for rivers of Paradise, four Seasons, four letters of the Holy Name.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The horse reminds of the animal side of human beings, and of the body. The rider stands for the intelligence or the intellect or mind.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The fourth leg is a shamed leg. The animal has been crippled by shame.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When we were very tiny, our horse had all four legs. By the time the child in our culture is twelve, at least one of the legs will be crippled by shame.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>We need an older man, or a mentor, who will provide is with a four-legged horse. We know we have to return it, but just the experience what it is to ride a horse without a crippled legs, even for a few minutes, is worth it all.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Iron John, lending us the horse, does not away with out early shaming; that cannot be done away with. But we can work to prevent further shaming. And we can learn what connection we still have to that earlier, four-legged horse.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="warriorhood-in-teaching-in-literature-and-in-science">Warriorhood in Teaching, in Literature and in Science&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>disappearance of fierce debates is a loss. &lt;strong>When the playful verbal combats disappears, then warriorhood becomes reduced to wrestling, football, the martial warfare, blood-and-guts movies.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Science adopted generational struggle during the Renaissance as a means of progress, and still uses it. Blake fought a mental fight against Newton.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The collapse of the warrior means that the sword is thrown away.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-pelasgian-creation-myth">The Pelasgian Creation Myth&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>more than one American man today needs a sword to cut his adult soul away from his mother-bound soul.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>sharp interior sword. Tibetans refer to it as &amp;ldquo;the Vajra sword&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>We may need a sword to cut us apart from our own self-pity.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Pelasgian creation myth: Once upon a time there was an egg floating on the ocean. Then a sword cut the egg in two. It turned out that Eros was inside the egg.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>No sword, no Eros in the World.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Such a history of creation is history of discriminations. Great Cutter arrived and divided matter into heavy and light. Then he appeared once more and divided the light stuff that became Fire and Air. Then he divided the heavy matter into Earth and Water.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The Divine Cutter - Logos&lt;/strong> - kept dividing.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>These cuttings resulted in the finely articulated, singing, beautifully detailed, shining world of minute particulars that the landscape painters love.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Cutter leaves behind its tracks as pair of opposites that exist everywhere.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung: Animals always remain what they are. But human beings are suggestible and can lose distinction. When they merge into &amp;ldquo;the masses&amp;rdquo;, they fall into indistinctiveness.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gnostics: &lt;strong>Pleroma - place of enormous abundance, but also enormous indistinction.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;prodigious complexity&amp;rdquo; we all love depends both in nature and in culture on a love of distinctiveness.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="warriorhood-in-marriage-and-relationship">Warriorhood in Marriage and Relationship&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>conscious fighting is great help in relationships between men and women.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung: &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;American marriages are the saddest in the whole world, because the man does all his fighting at the office.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>When shouts of rage come out of the man, it means his warriors have not been able to protect his chest;&lt;/strong> the lances have already entered, and it is too late.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Begin identifying the weapons that have come down through their family lines. Short dagger used unexpectedly, spiked mace which swings down onto the soldier&amp;rsquo;s head, broad indiscriminate sword, doorway lance&amp;hellip;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A good fight gets things clear, and I think women long to fight and to be with men who know how to fight well.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When both use their weapons unconsciously or without naming them, both man and woman stumble into the battle, and when it is over the two interior children can be badly wounded.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The adult warrior inside both men and women, when trained, can receive a blow without sulking or collapsing, knows how to fight for limited goals, keeps the rules of combat in mind, and is able to keep the fighting clean and to establish limits.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If a woman has a fair argument, it is not right for the man to leave; he should stay and fight.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Anger comes from personal level, rage from an archetypal core.&lt;/strong> It comes out of centuries of abuse. &lt;strong>If taken into relationships, it destroys.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The interior warrior in both men and women can help them to fight on the human plane.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If men and woman have only soldiers or shamed children inside, they will have to settle for damaging battles constantly.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="iron-vs-copper">Iron vs. Copper&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Iron belongs to Mars and Ares. Iron relates to blood because of the red hiding in it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Two kinds of iron: magnetic associated with sky-gods, that has &amp;ldquo;fallen from heavens&amp;rdquo; and ordinary, with earthly dark gods, such as Set, who pursues and kills the solar god, Osiris.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Iron often considered lucky - horseshoes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Iron associated with intellect and spiritual warfare.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The Vajra sword should cut apart what has been inappropriately joined.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What if we feel to young to inhabit the dangerous space between male and female? A child can easily become a professional bridge. Conducting metal - copper.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mother and father talk through the child.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Copper is such a good conductor, that the boy doesn&amp;rsquo;t heat up.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Intense isolation of the father. Intensity of female suffering.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The child loses his distinctiveness by learning to be a conductor.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The more the man agrees to be copper, the more he becomes neither alive nor dead, but an amorphous, demasculinized, half-alive psychic conductor.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Conducting large amounts of charm and niceness is also dangerous.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ingesting excessive amounts of copper is an occupational hazard for therapists, priests, ministers, resembling the hazards of ingesting the lead that some factory workers endure.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Men and women, often become conductors not from bravery or openness to change, but from a longing for comfort, for peace in the house, for padded swords, for protective coloration, a longing to be the quail hiding in fall reeds.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Becoming a conductor is not achieving andrygony. &lt;strong>Hermaphrodite is an image from alchemy and becomes possible on an inner plane after years of distinctiveness, years of cutting, opposites and discrimination. A false androgyny is achieved early through conduction, but usually neither Hermes nor Aphrodite are present.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="sustaining-the-tension-between-opposites">Sustaining the Tension Between Opposites&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>We lose our childhood and a lot of playfulness by becoming copper wires.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We become suspicious of all forms of merging. It is right to &lt;strong>examine all mergings:&lt;/strong> merging of molester and victim, of tyrant and citizen, of company and employee, of group mind and personal mind, of husband and wife.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Men and women, must learn, when faced with excessive merging, to say as the little boy did: &amp;ldquo;Get away! Shut up!&amp;rdquo;. Some merging is right, some is not. &lt;strong>Our intuition will tell us when the merging is appropriate; then it is the warrior inside who can teach us how to hold boundaries.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>able to sustain the tension between opposites, with neither attitude understood as wrong, but different.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Choice: bridging opposites with Aphrodite&amp;rsquo;s metal, copper, or living in the opposites, while not coming down hard on either side.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="living-in-the-opposites">Living in the Opposites&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>live between opposites, not only recognising that they exist, but rejoicing that they exist.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>does not mean identifying with one side and then belittling the other, regarding it as enemy.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Rejoicing in the opposites means pushing the opposites apart with our imaginations as to create space and then enjoying the fantastic music coming from each side.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Catholic church, obsessed with the opposites of pagan and Christian attitude, identified with one side during the Inquisition and the result was disastrous. In any religion it is tempting for ascetic men to identify with the male pole. Then, disguised as spiritual warriors they are angry at women all through life.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="admiring-paris-choice">Admiring Paris&amp;rsquo; Choice&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ares&amp;rsquo; sister was Eris (Discord), she was the one who caused trouble for Paris lending him a golden apple.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Paris saw Hera and her Rooted Earth Energy, Aphrodite and her Erotic Joy, and Athena and her Estatic Spiritual Knowledge.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Choosing a goddess is very different from identifying with one side of pair opposites. The question here is what you really love. &lt;strong>Eris says choose what you want and then pay for it.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;the one precious thing&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>At the instant Paris indicates his choice with his wand, the king wakes up.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>New Age people are in general addicted to harmony. Child does not become adult until it breaks addiction to harmony, chooses one precious thing, and enters into a joyful participation in the tensions of the world.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The battle happens over and over. &lt;strong>Each time we use the warrior well, we&amp;rsquo;re awakening the King.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="moving-from-copper-to-iron">Moving from Copper to Iron&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The process of reviving inner warriors goes on for years. Imaginative, not so much physical work.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The warrior&amp;rsquo;s task is to warn us when the person talking to us intends to pass on some of his or her shame.&lt;/strong> (sa:han)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;ll be shamed by you, if that&amp;rsquo;s all right with you&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Accepting thorns as well as the rose, living in scarcity, doing the unpleasant, avoid talk of how things might be better.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Conducting is unconscious and naming it helps move it to communication. &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;ll be a conductor for you any longer&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Odyssey says there are suitors inside who want to marry the soul. These toothy suitors have plans for you life. If a person never lifts the sword, he might get high marks for gentleness, but he may end up as a slave to the suitors or target of an arranged wedding.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Now that the images of eternal warrior and outward warrior no longer provide the model, one major task of contemporary men is to &lt;strong>reimagine the value of the warrior in relationships, in literary studies, in thought, in emotion&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the energy that loves to fight need to learn to play all over again.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="riding-the-red-the-white-and-the-black-horses">Riding the Red, the White, and the Black Horses&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>our society produces a plentiful supply of boys but seems to produce fewer and fewer men. We have no idea how to produce men.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Michael Ventura: &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;The Age of Endarkenment&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For about forty years, the young in our culture have generated forms - music, fashions, behaviours - that prolong the initiatory moment &amp;hellip; as though hoping to be something initiated by chance somewhere along the way.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The prolongation of the initiatory moment has everything to do with the massive drug market in the US.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="an-overview-of-classic-initiation">An Overview of Classic Initiation&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Five stages:
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>bonding with mother and separation from mother.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>bonding with father and separation from the father&lt;/li>
&lt;li>arrival of mentor, who helps to man to rebuild the bridge to his own greatness/essence and to his &amp;ldquo;Gold Head.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>apprentice to a hurricane energy such as the Wild Man, or the Warrior, or Dionysus, or Apollo. When he has done well, the young man receives a drink from the waters of the god (Such a drink is one thing the adolescents are asking for).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>marriage with the Holy Women or the Queen.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The personal father draws down both the orderly and twisted/poisoned side of the Sacred King.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>From Great Mother also her accepting, nourishing, praising positive side flows down to the son. But she&amp;rsquo;s got also a &lt;strong>Twisted, possessive side,&lt;/strong> for she too is an immense hurricane energy that puts her clawed hand through the wall. &amp;ldquo;It is necessary to steal the key from under mother&amp;rsquo;s pillow.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>conscious mother, aware of the power she is exercising over the child, and &lt;strong>unconscious mother, who keeps running Great Mother programs in her grain over and over, hardly distinguishing between partnership and domination.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Twisted side of Great Mother &lt;strong>doesn&amp;rsquo;t want the boy to pass out of her realm. She does not curse him as the Twisted side of the Sacred King, but she holds him.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It isn&amp;rsquo;t the personal mother who imprisons the son - she wants him to be free. It is the possessive or primitive side of the Great Mother.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Stepmother&amp;rdquo; is a code word in fairy tales for Poisoned Side of the Great Mother.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Collectivized education puts whole nations to sleep.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sometimes the intellectual ideas the mother brings to the son late at night are a blessing, sometimes not - the boy could end up years later isolated in a high mental tower. If the union takes place on a feeling level, he could end up imprisoned under the water.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sioux were more aware of the possibilities of psychic incest between mother and son.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Frank disclosure is often better than silence, but it becomes harmful if the son feels he has to do something about it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In American culture two trends come together, emphasis on adult man&amp;rsquo;s inadequacy and woman&amp;rsquo;s increased awareness of her own interior emotional richness. Hope for change and fulfillment falls on young sons.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>at forty or forty-five, he realizes that his task throughout his life has been to be substitute husband, lover, and soul companion for his mother.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the boy finds in himself an inexplicable anger, a rage, that prevents the mother&amp;rsquo;s dream of delicate man from becoming real.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>how difficult it is to become a conscious father and a conscious mother.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>son didn&amp;rsquo;t save his mother. He failed to replace his father and so father is in shame, but the son is in guilt.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>a traditional strategy, when one feels too much guilt, is to bite off one part of your body, and throw it behind you. A man in guilt man decide to fail during the first half of his life.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Some men who fail to rescue their mothers become therapist, and some attempt to rescue a woman over and over.&lt;/strong> They bite off the finger of their emotions, and listen to other people&amp;rsquo;s emotions the rest of their lives.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>His masculine beauty does not come out, and the &lt;strong>rigid boundaries, the angry boy inside, the dead King, the robotlike interior soldiers, throw his family and his wife into despair&lt;/strong>. His mother did not protect him from his father, as he sees it, and his father did not protect him from his mother. In that state, the two &lt;strong>hemispheres of his brain do not commune well with each other.&lt;/strong> He does not know what his feelings are, they do not come up into words.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>such a man needs &lt;strong>a male mother, in this world or the eternal world, to whom he can bring his three-legged horse and from whom he can receive a horse with all four legs&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-story-festival-of-golden-apples">The Story: Festival of Golden Apples&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Living in the marvelous opposites of the midbrain, its dreamlike furies, its secret defenses of passion, its heightened adrenaline-inspired bloow flow, a man can give spirit to the world, protect the community, and be in passion himself.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The ability to fight well, as well to dance - wholehearted intent to be in the world, is not savory when the man can imagine another person only as enemy.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>gave him a leg wound with the end of his sword.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Men invigorated by warrior energy need the ability to modulate out of the warrior mode.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-golden-apples">The Golden Apples&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>the apple associates with immortality.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Celts imagined paradise to be an apple orchard in the West where death is.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Ritual banquets used to begin with the egg of the east and apple of the west.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Apple is the earth and pentangle (apple sliced transversly) is its secret configuration and sign for Holy Women or Sophia - the soul of the earth.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="threshold-space">Threshold Space&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Protestantism has spread its ignorance of ritual space everywhere in the world.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dionysian initiation work took place in exquisitely maintained ritual space. Greek tragic theater amounts to a transfer of this elaborate ritual space to a public event.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>In ritual space our desire energy does not rush forward towards its climax, whether that be orgasm or battle, but delight replaces fury, and a turn of phrase or a turn of symbol replaces the turn of the sword.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Culture beings very likely with baskets made of reeds that are &amp;ldquo;soft&amp;rdquo; and hold emptiness.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>In ritual space we learn to experience emptiness or the longing and not to fill it.&lt;/strong> Such a man can be in the presence of innocence without moving to have sexual intercourse with it, enjoy his fierceness without acting it out physically, know his mother&amp;rsquo;s neediness without moving to satisfy it. A warrior can enjoy the beauty of his sacred warriorhood without engaging in battle.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>is there to be seen, to display.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Blake called the highest stage of consciousness &amp;ldquo;constant creativity&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;The Shining City of Art&amp;rdquo;. &lt;strong>The golden apple lets one into the paradise of form.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The heron or the peacock and the deer &lt;strong>express in their vivid outrageous display what the absence of shame is like.&lt;/strong> Blake: &amp;ldquo;The pride of the peacock is the glory of God&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To be without a supportive father is for a man an alternative phrase for &amp;ldquo;to be in shame.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Only &lt;strong>when a man&amp;rsquo;s interior warrior are strong enough can he go into the joy of display and enter the delight of form.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Shapeless clothing, verse that is sloppy, chaotic furnishings: all are linked in secret ways to shame. The universe is not ashamed, and it delights in form.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The delight in form, then, moves one away from old duality of hero and enemy, right and wrong.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When a man or woman enters ritual space, each takes actions meant to be seen, and the joy of display helps pull energy away that would otherwise be invested in conflict.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The knights who parade before the King&amp;rsquo;s stands, patiently waiting to receive a &amp;ldquo;golden apple&amp;rdquo;, are lovely emblems of the &lt;strong>new stage in which the infinitive &lt;em>to win&lt;/em> fades and is replaces be the infinitive &amp;ldquo;to be seen&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ritual space, headed by the Holy Feminine and the King, becomes hot enough to allow change.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="riding-the-red-the-white-and-the-back-horses">Riding the Red, the White, and the Back Horses&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>hero or heroine who chances to see a drop of red blood fall from a black raven into a white snow, sinks immediately into a yogic trance.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Red: &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;blood-red thread of life&amp;rdquo;, anger,&lt;/strong> menstrual blood, blood of birth, blood shed by weapon, &lt;strong>red earth, war, witchcraft and sacrifice&lt;/strong> of men and beast.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>white: semen,&lt;/strong> saliva, water, &lt;strong>milk,&lt;/strong> lakes, rivers, sea, priesthood. web of connection that ideally ought to include the living and the dead. &lt;strong>blessing, good fellowship, strength, purity, persons with high moral purposes.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>black: charcoal, river mud, badness, evil, blackened corpse, suffering, disease, lack of purity, night, darkness. death, mourning, depression, left-hand path, crude matter, &amp;ldquo;prima materia&amp;rdquo;, lead,&lt;/strong> Osiris&amp;rsquo; body when in the underworld.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>for the Ndembu, &amp;rsquo;to die&amp;rsquo; often means to reach the end of a particular stage of development &amp;rsquo;through death to maturity.'&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-great-mother-sequence">The Great Mother Sequence&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>white, red, black&lt;/li>
&lt;li>White of the virgin as the New Moon. Innocence&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Red of Motherhood as Full Moon. Love and battle&lt;/li>
&lt;li>black of the Crone as Old Moon. Death, destruction and knowledge&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We all travel this road and it is a broad one.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Feminine mysteries of life and death.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-alchemists-sequence">The Alchemists&amp;rsquo; Sequence&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>black - prima materia, lead, matter utterly untouched by spirit or consciousness.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Beauty and the (black) Beast&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>white: purification, imagination, spirit and humor&lt;/li>
&lt;li>red: rising sun. sulfur appears, flaring up, passion&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>lead-gold path of men and women who ant increased personality, more spirit, occult knowledge, who want spiritual lead to turn into spiritual gold. It begins maybe at 45, not at birth.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-masculine-sequence">The Masculine Sequence&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Iron John&amp;rsquo;s sequence - masculine mysteries of wounding and growth. Red, white, black.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>red: mars.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Gisu and Masai: Initiators encourage boys go express pride, get into trouble, be arrogant, antisocial etc. the young may stay in the red stage for ten or fifteen years. Girls make love to them but never marry them - they are unfinished. People do not trust them.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We try these days to move young men by compulsory education directly from childhood into the White Knight.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Saint George was riding a white horse. Man can have relationship to the dragon - doesn&amp;rsquo;t imply killing him - distorted version of original myth. In some old versions the dragon transforms into a woman, or gives treasure. The dragon is not evil, he&amp;rsquo;s dark water-energy.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Celtic hero gets into relationship with dragon by throwing loaves of bread into his mouth - he has to throw accurately, so we can say precision and skills enters white.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If a man hasn&amp;rsquo;t lived through the red stage, he is a stuck white knight who will setup a false war with some concretized dragon.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Black horse - decisive descent into woundedness,&lt;/strong> and is often wounded &amp;ldquo;by the King&amp;rsquo;s men&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>People who are in black usually give up blame.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>young male moves from red intensity to white engagement to black humanity. Each man is given three horses that we ride at various times of our lives; we fall off and get back on.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Teacher and parents tell us to skip the red horse. Such a man then will have to go back to red later, learn to flare up, and be obnoxious when he is forty.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Black - bringing all of the shadow material, which has been for years projected out there. &lt;strong>Retrieving and eating the shadow.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A man who goes into the black has to &amp;ldquo;walk the rest of the way&amp;rdquo;. It takes a long time to move into the black. When the man finds the dark parts of him he threw away, and retrieves them, other people will begin to trust him.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When he&amp;rsquo;s able to ride the black horse, it will carry him to the place where King&amp;rsquo;s men wound him. At that moment golden hair falls down over his shoulders&amp;hellip;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="the-wound-by-the-kings-men">The Wound by the King&amp;rsquo;s Men&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>leg wound&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="a-wound-to-the-genitals">A Wound to the Genitals&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>possible that leg is a euphemism for genitals&lt;/li>
&lt;li>piece of iron lodged in the testicles.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>In fairy tales iron relates to imprisonment for men, glass for women.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="a-wound-that-lames">A Wound That Lames&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The young man has become more and more in touch with underworld treasures -its ashes, its armed men, its horses - and now the young man is sent to the lower half of his body.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Boy&amp;rsquo;s first would, to his finger, sped him up. Wounded leg slows him down.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Old tradition says that Jesus walked with a limp.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Get &amp;ldquo;grounded&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>No man is adult until he has become opened to the soul and spirit world.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>People too healthy, too determined to jog, too muscular, may use their health to prevent soul from entering. They leave no door. Through the perfection of victory they achieve health, but the soul enters through the hole of defeat.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://dailyrumi.livejournal.com/188693.html">Lame goat by Rumi&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-boar-wound-that-kills-adonis">The Boar Wound That Kills Adonis&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>In old Mediterranean and Mesopotamian cultures, vegetation was assumed to be male. The earth lives forever; the &amp;ldquo;vegetable world&amp;rdquo; dies.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The boar, with his curved moon-tusk, have Adonis a wound in the genital area, and that wound was fatal.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Tusk has a beautiful curve, like a breaking wave, or the new moon, or the harvester&amp;rsquo;s scythe.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Pig was the earliest domesticated animal, and was succeeded by a layer of sheep and for some cattle culture.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Margaret Walker in &lt;em>Encyclopedia of Women&amp;rsquo;s Myths and Secrets&lt;/em>: Adonis: Greek version of Semitic Adonai, &amp;ldquo;The Lord,&amp;rdquo; a castrated and sacrificed savior-god whose love-death united him with Aphrodite, or Asherah, or Mari. In Jerusalem, his name was Tammuz&amp;hellip; Another form of the same god as Anchises, castrated: &amp;ldquo;gored in the groin&amp;rdquo; by Aphrodite&amp;rsquo;s boar-masked priest. His severed phallus became his &amp;ldquo;son,&amp;rdquo; the ithyphallic god Priapus, identified with Eros in Greece &amp;hellip; Castrating the god was linked to reaping the grain, which Adonis personified.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Abraham stopped the sacrifice of Isaac, which was going on for centuries presumably.&lt;/strong> At that time Palestine was in sheep culture, so a ram was substitute instead.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-boar-wound-that-no-longer-kills">The Boar Wound That No Longer Kills&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>There are men who do not survive an encounter with the negative side of the Great Mother, and there are men who do.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When the fight takes place under the care of old men - the grandfathers - the boar attack only leaves s scar. The man himself remains alive, and, when old, is cunning like Odysseus and full of knowledge.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Mythologically, Odysseus unites in himself the adventuresome young man, the &amp;ldquo;puer&amp;rdquo; and the steady old man, the &amp;ldquo;senex.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Ulysses&amp;rsquo; name, becomes literally &amp;ldquo;thight wound&amp;rdquo;. He receives wound and lives.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When Odysseus returns secretly to Ithaca, he stays in swine herder&amp;rsquo;s hut (pigs again).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Distinction between the boar wound that takes the boy to paradise and the boar wound that leaves him with a scar on his thigh. If we have that scar, our &amp;ldquo;old nurse&amp;rdquo; can recognize us. Our own eyesight apparently is also clearer.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We know Odysseus was the initiated man - he is &amp;ldquo;the thirtheenth&amp;rdquo; in his band when they visit Circe.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>If one has no scars, one becomes blind in the next world, but perhaps the man without scars is also blind in the imaginative world.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Odysseus gives evidence that the scar helps him see and escape all the dangers (e.g. Circe turning his man into pigs - again).&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-wound-as-male-womb">The Wound As Male Womb&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dionysus was born from Zeus&amp;rsquo; tight. Because Dionysus&amp;rsquo; destiny was to be &amp;ldquo;A Man with Two Mothers&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Siberian shaman needs be a wounded man. Spear gave Christ a wound before his death&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Spear when drawn is also phallus, wound a vulva.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>It is as if the boar is to the young man as a man is to woman. The boar opens a sexual passage; he crates sheath; the young man receives female opening.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-wound-as-a-mans-commitment-to-the-god-of-grief">The Wound As a Man&amp;rsquo;s Commitment to the God of Grief&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The Titans gave Dionysus a minor wound when he was an infant, and then while he was distracted tore him apart and ate him. He was reconstituted from the heart, which the Titans overlooked. &lt;strong>Dionysus stands for the ecstasy that can come from tearing and being torn. The ecstatic wine comes only if the cluster of grapes is torn apart, trampled, enclosed.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Ethical philosophy wants Apollo, morality, and perfection. The pagans want tearing and ecstasy.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Some young men in the past, presumably those guided by the old men, became more and more like evergreens and less like spring flowers.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>No one gets to adulthood without a wound that goes to the core.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>women have two hears: one heart in their chest and another heart in their womb.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The old initiators make the young man, through the ritual space, double-hearted. &lt;strong>Now the man has a physical heart he has always had, but also a compassionate heart.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-story-asking-for-the-bride">The Story: Asking for the Bride&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The man in earth time would be about fifty years old now, or older. Some flower has finally unfolded and blossomed; the golden salmon have laid their eggs; the young man has received through his descent a grounding that allows him to reconnect with some creativity that would have frightened him when he was younger.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Life in a family takes that assurance (of glory) out of one fast; and each of us goes through a shaming time or deprivation time.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Eventually at fifty, or fifty-five, we feel a golden ring on the finger again.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-wild-man-and-his-qualities">The Wild Man and His Qualities&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Rudeness and sarcasm may be savage, but the unexpected is not savage.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The wild man represents the positive side of male sexuality. He&amp;rsquo;s not been clean shaven out of shame and his instincts have not been suppressed as to produce the rage that humiliates women.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Wild Man&amp;rsquo;s sexuality does not feed on the feminine or pictures of the feminine, it resonates also to hills, clouds, and ocean.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Apollo, Hermes, the Virgin may be above nature, but the Wild Man is nature.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Wild Man encourages and amounts to a trust in what is below. &amp;ldquo;Water prefers low places&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Desires for the infinite, for the Woman at the Edge of the Word, for the Firebird, for the treasure at the bottom of the sea, desires entirely superfluous.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>We need to build a body, but not on parallel bars, but an activated, emotional body strong enough to contain our own superfluous desires.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Wild Man can come only to full life inside the man when he has gone through serious disciplines suggested by taking first wound, doing the kitchen and ashes work, creating a garden, bringing wild flowers to the Holy Woman, experiencing the warrior, riding the red, white and black horses. Learning to create art and receiving a second heart.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>He doesn&amp;rsquo;t come to full live being &amp;ldquo;natural&amp;rdquo;, going with the flow, smoking weed, reading nothing and generally being groovy.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Ecstasy amounts to living within reach of the high voltage of the golden gifts. The ecstasy comes after thought, after discipline imposed on ourselves, after grief.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Wild man prepares matter, emotional body, so he can receive grief, ecstasy, spirit.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Rumi: &amp;ldquo;everyone who is calm and sensible is insane&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Wild Man&amp;rsquo;s energy is that energy which is conscious of a wound. His face and body contains grief, knows grief, shares grief with nature.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The hard survivor in us survived to adulthood. Wild Man leads the return to the place of childhood abuse and abandonment.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Wild Man is better guide to that pain as our inner child, because he&amp;rsquo;s not a child. He knows stories and can lead us into personal suffering and through it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Wild Man&amp;rsquo;s qualities, among them love of spontaneity, association wild wilderness, honoring grief, respect for riskiness, frightens many people.&lt;/strong> Some men, as soon they receive first impulses to riskiness and recognize its link to the Wild Man, become frightened, stop all wildness and recommend collective behaviour and timidity to others. Some of these men become high school principals, some sociologists, some businessmen, Protestant ministers, bureaucrats, therapist; some become poets and artists.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If a man doesn&amp;rsquo;t descend to the kitchen, he won&amp;rsquo;t know ashes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Do not want ordinary life; they prefer possibility of intensity, even though it entails risk of failure or insanity, preferring it to the &amp;ldquo;even-tempered life promised to the good servant.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Aim is not to be the Wild Man, but to be in touch with him.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-community-inside-the-psyche">The Community Inside the Psyche&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Wild Man lives in complicated interchanges with other interior beings. A whole community of beings is what is called a grown man.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>King.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Warrior.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lover.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Wild Man - who energizes this whole story.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Tricker - does not go with the flow but reverses it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mythologist or Cook - knows how long cooking should go on, and how to move from one stage to another. Also called &lt;strong>Magician or Magus. Shaman at the highest level. Deals with energies in the invisible world.&lt;/strong> When the emotional body is severely crippled in the childhood, the Magician might survive. Pure intellectual energy not as damaged by emotions figures things out and ascends to keep sane. Perhaps Magician&amp;rsquo;s wise ascension is the way naive man gets born. The Magician is then a great blessing. He moves behind the screen of our story invisibly, sending the young man on to garden, for example, no matter what the King says.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Grief Man. Special figure in men who leads them down into one of their great strengths - the power to grieve. There is a grief in men that has no cause. Our culture gets very little permission to grieve.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Teachers and therapist often have a strong Cook, Mythologist or Magician inside.&lt;/strong> But if Wild Man is not developed, he will become an &amp;ldquo;academic&amp;rdquo;. &lt;strong>If a therapist doesn&amp;rsquo;t dive down to meet the Wild Man, he will try to heal with words.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Grief Man without the Wild Man can become lost in the labyrinth of childhood.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When a man inherits great warrior energy but does not incorporate Wild Man, he might sacrifice other but not know whom he is to be sacrificed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When the Wild Man is not strong part of the Trickster, the Trickster may reverse all flows but have none of his own.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If a Lover lacks the Wild Man, he may not give enough wild flowers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>King without enough Wild Man will be king for human beings, but animals, oceans, trees will have no representation in his Senate.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-story-the-wedding-feast">The Story: The Wedding Feast&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>the despised and lowly becomes honored, the being that is apparently primitive becomes a king.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Some invisible force that we know nothing about has put the sophisticated energy of this being into a primitive form and shape, as if into a cage.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Such &lt;strong>initiation does not take place at any one movement or only once. It happens over and over.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The initiatory road in our story includes eight segments, but another story may offer the same stages in different order, or entirely different stages.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>I don&amp;rsquo;t think there is any one right order of initiation. We go through the round of experiences over and over - at first lightly, then as we get older, more deeply.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A man whose Warrior or Lover has been damaged is already farthest from women. He couldn&amp;rsquo;t be farther.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;A strong power forced me by enchantment to live under the water until a young man appeared who was ready to undergo the discipline and go through the suffering that you have gone through. Now that you have done that, I can appear as I am - a Lord.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="the-wild-man-in-ancient-religion-literature-and-folk-life">The Wild Man in Ancient Religion, Literature, and Folk Life&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="the-hunting-era">The Hunting Era&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ancient man and women see through a veil to a firm, invisible being on the other side of the screen of nature.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Lord of Animals or the Releaser of Animals, crossed the line from animals&amp;rsquo; side of things to the human side.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a compact was made sometime in the past between the human realm and animal realm.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lord of Animals has been associated with the initiation of young men for at least fourteen thousand years.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>In our industrial system we ignore Great Mother and Lord of the Animals. We are some of the first people in history who have tried to live without honoring him and his depth, his woundedness, his knowledge of appropriate sacrifice.&lt;/strong> As a result, our sacrifices have become unconscious, regressive, pointless, indiscriminate, self-destructive and massive.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-agricultural-era">The Agricultural Era&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>In the Indian subcontinent the Lord of Animals transforms in such a way as to become Shiva.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dravidian culture, that was prior the Hindu culture, gave him the name Pashupati and Parvati to his companion, the Lady of the Mountain. Immense philosophical and religious movement around the Lord of the Animals enters classical Indian literature as Shivaism, which merged with earlier animism.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dravidian language shares many words with Sumerian, Basque, Georgian languages.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Shiva keeps wild aspect, but has also an ascetic aspect, a husbandly side, and enraged or Bhairava side.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lord of the Animals in the area around Caucasus, Thessaly, Greece and Crete expands into the god called Zagreus, Zan, Zeus.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cretans named Lord of Animals Zagreus and the Lady of the Mountain Cybele. The bull, the snake and the phallus speak for Zagreus or Zeus, the tiger and the lion speak for Cybele.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>As Cretan culture developed, the birth rituals of baby Zeus on Mount Ida and Mount Dicte began to merge with the rituals around the baby Dionysus (who came directly from the thigh of Zeus).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>As mankind moves toward the mystery of plants, the Lord of Animals can change while still keeping his sacrificial essence.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dionysus is the clump of grapes which when torn apart, trampled, enclosed in the darkness of an ox hide, gives to everyone in the community an ecstasy - a wine. Sufis: &amp;ldquo;Nothing can be sole or whole / That has not been rent&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>gr:tragedy = song of the (sacrificed) goat.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dionysus carries knowledge that comes to the soul when it broods on tearing and being torn.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>In Celtic societies of ancient Europe Wild Man appears as Cernunnos, Cornely, or Cornelius, emphasizing stag horns. In some Celtic lands he is known as Herne the Hunter, whose hunting dogs are white with red ears.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Visualization of Cernunnos found in Jutland known as Gundestrup Cauldron from first century BC. Cernunnos is seen sitting in yoga posture, holding a serpent in one hand and the Lady&amp;rsquo;s neck ring in the other, allowing stag horns and leaves to rise from his head. Al l around him is a company made of dolphin, gazelle, lion and dog. Celtic Arthurian circle keeps memories of him, e.g. in Yvain, where he is named Lord of the Animals and Guardian of the Fountain. Cernunno&amp;rsquo;s female companion has many names, among them Artio - who root she shares with Arthur - meaning &amp;ldquo;female bear&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>John the Baptist, Mary Magdalene - carries some of the feeling of &lt;strong>light hidden in darkness, which we associate with Sophia.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Sophia and Dionysus contain in their legends the secret of a sun that does not shine from the sun down, but rather a sun deep in earth which shines toward us.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Development of the Forest Lord stops dead around A.D 1100. As Wild Man, he is remembered of course in literature and folk imagination.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-wild-man-in-ancient-literature">The Wild Man in Ancient Literature&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>When a young king, Gilgamesh, golden, inflated, greedy for pleasure, beings to cause trouble, the elders say the only solution is to bring him in touch with the man called Enkidu.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Enkidu travels to the city, meets Gilgamesh; the two wrestle, Enkidu wins, and the two become inseparable friends. Enkidu appears a s a hairy shadow of the new civilized city king.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The tale of Esau (Bible) implies that at a certain point in Near Eastern history the hairy main was exiled or disenfranchised.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-wild-main-in-the-european-middle-ages">The Wild Main in the European Middle Ages&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valentine_and_Orson">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Valentine_and_Orson&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Symbolizing union with a women, the ring tempts the Wild Man into the holy and legal bond of matrimony from which he is barred. The soldier and the emperor, with his sword drawn, stalk the Wild Man, ready to strike him down for his transgression against man&amp;rsquo;s civilized order.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Burning Wild Man preceded the burning of witches by several centuries, and it proceeded from the same fear and anger.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-threat-of-the-wild-man-in-europe">The Threat of the Wild Man in Europe&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Pan, Greek god, whose name means &amp;ldquo;everything&amp;rdquo;, suggest nature itself.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Powerful sociological and religious forces have acted in the West to favor the trimmed, the sleek, the cerebral, the noninstinctive, and the bald.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>institutionalized drive of Christianity, which is toward the idea that sexuality inhibits spiritual growth.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --></description></item><item><title>PCA</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-20-pca/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-20-pca/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>non-directive (client autonomy): let patient guide the direction of the process&lt;/li>
&lt;li>emphatically listen (unconditional positive regard): do not fix the patient but listen even if it seams strange, stupid, bad, weak. Allow the person to accept their thoughts to heal. understanding means not judging create a safe environment (also external paraphilia).
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>less inclined to fix things ,set goals, mold people, manipulate or push them the way I&amp;rsquo;d like to be. I&amp;rsquo;m more content to be myself and the another person be himself.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>empathy: get inside the skin of the patient. how does it feel actually to be you?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>be authentic (congruence): no need to be always in calm, be honest. be yourself and let the other be himself too. allow therapist to express emotions, to have a personality.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>live flowing process, not a finished product. allow yourself to be changed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>allow contradictory feelings and be OK with it. facts are friendly&lt;/li>
&lt;li>basically positive (about the direction of the soul)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --></description></item><item><title>James Hollis: Finding Meaning in the Second Half of Life</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-15-james_hollis_finding_meaning_in_the_second_half_of_life/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-15-james_hollis_finding_meaning_in_the_second_half_of_life/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="introduction-the-dark-wood">Introduction: The Dark Wood&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Dante began his famous, fabulous descent into the underworld with the recognition that midway in life he found himself in a dark wood, having lost his way.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Aeschylus, the first great tragedian, observed that gods ordained a solemn decree that from &lt;strong>suffering alone comes wisdom.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Using the words soul and psyche interchangeably.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mystery in which our journey plays out:
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>the immense cosmos through which we are flung at warp velocity,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>ambient nature, which is our home and our context,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>each proximate other who brings the challenge of relationship, and&lt;/li>
&lt;li>our own elusive, insurgent Self, forever asking, insisting, not to be forgotten.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A life that constricts meaning wounds the soul&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung: &amp;ldquo;&lt;strong>Meaninglessness inhibits fullness of life and is therefore equivalent to illness.&lt;/strong> Meaning makes a great many things endurable - perhaps everything.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung once observed that one can travel no further with another than one has traveled on one&amp;rsquo;s own.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>inexplicably, &lt;strong>it is the soul itself that has brought us to that difficult place in order to enlarge us.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>individuation, that is, the lifelong project of becoming more nearly the whole person we were meant to be - what the gods intended, not the parents, or the tribe, or especially, the easily intimidated or inflated ego.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The Self is the embodiment of nature&amp;rsquo;s plan for us, or the will of the gods.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If we are in the service to the Self, we can seldom be in service to the herd as well.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the process of individuation must lead to more intense and broader collective relationship and not isolation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>In most lives, permission to live one&amp;rsquo;s life is not something one is given; it is to be seized.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Does this path enlarge or diminish me?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong> We know the answer intuitively, instinctively, in the gut.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>each of us is obliged to find our personal path through the dark wood. &lt;strong>In the medieval Grail legend the knights, having seen the Grail, and intuiting that it symbolized their search for meaning, undertook to challenge and began their descent into the dark wood. But the text tells us that each one choose a separate place of entry &amp;ldquo;where there was no path, for it is a shameful thing to take the path that someone else has trod before.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="chapter-one-expensive-ghosts-how-did-we-get-to-this-point">Chapter One: Expensive Ghosts: How did we get to this point?&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Paul Hoover (Theory of Margins): &amp;ldquo;We drag expensive ghosts through memory&amp;rsquo;s unmade bed.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If we have not had such moments of genuine confusion, perplexity, and doubt, chances are we&amp;rsquo;re simply living on automatic pilot.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Our greatest sin may be choosing to remain unconscious.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>As Shakespeare observed in Twelfth Night, no prisons are more confining than those we know not we are in.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>the presence of suffering is already manifestation of the psyche at work.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-freedom-of-this-contemporary-hour">The Freedom of This Contemporary Hour&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A young person can&amp;rsquo;t afford such questions, which threaten to erode the ego&amp;rsquo;s fragile structure. But by midlife, one may finally be strong enough, or desperate enough, to ask these questions in a committed fashion.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="thee-silent-passage-into-the-second-life">Thee Silent Passage into the Second Life&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Whatever &amp;ldquo;The plan&amp;rdquo; of their lives was, conscious or unconscious, it progressively seemed to not be working too well.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-midlife-crisis">The Midlife Crisis?&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>One has to have separated from the parents long enough to be in the world, to make choices, to see what works, what does not, and to experience the collapse, or at least erosion of one&amp;rsquo;s projections.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="how-it-begins">How It Begins&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The psyche is always speaking, and its urges will manifest as &lt;strong>ennui, the more conscious boredom, then inner resistance to our conscious scripts, and, as we continue to turn deaf ears, finally as eruption of invasive feelings and behaviours&lt;/strong>: interrupted sleep or eating habits, the lure of an affair, troubling dreams, self-medicating addictions, and so on.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We experience the unavoidable conflict between the natural Self and the acquired &amp;ldquo;sense of self&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The most common characteristic of this kind of passage, is the &lt;strong>deconstruction of &amp;ldquo;the false self&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>It is quite natural to cling to the known world and fear the unknown.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>is it not self-deluding, then to keep doing the same thing but expecting different results?&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>As Jung once put it humorously, &lt;strong>we all walk in shoes too small for us.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The person in the grip of this unconscious agenda cannot see that the outer woman is surrogate for his inner life, which has been neglected these many years. &lt;strong>The problem with the unconscious is that it is unconscious.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung: I&amp;rsquo;ve frequently seen people become neurotic when they content themselves with inadequate or wrong answers to the questions of life. They seek position, marriage, reputation, outward success or money, and they remain unhappy and neurotic even when they have attained what they were seeking. Such people are usually contained within too narrow a spiritual horizon. Their life has not sufficient content, sufficient meaning. If they are enabled to develop into more spacious personalities, the neurosis generally disappears.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It is generally through the experience of unsolicited suffering that we grow larger, not because the unexamined life proved easier.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>What we have ignored or denied inwardly will then more likely come out to us as outer fate.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="chapter-two-becoming-who-we-think-we-are">Chapter Two: Becoming Who We Think We Are&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Garden of Eden: Partaking of the Tree of Life is to abide forever int he world of instinct - whole, connected and living the deepest of rhythms without consciousness. Partaking of the Tree of Knowledge brings the mixed blessing of consciousness.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The birth is also the birth of neurosis, so to speak, because from that moment on we are in service to twin agendas - the biological and the spiritual drive to develop.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Twin gremlins of fear and lethargy.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The way forward threatens death - at the very least, the death of what has been familiar.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>People attack gays for stirring unconscious insecurities about their own sexual identities.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The daily confrontation with these gremlins of fear and lethargy obliges us to choose between anxiety and depression. &lt;strong>Anxiety will be our companion if we risk the next sage of our journey and depression will be if we do not.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Yogi Berra: When you come to a fork in the road - take it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>psychological or &lt;strong>spiritual development always requires a greater capacity in us for the toleration of anxiety and ambiguity.&lt;/strong> The capacity to accept this troubled state, abide it, and commit to life, is the moral measure of our maturity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Anxiety is an elixir, and depression a sedative.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung: &amp;ldquo;The spirit of evil is fear, negation &amp;hellip; the spirit of regression, who threatens us with bondage to the mother and with dissolution and extinction in the unconscious.&amp;rdquo; &lt;strong>Mother symbolizes the safe and sheltering harbor: the old job, the familiar warm arms, and the same unchallenged, and stultifying, value system.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="why-the-tragic-sense-of-life-matters-to-us">Why the Tragic Sense of Life Matters to Us&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>our ancestors believed that we often &amp;ldquo;offend the gods&amp;rdquo;, that is, violate energic designs of which they are dramatized personifications.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>one possessed by Ares will act out of unreasoned anger, with all its attendant consequences. Accordingly, they believed that by &amp;ldquo;reading&amp;rdquo; the texture of one&amp;rsquo;s life, one can identify the ignored or repressed archetypal powers, the gods offended, and offer homage and compensatory behaviours to them to resolve the balance.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>At birth, each of us handed lens by our family of origin, our culture, our Zeitgeist through which to see the world.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Right relationship with the gods&amp;rdquo; as a psychological concept means that we harmonize our concious life with the deepest powers that govern the cosmos and course through our own souls.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>(Is not this deepened journey of the soul, in fact, our &amp;ldquo;home&amp;rdquo;?). The tragic sense of life, then is not morbid but rather heroic, for it is a summons to consciousness.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Who ignores this summons will suffer the wrath of the gods, the splitting of the soul we call neurosis.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="existential-wounding-and-the-programming-of-our-sense-of-self">Existential Wounding and the Programming of Our Sense of Self&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Magical thinking results from an insufficient ability to differentiate self and world.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Lacking other &amp;ldquo;readings&amp;rdquo; of the world, it is natural fora child to conclude: &amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m as I&amp;rsquo;m treated&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-wound-of-overwhelmment">The Wound of Overwhelmment&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Given the message that the world is larger, more powerful, we may logically try to evade its potential punitive effect upon us by retreating, procrastinating, hiding out, denying, dissociating.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I have seen people marry someone they did not love because they felt unable to approach the one they did love, because they had reflexively imbued that other with such transferred powerfulness that they were afraid to approach them.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The second logical response to overwhelmment is found in our frequent &lt;strong>efforts to seize control of the situation.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;The world is hurtful and invasive. You must hurt or invade first, or be hurt and invaded instead&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>We may pursue education, because to understand is to be in control&lt;/strong>&amp;hellip;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Their &lt;strong>urgent desire for power is a measure of their inner powerlessness.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Accommodation&lt;/strong> is a learned response, sometimes even necessary for civilization to survive.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We say someone is &amp;ldquo;sweet,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;personable,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;amiable,&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;easygoing,&amp;rdquo; and most often &amp;ldquo;nice.&amp;rdquo; When these labels repeatedly apply to someone&amp;rsquo;s behaviour the consequences to the person&amp;rsquo;s inner life may be in fact ugly.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Codependence is predicated on one&amp;rsquo;s reflexive assumption of powerlessness&lt;/strong> and the inordinate power of the other.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Learning to find one&amp;rsquo;s own truth, to hold it, to negotiate with others seems easy enough on paper.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-wound-of-insufficiency">The Wound of Insufficiency&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>the unconscious equation is &amp;ldquo;I am as I am treated by others&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>something in us does dream, and brings an invitation to consciousness, to risk embodying a larger sense of self.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>what one lacks within one will seek in the outer world.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>How many marriages are in the service to the hidden agenda of the less psychologically evolved of the two?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Narcissist work very hard to conceal their inner poverty from recognition by others.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>sense of self is predicted upon emptiness&lt;/strong>, derives from early childhood neglect or insufficient mirroring&lt;/li>
&lt;li>any argument or disappointment with them will always prove to be your fault and not their responsibility&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fate dominates destiny, history dictates future&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Food, for example, is especially prone to receive the projections of perceived loss and gain.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Any reflexive response to stress and anxiety, whether conscious or not, is a form of addiction. The chief motive of any addiction is, of course, to help one not feel what in fact one has already been feeling. Breaking the tyranny of the addiction will require one to feel the pain that the addiction defends against.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Whenever we&amp;rsquo;re fatigued, stressed, or whenever conscious control is lessened, these old patterns are especially prone to reactivation.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Seldom are we wholly present to this moment, this ever-new reality, without interference of the past.&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Faulkner: &lt;strong>past is not dead; it is not even past&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>No freedom is possible, no authentic choice, where consciousness is lacking. Paradoxically, consciousness usually only comes from the experience of suffering.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="chapter-three-the-collision-of-selves">Chapter Three: The collision of Selves&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It is far easier to talk in the shoes too small for us than to step into the largeness that the soul expects and demands.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Most of us are brought into therapy on our knees, or at best in a state of disorientation.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A formal, committed therapeutic relationship provides a deeper, more objective, more informed conversation with oneself, through the engagement of another person who has our interest at heart.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The invitation to meet oneself is seldom if ever solicited; it is rather brought on by outer or inner events that force one to question who one is, and in service to what values.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>None of us is pleased to encounter the &lt;strong>false self, the necessary fictions in which we invest, until even we can no longer believe them.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Perhaps 95 percent of our daily functioning is reflective&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Come to live his life as a &lt;strong>conscious, self-examining being.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The ego wishes comfort, security, satiety; the soul demands meaning, struggle, becoming.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Stronger soul seek therapy, the more damaged seek someone to blame.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He had to complain about his wife, not to look at himself.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="depressions-therapeutic-gift">Depression&amp;rsquo;s Therapeutic Gift&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Grieving is an honest affirmation of the value of the original investment of energy.&lt;/strong> No grief, no true investment occurred.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Many people in therapy have learned that &lt;strong>the way out of a depression is through it, asking not what I, the ego consciousness, want, but what the soul wants.&lt;/strong> Only the reorienting conscious energies in service to other values will lift the depression.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Anxiety must be chosen over depression, for it is developmental and depression is regressive.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Need to differentiate the forms of depression; namely, does it come from a biological base, a reaction to loss, or an intrapsychic conflict that, becoming conscious, has great information for us about the next stage of our journey.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="relationship-as-field-of-fire">Relationship As Field of Fire&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>the field of outer relationship is always troubled when we are troubled within.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>it is much easier to blame our partners, or try to reform them, or leave them.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="projections-eroded-projections-renewed">Projections Eroded, Projections Renewed?&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Projections always pass through five identifiable stages:
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>At the onset they feel magical; they literally alter our sense of reality. We are seeing some unknown part of ourselves in the exterior world&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The second stage begets disillusionment. The other does not carry through as expected.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We begin to do whatever we can to reinforce the projection, to recover its pristine attraction.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To suffer the withdrawal of the projection.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>if we reach this point at all, is to become that a projection has occurred.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Every failed projection is quantum of energy, our energy, an agenda for growth or healing, and a task that has come back to us.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="jobs-abrogated-contract">Job&amp;rsquo;s Abrogated Contract&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>a deal is a presumption of the ego in service to its now familiar agenda, which promotes its own security, satiety, and continuity.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Robert Frost: &lt;em>Forgive, O Lord, my little joke on thee, And I&amp;rsquo;ll forgive thy great big one on me.&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>This betrayal by the other&lt;/strong> - by God, by our lover, by our friend, by the corporation - &lt;strong>is a betrayal of our hope that the world might be manageable and predictable&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>our presumptive &lt;strong>contracts are delusory efforts by the ego to be in control&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The world is more magical, less predictable, more autonomous, less controllable, more varied, less simple, more infinite, less knowable, more wonderfully troubling than we could have imagined being able to tolerate when we were young.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="competing-agendas">Competing Agendas&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>If &lt;strong>the agenda of the first half of life is social, meeting the demands and expectations our milieu asks of us,&lt;/strong> then &lt;strong>the questions of the second half of life are spiritual, addressing the larger issues of the meaning&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The psychology of the first half of life is driven by the fantasy of acquisition.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>When the ego prevails, change is forestalled, and spiritual stagnation, even regression, sooner or later occurs.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="chapter-four-barriers-to-transformation">Chapter Four: Barriers to Transformation&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>W. H. Auden (The Age of Anxiety): &amp;ldquo;We would rather be ruined than changed, We would rather die in our dread Than climb the cross of the present And let our illusions die.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>we must recall that the &lt;strong>central, universal message of the world to the child is: &amp;ldquo;I am big and you&amp;rsquo;re not; I am powerful and you&amp;rsquo;re not; now find a way to deal with that.&amp;rdquo; Whatever stratagem we evolve &amp;ndash; approach/avoidance; trust/distrust; fight/flight; control/placate &amp;ndash; has a tendency to get locked in as a core relational paradigm for self and world, a reflexive strategy for survival and means for getting one&amp;rsquo;s needs met.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It is essential that we not judge ourselves, for we cannot be blamed for choices we made as children.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A complex is a cluster of energy in the unconscious, charged by historic events, reinforced through repetition, and generating a programmed response and an implicit set of expectations.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Folk wisdom has long recognized the presence and power of complexes in such homey sayings as, &amp;ldquo;Count twenty before you say something&amp;rdquo;, or &amp;ldquo;Write the letter but wait a week before you send it.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If I&amp;rsquo;m not my ego state, then who am I?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>when a complex is at work, there is always some seizing up of the body - a constricted throat, flutter in the stomach, sweating palms&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A complex takes place when an unconscious stimulus is received.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>historically generated but invisible clusters of energy are activated over and over that patterns &lt;strong>(complexes) form in our lives, patterns which seemingly have a life of their own and are seldom consciously chosen. For this reason, our ancestors speculated that the hand of an offended divinity was at work.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A person in the first half of life is so swarming with the power of these unconscious forces&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Zen saying: &amp;ldquo;Everywhere you go, there you are.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;the middle passage&amp;rdquo; occurs only when a person begins to discern that his or her repetitions, compensations, and treatment plans for life have their origin not in conscious life but in unconscious history.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ixion: the wheel of repetition.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>St Paul: while we may intend the good, we seldom do it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>lethargy - Lethe, the river of forgetfulness&lt;/strong> in the classical topography of the underworld. Forgetting that we are summoned by each moment to make life-defining choices.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Perhaps to &lt;strong>greatest addictions in our culture do not include street drugs, but are television and food.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Blaise Pascal noted that popular culture has become a vast divertissement, a &lt;strong>diversion from the engagement with the Self. Even the king had to have his jester&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>our age, where &lt;strong>lethargy of the spirit&lt;/strong> is merchandised by very intelligent people and lulls all of us into the &lt;strong>sleep of reason,&lt;/strong> and the &lt;strong>slumber of the spirit.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Growing up, leaving home, require two practices.
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>we must take responsibility for ourselves, and stop blaming others:&lt;/strong> the society, the parents, the partner, the malevolent gods.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>we have to look within to see the repetitive core ideas, the complexes, and the historic influence where the true enemy lies.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rumi mused: &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>A king sent you to a country to carry one special, specific task. You go to the country and you perform a hundred other tasks, but if you have not performed the task you were sent for, it is as if you have performed nothing at all. So man has come into the world for a particular task and that is his purpose. If he doesn&amp;rsquo;t perfdorm it, he will have done nothing.&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="chapter-five-the-dynamics-of-intimate-relationship">Chapter Five: The Dynamics of Intimate Relationship&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Rumi (&amp;ldquo;Sometimes I Forget&amp;rdquo;): &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>Sometimes I forget completely What companionship is. Unconscious and insane, I spill sad energy everywhere.&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Of all the ideologies that possess the contemporary soul, perhaps none is more powerful, more seductive, and possibly more delusory than the romantic fantasy that there is someone out there who is right for us, the long-sought soul mate, what I call &amp;ldquo;the magical other&amp;rdquo;, the one who will truly understand us, take care of us, meet our needs, repair the wounds, and, with a little luck, spare us the burden of growing up and meeting our own needs.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>its chief rival: the fantasy that material goods will bring us happiness.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>In earlier epochs the notion that one might find fulfillment in this life was considered laughable, even impious. This world, our predecessors believed, was a &amp;ldquo;vale of tears&amp;rdquo; and could only be compensated by an afterlife.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>It is far easier to be disappointed in the other than to call ourselves to account.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="the-psychodynamics-of-relationship">The Psychodynamics of Relationship&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>All relationships begin in projection.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>As historically charged creatures, we have a tendency to transfer those historical patterns, and their predicable outcomes, into every new relationship.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Either &lt;strong>choice is dictated by the unmetabolized events of the childhood.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If we are sincere, and really do wish to &lt;strong>improve relationships&lt;/strong>, as so many popular books and magazines claim, we may usefully &lt;strong>ask: &amp;ldquo;What do we project, and what do we transfer onto the other person?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>An &lt;strong>imago is a very deeply charged image.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Our intrapsychic imago of the beloved other will most commonly have been shaped by our most primal experiences of relationships. This imago most likely derives from our experience of our parents.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the surest evidence that a complex-ridden imago is in charge is the ready availability of a rationalization to justify it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>This search, this fantasy, is the &lt;strong>chief fuel for our culture - the fantasy of romantic love&lt;/strong>, the fantasy that there is this other who will make our life work for us, heal us, protect us, nurture us, and spare us the world&amp;rsquo;s trauma.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The mere presence, appearance, or context of person B can activate the unconscious of person A, triggering a projection, with its attendant transferential history. When this engagement occurs, powerful emotion, be it attraction or repulsion is activated.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Not only do individuals relate to each other in these powerful but unconscious ways, but so do groups and even nations&lt;/strong>, often with tragic, repetitive outcomes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>When two parties are caught in a mutual projection, they may have strong repulsion to each other or strong attraction.&lt;/strong> When however, this projection is of &lt;strong>attraction, a strong desire to merge with that other occurs.&lt;/strong> This projective identification is called &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;romance&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Folk wisdom observes that lovers are fools, lovers are blind;&lt;/strong> we also speak of a folie a deux because in this mutually projective state, the person is acting not out of a conscious relationship to reality, but out of archaic and often overwhelming power of personal history.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Behind our projections, is surprise, surprise, a mere human being like us. Whoever they are, whatever they are, their imperfect reality will inevitably wear through the projection until a different picture emerges.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Rarely does one truly analyze the phenomenon and discern the humbling truth, that some dynamic, script, expectation, or project from our consciousness has been unwittingly projected onto the other.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The weaker the consciousness of a person is, the more he or she is likely to get fixated in the projection.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Spousal violence similarly derives from the failure to honor the reality of the other when it does not conform to projective expectations. &lt;strong>A weak ego can only tolerate discrepancy by resorting to violence.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Violent men don&amp;rsquo;t have the strength of consciousness and character to own responsibility for what is missing in their own psychological life.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>it is virtually impossible to do therapy with a person &amp;ldquo;in love&amp;rdquo;, just as one cannot work with a drunk.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We find ourselves repelled by a stranger, a character in a sitcom, and for what reason?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Generally speaking, &lt;strong>whatever moves us, whatever consciously or not, will somehow be found as touching a deeply buried aspect of ourselves.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The much greater risk of truly loving the other presents a quite different agenda, a more demanding summons.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>When the other does not conform to our relationship agenda, we often seek to control them through admonishment, withdrawal, passive/aggressive sabotage, and sometimes overtly controlling behaviours. We profess innocence when confronted for we usually believe our own rationalizations.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;we wish to colonize the other,&amp;rdquo; and like most imperial powers, we are flush to rationalizations to justify our agendas of self-interest.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;What am I asking of my beloved that I need to do for myself?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Difficulty of couple&amp;rsquo;s therapy is getting each party to look rigorously at the psychodynamics they bring to their disagreement without continuing to blame each other.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The failed projection is experienced by the ego as a frustration and a defeat.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>inescapable truth of any relationship is that it can achieve no higher level of development than the level of maturity that both parties bring to it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It is not a fault to have a childish region of our psyche, for we are all recovering children, but it is a culpable act to impose that disempowered, narcissitically driven history on the present beloved.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>What another really can bring to us, their greatest gift, is not an imitation or confirmation of our limited vision, but the gift of their quite different vision, their otherness as otherness. The immature psyche needs confirmation to be secure, a cloning of interests and sensibilities, and there is no surer path to staying immature and undeveloped than seeking agreement in all things.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A more mature relationship is based on the &amp;ldquo;otherness&amp;rdquo; itself, on the dialectical principle that demonstrates that my one and your one together create the third. This &amp;ldquo;third&amp;rdquo; is the developmental process that results as we influenced each other in turn;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Consciously loving another obliges risk, courage in the face of ambiguity, and the strength of tolerance. Whoever lacks these qualities will never truly have relationship.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>that &lt;strong>wholeness only comes through relationship with another. Only in such fashion can the third appear.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The more we wish another person to repair our wounds, meet our needs, and protect us from having to grow up, really grow up, the more dissatisfying the relationship will prove over the long haul.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The problem is not romance, but what extra baggage romance is obliged to carry.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>we&amp;rsquo;re asked to confront the essential mystery that we are with the essential that our partner is&lt;/strong>. When we can &lt;strong>tolerate this mystery&lt;/strong>, we are already becoming a larger person.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>What we fear in ourselves we will fear in the other; what we avoid addressing in ourselves we will avoid in the other; where we are stuck with ourselves we will be stuck with the other.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>constant companion of Eros is pathos, desire and suffering are twins.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>the cure for loneliness is solitude&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Without Eros, the life force, pulling us into the world, we would all stay home and perish.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>engagement of the soul&amp;rsquo;s agenda is our real task, this journey is our real home&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Accepting the journey as our home will free the relationship to serve the agenda of life, the agenda of growth, and the agenda of the soul. When we have accepted this journey, truly accepted it, we will be flooded with a strong supportive energy that carries us through all the dark places. For this energy we have an appropriate word. It is called love. It is &lt;strong>love not only for the other, but love o this life, this journey, and love of this task of soul.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="chapter-six-the-family-during-the-second-half-of-live">Chapter Six: The family During the Second Half of Live&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>idea of marriage, with sufficient sanctioned powers to govern and channel the wild swings to which Eros is so often to prone.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>family became the one stable unit in the world of change,&lt;/strong> hostile invasion, depredations of nature, and constant search for food and shelter.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung: When a situation occurs which corresponds to a given archetype, that archetype becomes activated and a compulsiveness appears, which, like an instinctual drive, gains its way against all reason and will.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;How many of my family can I save?&amp;rdquo; &amp;ldquo;One&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>marriage and family therapist know that &lt;strong>family interactions are typically arrayed around its most damaged member. Except in the case of a catastrophic illness of a child, that damaged member is inevitably one of the parents,&lt;/strong> and sometimes both of them in their pas de deux.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Of every family we must ask, &amp;ldquo;How well did the soul flourish here; how much life was lost through the failure of modeling a larger life, granting permission to follow one&amp;rsquo;s own course, or was constricted by the glass ceiling of familial fears and limitations?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Tostoy (Anna Karenina): &lt;strong>all happy families are happy in similar ways, whereas unhappy families find their unique ways of being unhappy.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>having not taken on the journey, remain narcissistic, demanding&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>My advice to parents is always the same: Hold your breath - they will finally grow and leave, no doubt blaming you for everything until they find that their problems have followed them. Try to model the fuller life, and such ethical standards as you wish to affirm; give permission to them to be different, to be, that is, who they are; manifest unconditional love while maintaining standards, boundaries, and reasonable expectations.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Until they can be wholly responsible for their own journey, and not project it onto the child, such parents are not grown-ups either.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What a terrible &lt;strong>dilemma facing a child: &amp;ldquo;Please my parents and die within, or live my separate journey and lose their love.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong> Such deformation of the child&amp;rsquo;s unique journey is a kind of &lt;strong>spiritual violence.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Robert Frost: &lt;strong>home is where you go and they have to take you.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The difficult task is to balance one&amp;rsquo;s own need for personal freedom and personal growth with the needs of others. Failure will ensure burnout, resentment, and depression, which is typically anger turned inward. However great one&amp;rsquo;s sense of responsibility, no good fruit comes from a such contaminated tree.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>rather than mellowing, most people become more of that they already are.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>guilt that compels compliant behaviours is really anxiety management.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>stand up to the anxiety and be the only adult on the scene, the only one capable of knowing when enough is enough.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>I have already told my adult children that I do not expect, nor do I wish, them to take care of me should I become dependent, or even mentally incompetent.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Just as they knew they always had my love, so I know that I always have theirs. We do not have to prove that through some compliant acts.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>family is the chief arena for pathologizing of the child.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The modern healthy family posits the nurturance of the individual as its highest value - all the individuals in that family.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>None is there to serve the narcissistic needs of any other. Each is there to support that growth and feel that support in return.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The more the family can be a holding environment in which differences are valued rather than suppressed in service to the anxieties of a parent, the more each person will flower.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The parent&amp;rsquo;s first task is personal growth, allied with the conscious assumption of responsibility for the growth of others.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>One treats the other as one would wish to be treated in return&lt;/li>
&lt;li>service not to selfish agenda but to the Self, which in turn is service to the soul. &lt;strong>The ultimate test of the family is not whether it provides safety and predictability, but whether or to what degree each person can leave it, freely, and return, freely, as a larger person.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="chapter-seven-career-versus-vocation">Chapter Seven: Career Versus Vocation&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>I always wondered if such parents really thought they were helping their children by enlisting them in their own security needs.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Freud once noted that &lt;strong>two requisites necessary for sanity: work and love.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>many find that their work drains rather than energizes them.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Making a living is the easy part, but far more critical is what liberates us from the limits of our family and cultural history. What values, what ways of critical thinking and discerning evaluation do we possess to enrich our lives? What understanding of history allows us to escape its binding repetitions?&lt;/strong> What personality development and differentiation will we carry with us through all days of our journey?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nietzsche once observed that the &lt;strong>teacher is ill-served whose student do not surpass him.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>unaware of that cause issue when they arrive, &lt;strong>focusing on their emotional state rather than the source of it&lt;/strong>. So often the work of therapy, certainly not to be narrowed to career counseling, is to examine the forces that brought about the original choices.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I discovered that I had lost interest in much of the body of knowledge I had acquired and was more keenly focused on where it came from within us, what it activated in us, and what meaning it could have in the conduct of a larger life. I found that I was more interested in the symbolic life than the intellectual life - the symbolic engaging the soul, while the intellect engaged only the mind.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;May God grant your soul no peace.&amp;rdquo; I came to accept as one benefit of that blessing the powers that moved me from a fine career to an even richer vocation.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Yes, we need to earn a living, support ourselves and those who depend on us, but there is another call to serve, a summons &lt;strong>to serve spiritual enlargement. An that is our true vocation.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>we are more than economic animals.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>most women do not recognize that man have fewer inner choices&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>What was not modeled in the family of origin, what was not made available in the popular culture, becomes a personal task for each of us in the second half of life.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>he had in fact left what he loved, in service to the expectations of parents and spouse, and grown miserable in turn.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>If our work does not support our soul, then the soul will exact its butcher&amp;rsquo;s bill elsewhere.&lt;/strong> Wherever the soul&amp;rsquo;s agenda is not served, some pathology will surface in the arena of daily life.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>We may choose careers, but we do not choose vocation. Vocation chooses us.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In the first half of life there is a place for ambition, for the driving powers of the ego.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung: &amp;ldquo;We cannot live the afternoon of life according to the program of life&amp;rsquo;s morning - for what was great in the morning will be little at evening, and what in morning was true will at evening have become a life.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Thoreau noted a hundred and sixty years ago that we had grown imprisoned by the abstractions we created. His &lt;strong>longest chapter in Walden is titled, and decries our growing enslavement to, &amp;ldquo;Economics&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Contrary to Sartre&amp;rsquo;s bon mot, Hell is not other people; it is ourselves, constrained by the world we have constructed for ourselves, or allowed others to construct of us.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>In the second half of life the ego is periodically summoned to relinquish its identifications wit the values of others, the values received and reinforced by the world around.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the very achievement of ego strength is the source of our hope for something better. We need to be strong enough to examine our lives and make risky changes. A person strong enough to face the &lt;strong>futilities of most desires, the distractions of most cultural values&lt;/strong>, who can give up trying to be well adjusted to a neurotic culture, will find growth and greater purpose after all. &lt;strong>The ego&amp;rsquo;s highest task is to go beyond itself into service, service to what is really desired by the soul rather than the complex-ridden ego or the values of the culture.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>One engages in work because it is meaningful, and if it is not, one changes the work&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Being well adjusted is a trivial goal when one factors in the soul. The soul has no interest in social adaptation as such.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Hindu scripture: &lt;strong>&lt;em>It is better to do your own duty badly, than to perfectly do another&amp;rsquo;s; you are safe from harm when you do what you should be doing.&lt;/em>&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In the end, the meaning of our life will be judged not by our peers or their collective expectations, but by our experience of it, and by whatever transcendent source brought us to it in the first place&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Meaning is found, over the long haul, through the feeling of rightness within. No one can give that to us, although we may allow others to take it away from us.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>At such moments of surrender to the soul, we are in the presence of the divine, and in harmony with its intent.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>we are here to bring consciousness to brute being.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="chapter-eight-the-new-myth-emerging-from-the-psychopathology-of-everyday-life">Chapter Eight: The New Myth Emerging from the Psychopathology of Everyday Life&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>world where we are bombarded by sensations, driven by addictions, medicated beyond accountability, agitated into constant motion, and further from our selves than ever&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>we also had to become psychological, because the spiritually charged images that once linked humanity to nature and to the gods had eroded with the waning powers of tribal mythologies ans sanctified institutions&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>four orders of mystery: the transcendent (the gods), the environment (their home in nature), the tribe (the social fabric), and their own psychological grounding (personal identity)&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What fills this existential void, this meaning gap, this time between the gods who vanished and the gods not yet arrived (as Heidegger put it) is the stuff of our daily life.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Our ancestors could seek the relief of their personal and tribal problems by asking which god had been offended and then offering propitiation to reestablish right relationship with that god.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A culture without living mythological access to the mysteries is a culture in trouble.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>materialism, hedonism, and narcissism&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Without a &amp;ldquo;vertical&amp;rdquo; sense of participation in divinity, humankind is condemned to a sterile, &amp;ldquo;horizontal&amp;rdquo; existence, circling its own absurdity and ending in its own annihilation.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Being connected to the mystery only comes, Jung suggests, &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;when people feel that they are living the symbolic life, that they are actors in the divine drama&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>fundamentalism and the culture of sensation&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Fundamentalism, be it religious or political or psychological, is an anxiety management technique that finesses the nuances of doubt and ambiguity through rigid and simplistic belief systems. If I can persuade myself that the world is perpetually founded on the values of another, culturally limited, less conscious age, then I do not have to address the new subtleties.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>fundamentalism is a form of mental illness that seeks to repress anxiety, ambiguity, and ambivalence.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The culture of sensation - pop culture.&lt;/strong> News that runs twenty-four hours create info junkies.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A modern Dantean descent into Hell might be defined as taking a good thing, asking too much of it, and being left only with it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The culture of sensation can only produce addiction and broken hopes, just as fundamentalism can only produce rigidity and a very large shadow.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Addictions are found in our reflexive, frequently unconscious anxiety-management behaviours.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>dreams, the ongoing commentary offered by the Self as to just how things are going and how they might be better.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>all addictions have as their motive anxiety reduction through some form of connection with the &amp;ldquo;other&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>anxiety is further deepened by the loss of connective mythologies, those charged images that link us to the gods, to nature, to each other, and to ourselves.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>it is most commonly through suffering that we are stretched enough to grow spiritually. &lt;strong>The road of continuous ease results in the circular trap of addiction.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Similarly, paraphilias have us in their grip&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Desire itself derives from a Latin nautical term which means &amp;ldquo;of the star.&amp;rdquo; To have desire is to have a vector, an intentionality, a direction.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>paraphilias&lt;/strong> of our time, disturbances of desire, include sexual addiction, pornography, substance disorders, and toxic consumerism, which &lt;strong>offer to fill the empty space of the soul.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;Success&amp;rdquo; has become an unquestioned cultural icon.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The difference between an icon and a symbol is that the former contains only its own limited meaning, while the symbol points beyond itself toward a larger ream of mystery.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>T. S. Eliot: in a world of fugitives, the person who is headed in the right direction will appear running away.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The erosion of tribal life and linking mythic systems has more and more melted the glue that held us together. &lt;strong>We sit now behind locked doors, in front of glowing cathode tubes, and robotically rehearse our common cultural conditioning.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We can be enlarged only when we are exposed to a wider range of images, such as are provided education, travel, learning, dialogue with others, and the soul&amp;rsquo;s frequent visitors.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="living-myths">Living Myths&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>opened a person or a tribe to mystery.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A person who dreams of possessing a new object, or a position in life, in order to provide some large measure of happiness, inevitably ends in dissatisfaction. The vitality of the object or position, which unbeknownst to the person is an unconscious aspect of his or her unaddressed agenda, has been spent, and has autonomously reentered the unconscious, where it awaits a new goal upon which to project.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung: &lt;strong>People speak of belief when they have lost knowledge.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Whenever the level of conscious attention is lowered, perhaps in times of personal or cultural crisis, the tendency of the ego to project what is not addressed in the inner life increases its fascination with the outer -&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>bewitchment - They speak to something deep within us without requiring us to know our own part in them, or pay the price of consciousness and personal responsibility to truly make them ours.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To free ourselves from bewitchment we are obliged to begin to read the world psychologically:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;What is this touching in me?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Where does this come from my own history?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Where have I felt this kind of energy before?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Can I see the pattern beneath the surface?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;What is the hidden idea, or complex, that is creating this pattern?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Is there something promising magic, Easy Street, seduction, &amp;lsquo;solution&amp;rsquo; here, when as we know life will always remain raggedy and incomplete?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Am I made larger, or smaller, by this path, this relationship, this decision?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The unconscious fantasy of a child is that in taking care of the other, perhaps fixing them, the child guarantees that other will be there to take care of them.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The &amp;ldquo;enemy&amp;rdquo; we face in situations like this is never the &amp;ldquo;other&amp;rdquo;; it is the power of history.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>the individual human psyche is the arena in which both outer world and inner world meet and are experienced.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It is so much easier to be seduced than to assume sole responsibility for our consciousness, for ourselves. This is the deepest &lt;strong>psychopathology of daily life - the routine flight form the summons of the soul&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Being psychological means that one will need to find the new, the personal myth from within.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The greatest gift of depth psychology is returning to us again the possibility of a deep dialogue with this mystery. To be &lt;strong>psychological does not mean that one must enter therapy, although with the right person, that decision can be transformative. It does mean that one ask, much more radically than ever before, what is going on beneath the surface.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>reconnected with our journey, that we found our myth again.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="chapter-nine-recovering-mature-spirituality-in-a-material-age">Chapter Nine: Recovering Mature Spirituality in a Material Age&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The recovery of a mature spirituality is one of the most difficult task of our time.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We flee from growing up and being wholly responsible for our experience.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>move from victimhood to participation in the meaning of our journey&lt;/strong>, and to recognize that in all events, even the traumatic, there is an invitation to greater engagement with depth, with mystery.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>In the second half of the life there are two major tasks. The first is the recovery of personal authority.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We believe ourselves conscious agents, when in fact much if not most of the time we&amp;rsquo;re subject to these authority clusters derived from the fortuities of our personal history and the variegated values of our time.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>personal authority = to find what is true for oneself and to life it in the world. If it is not lived&lt;/strong>, it is not yet real for us, and we abide in what Satre called &amp;ldquo;bad faith,&amp;rdquo; the &lt;strong>theologian calls &amp;ldquo;sin,&amp;rdquo; the therapist calls &amp;ldquo;neurosis&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>task of discovering a personal spirituality&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>confuse the spirit&amp;rsquo;s longing for largeness with familiar institutions, creeds, dogmas and practices.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Our culture is crowded with spiritual snake oil.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>It is &lt;strong>of paramount importance that our spirituality be validated or confirmed by fidelity to our personal experience.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Only what is experientially true is worthy of mature spirituality.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>A mature spirituality will seldom provide us with answers, and necessarily so, but will instead ask ever-larger questions of us, Larger questions will lead to a larger life.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>religion is for those afraid to go to Hell, and spirituality is for those who have been there.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Growing up spiritually means that we are asked to &lt;strong>sort through the possibilities&lt;/strong> for ourselves, find &lt;strong>what resonate with us, what is confirmed by our experience&lt;/strong> and not the consensus of others, and be willing to stand for what has proven true for us.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Symbols help bridge us to the mysteries of the cosmos, to natural events, to each other, and to our own mysterious selves. Mysteries are not knowable directly. If they were knowable, they would not be mysteries.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Symbol and metaphor are our greatest gift, for they make culture and spirituality possible.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Limited as we are, we are nonetheless able to &lt;strong>approach the largeness of mystery&lt;/strong> through the tools of metaphor and symbol.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He (Kant) was not saying that external reality does not exist; rather, that we can only know it subjectively. Our psyche takes the raw chaos of stimuli and organizes it into coherence according to categories of time, number, spatiality, and other elements of our minds.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Teilhard de Chardin came closest to bridging these worlds when he said that &lt;strong>matter is spirit moving slowly enough to be seen.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Over time, the ego tends to privilege its own constructs and confuse them with external reality, or confuse them with the mystery. &lt;strong>Our finite sensibility cannot ultimately know that infinite mystery that has been called God&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The immature person, or culture, proclaims &amp;ldquo;our God is superior to your God,&amp;rdquo; the way children do.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If I insist that my taste is right and yours is wrong, then I have offended your humanity by denying the reality of your experience.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Remember that the word &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;soul&amp;rdquo; is designation of the autonomous energy that courses through the material guises of the world&lt;/strong> - in you, in me, in nature, in dream images and so on (Ishavara).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>tragic devaluation of the spirit has led many to reject the possibility of transcendent and to throw themselves into the addictions and diversions of popular culture as antidotes for the pain of this great loss. It has led others to cynicism and depression.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Early cultures experiences the &lt;strong>world as &amp;ldquo;en-souled,&amp;rdquo; that is, all things being the embodiment or carriers of soul energy.&lt;/strong> The tree had soul (from which we still derive the expression &amp;ldquo;knock on wood&amp;rdquo;, as a summoning of the anima within the tree to stand by us for good fortune).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Comte noted that the sage of animism was replaced by the theological sage.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We see the &lt;strong>transition from the animistic to the theological occurring when, for example, the immense power of the sea is embodied in a specific deity, Poseidon, whose name appropriately means &amp;ldquo;earth-shaker.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>By the mid-nineteenth century many noted thinkers, from Kierkegaard to Nietzsche to Dostoevski, had concluded that &amp;ldquo;the gods had died.&amp;rdquo;. They were making psychological statements even before psychology as we know it, not metaphysical statements.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>cultural forms of the gods, and their attendant value systems, no longer evoked the immediacy of personal experience.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>rise of secular surrogates such as scientism and materialism&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>animist understood that survival, and meaning, depend on the capacity to read the signature of the invisible at work in the visible world.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>One may see in popular theologies the same heresy as in psychology, namely the &lt;strong>confusion of the image with the energy that animates it.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>world is de-souled, when what it needs is reanimation&lt;/li>
&lt;li>religious experience. Most people intuit this threat, this likely summons to largeness.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Dogma serves as a reassuring program of answers to questions that arise&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The dogma itself does not carry the mystery, though it may sincerely seek to sustain the impact. Rituals have the intent to re-crate the encounter with the mystery, to summon up the spirits, and hopefully reanimate the original encounter.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In time they tend to become rigid, inflexible entrapments of soul rather than summers to largeness. Similarly, the cultural forms of dress, behaviour, ethics that distinguish one group from another can grow arbitrary, disconnected, and cultlike and become the source of alienation from other groups&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>institutions - encapsulated entities that are most invested in preserving themselves.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>sterile kingdoms of atheism and materialism, in which no transcendent expression will be found.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Any project to revivify by going back is doomed to failure. New wine does not come from old wine bottles.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>These questions never go away, they go underground, into the unconscious.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>move us, that is set off a resonance within us&lt;/li>
&lt;li>we know that that image has some meaning for us. We feel it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>when the spirit is present, we&amp;rsquo;ll be moved.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>eternal questions will arise in quite different guises in all times, and persist in determining the value of our lives whether we are conscious of them or not.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>inquire seriously&lt;/li>
&lt;li>only when it begins to hurt too much to deny any longer&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>reclaim our lives from our history&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>resonance, that is, inner confirmation as opposed to external authority&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>often the conscious values we adopt, and cherish, are apotropaic defense against evil, rationalizations of our wounds, flights from the terror of being alone, or unwitting confessions of intimidation at the prospect of conducting our lives on our own authority&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>each of us has to make that discovery on our own&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>not psychologizing, that is reducing everything to subjective experience alone, but acknowledging that without that subjective confirmation, nothing finally will have a reality for us.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung is suggesting that the &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;truth&amp;rdquo; within the image can be only true for us if it becomes a psychological fact, that is inwardly apprehended and experienced by us.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Serving a past image unconsciously may very well prove to be that oldest of religious heresies - idolatry! Idolatry is often a comforting artifact of the ego, but it does an impediment of the renewing agenda of the soul.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>dreaming - an average of six times per night,&lt;/strong> we are visited by this other world, which is nonetheless our world.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The new myth will not come from above. Only totalitarian ideologies, or ego-crafted appeals to our complexes, will appear in such fashion. The &lt;strong>new myth will come as it always has, rising from the depths, greeting the tribe, summoning the individual to serve that which enlarges rather than diminishes.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="chapter-ten-swampland-visitations">Chapter Ten: Swampland Visitations&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;In the midst of my day I shall go to the gates of Hell.&amp;rdquo; Isaiah 38:10&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>powerful fantasy of progress that lurks beneath the surface of contemporary culture&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nowhere is this fantasy more identifiable than in our preoccupation with health, with youthful image, and with resistance to aging and mortality.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The avoidance of our mortal transient condition is pathological.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>those who handle aging and mortality least well are those who fear that they have not been in this life, that they have not been here, that they have not lives the life they were called to live. Those most preoccupied wit appearance are typically those most resistant to the task of inner authority, for they continue to seek validation from the world out there.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>suffering that forges larger and larger consciousness.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>magic versus the daily work of constructing our lives, and reward us with only superficial engagements with the wonder of terror of being here.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Pain is physiological and should be always alleviated when possible, for pain can erode the spirit&amp;rsquo;s vitality. Suffering is spiritual,&lt;/strong> for it inevitably raises question of meaning.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>medieval adage: &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;suffering is the fastest horse to completion.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Koran asks, do we expect that the pathway to the Garden of Bliss will be less troubled for us than for those who have preceded us?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>a West African metaphor that someone&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;feet are in agreement.&amp;rdquo; That is a metaphoric euphemism for death.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We are implicitly asked: &amp;ldquo;How am I to enlarge consciousness in this place; how embrace life here amid peril; hot find the meaning for me in this suffering?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>ego&amp;rsquo;s central project is maintaining itself and privileging its own narrow position, we can see that without some challenge to that agenda, we would never grow larger than the messages of childhood and the limits of familial and cultural environment into which fate places us.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>ego&amp;rsquo;s agenda of reinforcement, comfort, order, control, security.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>fantasies of untroubled lives&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung has made clear, fidelity to &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;The Self is manifest in the opposites and in the conflict between them&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="guilt">Guilt&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>guilt is a necessary companion to a life of value, a life in which responsibility is assumed&lt;/strong>, in which moral vision matters.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>acknowledge the wrongs they have committed to redress them wherever possible, or to at least make the attempt to symbolic compensation and restoration.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>unacknowledged guilt is an unconscious anchor that weights upon the soul and siphons off its energy&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>existential guilt&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Deeply programmed into us by adulthood is the fear of loss of the love, approval, and cooperation of the &amp;ldquo;other&amp;rdquo; in our lives, be it parent, partner, or institution&lt;/li>
&lt;li>archaic warning system. Guilt then acts as an internal governor, shutting down our natural selves and recalling the agenda of adaptation rather than authenticity.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="grief-and-loss">Grief and Loss&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Loss seems to be the price of abundance, the counterpoise to the richness of life.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Grief, which etymologically is related to the word gravity, from the Latin &amp;ldquo;gravis&amp;rdquo; (&amp;ldquo;to bear or carry&amp;rdquo;) is in due proportion to our commitment to life.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Greek myth of &lt;strong>immortal Tithonus relates how he found his life meaningless because every choice this hour could be reversed in another. So he petitioned the gods to grant him mortality, so that his life, through his now risky choices, could be experienced as meaningful.&lt;/strong> They so blessed Tithonus.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Grief is honest acknowledgement of loss, which is based on honest acknowledging of value.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>We cannot have the richness without the possibility of loss, and without loss we cannot fully treasure the gifts we have been given.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;serenity&amp;rdquo; is Gelassenheit.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>market-fueled fantasies of acquisition, control and ownership&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="betrayal">Betrayal&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;&lt;strong>betrayal&amp;rdquo; is the betrayal of our expectations for such contracts.&lt;/strong> As Ecclesiastes recognized millennia ago, the rain falleth on the just and the unjust alike. So much for &amp;ldquo;deals&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Those who are incapable of trust live in a conspirational, fear-flushed world and suffer the overgeneralizing, paranoid fantasy of betrayal. Often this sensibility is derived from actual slights, injustices, and abuses in the past.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Such a person, so defended against betrayal, will never experience the richness and depth of relationship. In protecting our vulnerability we blunt all our possibilities.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Most relationships, especially those most intimate, have an aura of disappointment about them, for we silently feel the other has betrayed us by not meeting our agenda for that relationship.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Betrayal may unmask our hidden dependencies.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The subtext of most relationship is dependency, rather than mutual support of the independence of each party.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="doubt-and-loneliness">Doubt and Loneliness&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>In seeking certainly they are courting the death of the soul, whose nature is forever churning possibility&lt;/strong>, forever seeking the larger, forever riding the melting edge of certainty&amp;rsquo;s glacier.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung: &amp;ldquo;People who merely believe and don&amp;rsquo;t think, forget that they continually expose themselves to their own worst enemy: doubt. &lt;strong>Wherever belief reigns, doubt lurks in the background.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>hysterical certainties propagated by political and religious institutions are in fact unconscious confessions of their own insecurity.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Our anxieties lead us to grasp at certainties. &lt;strong>Certainties lead to dogma; dogma leads to rigidity; rigidity leads to idolatry; idolatry always banishes the mystery and thus leads to spiritual narrowing.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the more we seem to know, the larger the mystery grows.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>How can we not doubt everything when the world is so rich, and our conscious capacities so limited? Our &lt;strong>doubt, then is a form of radical trust, a trust that the world is richer than we know.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>loneliness, the place without external validation&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Loneliness is not one of the greatest disorders of the soul, but the fear of loneliness is.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Those who manage to find respect for themselves, who learn to dialogue with themselves, who find that their dreams and other such phenomena are communicating with them from some deeper place within them are not really alone.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The failure to accept ourselves makes it very difficult if not impossible, to accept others.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Loneliness is not inimical to companionship &amp;hellip; for &lt;strong>companionship thrives only when each individual remembers his individuality.&lt;/strong>&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="depression">Depression&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>work our way through the depression to its meaning.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>for who among us has managed to live a life wholly in accord with the soul when we&amp;rsquo;re all trying to serve the cultural agenda at the same time?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;A neurosis is an offended god.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The therapeutic secret of a depression is not found by suppressing it with biochemical agents, but by asking its meaning.&lt;/strong> This investigative approach is enlarging, and the soul will not fail to offer direction if we are willing to be open.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="addictions">Addictions&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>No one is free of addictions, for &lt;strong>addictions are anxiety-management techniques the purpose of which is to lower the level of psychic distress we feel at any given moment, whether we are conscious of the distress or not.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>compulsive character, which means that they have a life outside our conscious control of awareness.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>the subtlest, and most pervasive, of addictive management techniques is habit itself, for habit is one of the means by which we hold off ambiguity and anxiety.&lt;/strong> Simple reflect on how irritated, that is how anxious, you feel when your habits, your daily routines, your conventional expectations are interrupted.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>caught in a circular response to life that can only replicate itself, and the pain that lies at its core&lt;/li>
&lt;li>To ever break the stranglehold of addictions, one is going to have to &lt;strong>face what the compulsive behaviour is a defense against&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>It is to break the tyranny of anxiety without ceasing to feel anxious&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>as Heidegger observed once, &lt;strong>&amp;ldquo;the terrible&amp;rdquo; has already happened.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="anxieties">Anxieties&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>At bottom, all of our problems can be traced back to the omnipresence of anxiety.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Angst is the German word for therapeutical anxiety.&lt;/strong> threat of annihilation is palpable and present from our first to our last breath.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>An acceptance of this angst as normal is healthy; its denial pathological.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Anxiety is free-floating, unattached, not unlike the fog that obscures the road we drive. Fear, however is specific.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Our fears are typically derived from our powerless past.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>when one learns that beneath the current anxiety there is a buried filament that reaches back to the childhood fear, then one learns the secret of the disabling power of the anxious present.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Philo of Alexandria: &amp;ldquo;Be kind. Everyone you meet is carrying a big problem&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Accept the normality of anxiety, seek the roots of identifiable fears in that anxiety, then simply do the best we can and forgive the rest.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="how-do-we-avoid-swamplands">How Do We Avoid Swamplands&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>swamplands are &lt;strong>inevitable and necessary counterpart to our conscious fantasies of power.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The more we have conquered in the outer world, the more the disquiet of our inner world.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>task of life asks that we embrace this agenda of apparent loss as much as the agenda of acquisition that the first half of life served.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The flight from the swamplands of the soul, however unpleasant they may be to consciousness, is the flight from the wholeness of life, a wholeness that may only be expressed in paradox, and any psychology or worldview that excludes paradox is excluding half of life itself.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Wholeness is not about comfort, or goodness or consensus - it means drinking this brief, unique, deeply rooted vintage to its dregs.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The task of ego consciousness in the second half of life is to step out the way and embrace a larger spiritual agenda.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung: &amp;ldquo;A life without inner contradiction is only half a life, or else a life in the Beyond which is destined only for angels. But God loves human beings more than the angels.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Nikos Kazantzakis: &amp;ldquo;the report to a general: This is what I did today, this is how I fought to save the entire battle in my own sector, these are the obstacles found, this is how I plan to fight tomorrow.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="chapter-eleven-the-healing-of-the-soul">Chapter Eleven: The Healing of the Soul&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>devotion to change&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>psychology has banished psyche, or soul, from its serious consideration, in favor of the lesser forms of behaviour and cognition and biochemistry.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>For all the changes that have occurred over the last four centuries, perhaps our greatest loss is the diminution of dialogue about that mystery toward which the word soul is meant to point.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>the world once summoned the priest in his black gown and then, when he could not save, transferred their demands to the physician in his white gown.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Living the questions that serve the ego, or culture&amp;rsquo;s insecurity, will only infantilize. We need questions that ask that we grow up.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="what-has-brought-you-to-this-place-in-your-journey-this-moment-in-your-life">What has brought you to this place in your journey, this moment in your life?&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Destiny is a word that originally meant following a course, as a river within its banks, subject to modification, risking draying, flooding at times, being replenished, but always coursing toward an outlet in the large, tenebrous see of the soul.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Consciousness is a task that renews its challenge every morning&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="what-gods-what-forces-what-family-what-social-environment-have-framed-your-reality-perhaps-supported-perhaps-constricted-it">What gods, what forces, what family, what social environment have framed your reality, perhaps supported, perhaps constricted it?&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>We are not summoned to perfection; that is the realm of gods; we are rather called to mindfulness, to approach such fields of divine reverence with sensitivity, respect and humility.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>deep split evolves between fate and destiny, between the forces of determination and the possibilities inherent in all of us&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&amp;ldquo;Whose life have I been living?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>we are the only character who is present in each scene, so we must be held accountable in the end.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>accountability. If you do not like your life, change it, bust stop blaming others, for even if they did hurt you, you are the one who has been making the choices of adulthood.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We are, in the end, mythological creatures.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>relationship to the inner world (what Jung called the &lt;em>anima&lt;/em>, Latin for &amp;ldquo;soul&amp;rdquo; that which is compensatory to his outer masculine identity and role.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Why would he not have unstable, inconsistent relationships with women when this is the relationship he has managed to his inner feminine?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="why-even-when-things-are-going-well-do-things-not-feel-quite-right">Why, even when things are going well, do things not feel quite right?&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Gnostic Gospel of Thomas: the kingdom of God is spread all over the world and we do not see it.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Clues everywhere! But these clues are so often drowned by the cacophony of messages from the world around us, as well as the committee of complexes within.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>siren calls?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Why is that &amp;ldquo;success&amp;rdquo; in achieving these goals so often feels empty? Why, having followed the plan, served the marching order, does one not feel an inner assent, a lightness which confirms?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="why-does-so-much-seem-a-disappointment-a-betrayal-a-bankruptcy-of-expectations">Why does so much seem a disappointment, a betrayal, a bankruptcy of expectations?&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Joseph Campbell: &lt;strong>we can spend decades climbing the ladder, only to realize too late that we have places it against the wrong wall.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>No person, no role in life, however rewarding, can ever carry the complete aspirations of the soul - only our move toward wholeness can**. Wholeness is not found in perfection.**&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>the youth needs projections to pull him or her into life.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The first half of life feeds on these projections. During the second half of life, these projections lose their powers in the face of abrasions of daily life, and one suffers &lt;strong>ennui, disappointment&lt;/strong>, or even a sense that the presumed contract has been betrayed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Could these so called symptoms prove precisely the &lt;strong>clue for which we seek? Are they not the rejected gods of the underworld, speaking in their symbolic ways?&lt;/strong> Is what week to be found not &amp;ldquo;out there,&amp;rdquo; but beneath our noses? If such projections are necessary for the first half of life, then their erosion, their bankruptcy may be necessary for the second half of life.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What, indeed, does it profit one to gain the world that the projects have offered, and to find the price is loss of relationship to one&amp;rsquo;s soul? It is in the swamplands of disappointment, then, tat the task of personal ownership of the soul may be reclaimed.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>As long as we continue to cruise along, buoyed by the success of projects, we will be seduced into unconscious identification with trivial values.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The bad news for ego&amp;rsquo;s fantasy of sovereignty is that we suffer; the good news for the soul is that we suffer.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The projections, if examined carefully, diminish life through their narrow frame; growing up enlarges life, makes it more interesting, and we might even become thereby somewhat less of a problem to those around us.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="why-do-you-believe-that-you-have-to-hide-so-much-from-others-from-yourself">Why do you believe that you have to hide so much, from others, from yourself?&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The less supportive the environment, the more troubles or preoccupied the family, the more costly the child&amp;rsquo;s disclosures of his or her natural narcissistic needs will prove.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>permission will not be given; the adult must seize it&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>paying of forgotten dues, is the requisite for reforming one&amp;rsquo;s life&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="why-does-life-seem-a-script-written-elsewhere-and-you-barely-consulted-if-at-all">Why does life seem a script written elsewhere and you barely consulted, if at all&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>most important message of life comes from the primary relationship with mother, father and siblings, and then ever-widening circles, the culture as a whole.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The psyche is autonomous and will express another, deeper script than that we received from our fated family of origin, culture, and peculiar histories&lt;/li>
&lt;li>surrender to this will&lt;/li>
&lt;li>sense of purposefulness&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The loss of alignment with the soul is both the origin of suffering and the invitation to redemption.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="why-have-you-come-to-this-book-or-why-has-it-come-to-you-now">Why have you come to this book, or why has it come to you, now?&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>well all retain an intuitive tie to that great, immortal sea from whence we came.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We have mastered the language of the outer world through physics and chemistry, but the principle of synchronicity acknowledges that there is an inner world of causality as well. When the moment is ripe for us to hear, then the word is spoken.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="why-does-the-idea-of-the-soul-both-trouble-you-and-feel-familiar-like-a-long-lost-companion">Why does the idea of the soul both trouble you and feel familiar, like a long-lost companion?&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Jung: &amp;ldquo;It is not I who create myself, rather I happen to myself.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>The soul is intuited in childhood, pushed aside by the adaptive choices of consciousness, and recovered in adulthood only when we are willing to open to it.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>So the idea of the soul, the felt presence of the soul, intimidates while it sustains, and the summons to the ego is to relinquish its fantasy of sovereignty and be held in that fell.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="is-the-life-you-are-living-too-small-for-your-souls-desire">Is the life you are living too small for your soul&amp;rsquo;s desire?&lt;/h3>
&lt;h3 id="why-is-now-the-time-if-ever-it-is-to-happen-for-you-to-answer-the-summons-of-the-soul-to-live-the-second-larger-life">Why is now the time, if ever it is to happen, for you to answer the summons of the soul, to live the second, larger life?&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>We live amid politicians and theologians who infantilize us by fear-mongering, and scientist and psychologist who trivialize life by addressing only what can be empirically verified. We are so much larger than that.&lt;/strong> Just as much theology has forgotten the psyche, so much psychology has retreated from the soul.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>This spiritual homesickness gives us the journey; the journey gives us our life, once again.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Poet Paul Eluard: &lt;strong>there is another world and it is this one!&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Everywhere we look we see intimations of the soul.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Here you are, in this mysterious now.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Called to witness, and to serve, to serve something much larger.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Even when surrounded by many other, your journey is solitary, for the life you are to choose is your life, not someone&amp;rsquo;s else.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Finding what supports you from within&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Agenda of growth, purpose and meaning that we all are meant to carry into the world and to share with others.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --></description></item><item><title>James Hollis: A Summons to a Deeper Life</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-04-james_hollis_a_summons_to_a_deeper_life/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-04-james_hollis_a_summons_to_a_deeper_life/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://content.blubrry.com/sounds_true/PD05604W_James-Hollis_FINAL.mp3">src&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Psyche - Greek for &amp;ldquo;soul&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Who am I?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Knock of the door. Initiatory moment to question.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Deeper voice within us. In the long run tells us what&amp;rsquo;s right for us. Not the ego.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Escaping the dictate of the time and place: right place, right attitude, right neighborhood, right career.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Five stages. Kuebler-Ross. Denial, anger, bargaining, despair, acceptance.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Living an authentic life. Escaping the programming. So much of our life is routinized and patterns. Often good goals. At the same time psyche has another point of view.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nature calls us the sick animal.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Society required compromises and tradeoffs. But the greater the tradeoffs the greater the self-estrangement.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dreams operate within us from a different perspective than the ego consciousness.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We keep mobilizing life&amp;rsquo;s energy counter to the depth and wisdom and purpose of the soul. The price is burnout, boredom, depression.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Feeling function is also autonomous. We don&amp;rsquo;t choose feelings. Feelings are autonomous responses to our circumstances from the perspective of the deep self.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ego cannot account for the autonomy of others.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung: anyone who really discovers the power of unconscious knows from that point on one is not the master or mistress of one&amp;rsquo;s own house. That&amp;rsquo;s a certain dethronement of ego&amp;rsquo;s fantasy of sovereignty, omniscience and omnipotence.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Whenever I need to know something important for me I need to wait.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you wait upon the silence, it ultimately speaks.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is a wisdom in me that is wiser than the conscious self. Those two are not enemies, they need to be in conversation.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fitting in is critical for the child and the infant. But if it dominates the intentions of one&amp;rsquo;s soul, you lose yourself.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Growing up: when I&amp;rsquo;m fully accountable. I&amp;rsquo;m in.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is a needy part in us, that is wanting people to take care of us, lift burden of life for us. Explain things for us. &amp;hellip; Wake up. You&amp;rsquo;re in.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>One of the aspects of traditional rights of passage was ordeal and isolation. One had to learn to depend on oneself. These are the attributes of adulthood. They are not developed by our culture nor by our elders.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Children and adolescents are impulsive, impatient, don&amp;rsquo;t like ambiguity, want clarity, resolution. Too insecure to own their own stuff so they are always looking for somebody to blame it on. Organize their life evading as much responsibility as they can. They are looking for someone to explain it to them. It&amp;rsquo;s a culture driven by sensation. You don&amp;rsquo;t have to reflect upon your self if you&amp;rsquo;re distracted all the time. Our electronic world has made distraction more possible than any time in history.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Blaise Pascal (17th century): Even the king grow miserable if he reflected upon himself, so we invented the jester to distract the court. All of our troubles stem from one thing - that we cannot bear to be alone with ourselves in our private chambers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Our culture&amp;rsquo;s answer to the existential anxiety of being human is distraction.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Little questions give you little answers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Richness of your journey.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fear and lethargy (wants to pull us to the sleep of the childhood) are the only enemies of us. We carry them wherever we go and they&amp;rsquo;re with us.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We long to make sense of things.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If I don&amp;rsquo;t try to make sense out of my journey somebody else will do it for me. Authorities will tell you who you are, what your values are and what choices you&amp;rsquo;d make.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Task of meaning has shifted from the shoulders of the tribe to the shoulders of the individual. What a burden and what a privilege. Psychologically we were never freer. We can use the distractions, avoidance, anesthetization processes trying not to show up.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Walt Whitman: I loafe and invite my soul. Sometimes you have to do that by doing nothing.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Choose meaning over happiness. Happiness is momentary, transitory, feeling state. The problem is it&amp;rsquo;s transitory. Happiness is very contextual, idiosyncratic.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Frank: Logotherapy. Gr: logos = meaning. They can take everything from me but the power to chose the attitude, when I could not choose my circumstances. Final freedom.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We&amp;rsquo;re not against happiness but you cannot bottle it up and store.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Terrible in-between where something at some level has to die which is how nature renews. The ego is never thrilled with that.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Welcome to 2nd half of your life. Something is dying. What&amp;rsquo;s dying is your old understanding. Your old roadmap.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sooner or later we visit swampland places. Here lies a task.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jung: work of an evolved human being consisted of three parts. Insight, courage and endurance.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When we don&amp;rsquo;t challenge our stories they are going to make choices for us. And that&amp;rsquo;s where insight is important. You&amp;rsquo;re not what happened to you. You&amp;rsquo;re what is wanting to enter the world through you. You&amp;rsquo;re in some way the unfolding journey that we have.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If it would be easy we would not use worlds like &amp;ldquo;courage&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If I would not believe in people changing I would not be a therapist, a writer.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Just as we were creatures of adaptation. Security and adaptation were the no. 1 priorities. Power of security often diminishes us. We cling to the shore. We live a small life.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Embrace of ambiguity is what opens us to enlargement. Ambiguity inherently is unpleasant to the human ego. That&amp;rsquo;s what produces one sided behaviour, maladaptions, fundamentalism &amp;hellip; is the effort rid us of ambiguity. With clear marching orders I don&amp;rsquo;t have to stop and think who am I.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ambiguity is what gets us our journey. We don&amp;rsquo;t grow through certainty. We grow through doubt.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We&amp;rsquo;re not here to fit in, to please the world. Not about narcistic self-indulgence. It&amp;rsquo;s calling for humility and sacrifice. What&amp;rsquo;s being sacrifice? That ego&amp;rsquo;s in charge, that it&amp;rsquo;s the boss. Ego&amp;rsquo;s job is to execute as consciously and faithfully as possible what it needs to do to be in the world more authentically.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In a true dialogue with the depths of one&amp;rsquo;s psyche ego will often find itself put into a precarious position. That&amp;rsquo;s where our life takes on its fine edge and that&amp;rsquo;s where it gets most interesting. That&amp;rsquo;s where we get to life the fine drama of the soul.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --></description></item></channel></rss>