<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Psychology on uzak.github.io</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/tags/psychology/</link><description>Recent content in Psychology on uzak.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://uzak.github.io/tags/psychology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Iron John</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-21-iron_john/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-21-iron_john/</guid><description>The Pillow and the Key In The Odyssey, Hermes instructs Odysseus when he approaches Circe, who stands for certain kind of matriarchal energy, he is to lift or show his sword. Showing a sword doesn&amp;rsquo;t necessarily mean fighting. It can also suggest a joyful decisiveness. Finding Iron John &amp;ldquo;What can I do? Anything dangerous to do around here?&amp;rdquo; When he approaches what I&amp;rsquo;ll call the &amp;ldquo;deep male&amp;rdquo;, he feels risk. The Loss of the Golden Ball King&amp;rsquo;s eight year old son&amp;rsquo;s golden ball rolls into Wild Man&amp;rsquo;s cage.</description></item><item><title>PCA</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-20-pca/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-20-pca/</guid><description>non-directive (client autonomy): let patient guide the direction of the process emphatically listen (unconditional positive regard): do not fix the patient but listen even if it seams strange, stupid, bad, weak. Allow the person to accept their thoughts to heal. understanding means not judging create a safe environment (also external paraphilia). less inclined to fix things ,set goals, mold people, manipulate or push them the way I&amp;rsquo;d like to be.</description></item><item><title>James Hollis: Finding Meaning in the Second Half of Life</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-15-james_hollis_finding_meaning_in_the_second_half_of_life/</link><pubDate>Mon, 15 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-15-james_hollis_finding_meaning_in_the_second_half_of_life/</guid><description>Introduction: The Dark Wood Dante began his famous, fabulous descent into the underworld with the recognition that midway in life he found himself in a dark wood, having lost his way. Aeschylus, the first great tragedian, observed that gods ordained a solemn decree that from suffering alone comes wisdom. Using the words soul and psyche interchangeably. Mystery in which our journey plays out: the immense cosmos through which we are flung at warp velocity, ambient nature, which is our home and our context, each proximate other who brings the challenge of relationship, and our own elusive, insurgent Self, forever asking, insisting, not to be forgotten.</description></item><item><title>James Hollis: A Summons to a Deeper Life</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-04-james_hollis_a_summons_to_a_deeper_life/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-04-james_hollis_a_summons_to_a_deeper_life/</guid><description>src
Psyche - Greek for &amp;ldquo;soul&amp;rdquo; Who am I? Knock of the door. Initiatory moment to question. Deeper voice within us. In the long run tells us what&amp;rsquo;s right for us. Not the ego. Escaping the dictate of the time and place: right place, right attitude, right neighborhood, right career. Five stages. Kuebler-Ross. Denial, anger, bargaining, despair, acceptance. Living an authentic life. Escaping the programming. So much of our life is routinized and patterns.</description></item></channel></rss>