<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Diary on uzak.github.io</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/tags/diary/</link><description>Recent content in Diary on uzak.github.io</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://uzak.github.io/tags/diary/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Don't Force Anything</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-21-dont_force_anything/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-08-21-dont_force_anything/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2MQdMrs9w28">src&lt;/a> - Thanks Waldi!&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Life in the present
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Meditation&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Understand the impermanence of life&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Power of &lt;strong>acceptance&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean surrender&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>face every situation with calmness and clarity&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Letting go&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Mindfulness
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Marcus Aurelius (MA): &lt;strong>happiness of your life depends on the quality of your thoughts&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>MA: you have the power over your mind, not outside effects&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Embrace the silence&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Enjoy the journey, not just the outcome&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Find joy in simplest things
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>MA: very little is needed to make a happy life, it is all within your self, in your way of thinking&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The richest person is not the one who has the most, but who needs least - learns gratitude&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The art of &lt;strong>gratitude&lt;/strong>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>MA: &lt;strong>when you arise in the morning, think of what precious privilege it is to live, to breathe, to enjoy, to love.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Let gratitude to be your guiding principle to a peaceful and happy life&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Appreciate solitude
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>You can discover endless inspiration and peace&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>MA: the best revenge is to be unlike him who performed the injury.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Symbolika poslednej večere</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-29-symbolika_poslednej_vecere/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-29-symbolika_poslednej_vecere/</guid><description>&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Večera je na zemi, v čase a priestore.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Je prítomných 12 učeníkov. Deň ma 12 hodín.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Potom nasleduje ukrižovanie.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ježiš je mimo času a priestoru. Už nie je v sprievode učeníkov, ani nie je na konkrétnom mieste.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --></description></item><item><title>Perfection</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-19-perfection/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-07-19-perfection/</guid><description>&lt;p>Do you know what goes hand in hand with perfection? It&amp;rsquo;s boredom!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imagine working hard your entire life for perfection. You improve, then push even harder and improve more. Finally, you become the best. There you are—perfect. You know all the rules of the game, and all the tricks, too. Each game is fixed; you know the winner in advance - it&amp;rsquo;s you! The first game, the next, and even the last, you know the results beforehand. And you start to yawn. Yes, it&amp;rsquo;s become so boring.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Radim Pařík - Argumenty nefungují. Vyjednávejte jako agenti FBI!</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-04-09-radim_par%C3%ADk_-_argumenty_nefunguji._vyjednavejte_jako_agenti_fbi/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-04-09-radim_par%C3%ADk_-_argumenty_nefunguji._vyjednavejte_jako_agenti_fbi/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=guDHr7ccXL8">src&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Vyjednávanie nemá nič spoločné s logikou, je to len bitka emócií&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Predpoklady
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Spoločný záujem
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Podieľať sa na spoločnom vypracovaní riešenia
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ak to nič nestojí, nikto si to neváži&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Spoločná závislosť&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Konflikt - rozdielne záujmy
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Ak máme spoločné záujmy nemusíte vyjednávať - môžete obchodovať.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Príprava (1.)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Maximálny ciel&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Minimálny ciel.
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Lepšia žiadna dohoda ako niečo menej&lt;/li>
&lt;li>otázka: dava zmysel vyjednávať?&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>role:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Decision Maker
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Nemá u vyjednávacieho stolu čo robiť, aby nebol emocionálne ovplyvnený&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Commander
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Mlčiaci vyjednávač.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stanovuje stratégiu.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Buduje vzťah s commanderom na druhej strane.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pozor: nevyjednáva.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Negociator
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Je v emočnom tuneli.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Najmenej dôležitá osoba, je ľahko vymeniteľný.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Na všetko hovori &amp;ldquo;ťažké&amp;rdquo;. Na druhej strana na to odpovie &amp;ldquo;ďakujem&amp;rdquo; po krátkej odmlke a tak udržuje dobrú náladu.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Hovori, čo všetko by ešte chceli&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Odmieta požiadavky protistrany.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>POZOR: nikdy nehovorte, čo nespravíte.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vstup (2.)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Povedať, čo chcete a dokedy to chcete. Ak nepoviete čo chcete, nemôžete to dostať.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Taktická fáza. Nie detaily kontraktu, to je už za nami a bez toho by sme tu neboli.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Riadenie (3.)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Vyjednávanie neurčuje, kto ma lepší argument, vyjednávanie určuje ten, kto stanovuje ďalší krok&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ak nie je protistrana pripravená, dajte jej domácu úlohu.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Eskalácia (4.)
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Naplánovaná, nie prekvapenie.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Súčasť taktického plánu.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vyjednávanie nikdy neskolabovalo na tom, že by sme chceli niečo alebo veľa. Vždy skolabuje na:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>nevhodnom tone&lt;/li>
&lt;li>nevhodnej formulácii alebo, že&lt;/li>
&lt;li>sa niekoho snažíme presvedčiť, že máme pravdu a ten druhý nie.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ľudský mozog
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>limbický systém
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Najstarší, vôľou neovládateľný&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vydáva tri pokyny
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>ústrn,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>útek,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>útok.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>neokortex
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>logika,&lt;/li>
&lt;li>najväčší klamár&lt;/li>
&lt;li>logiku človeka behom vyjednávania nemôžeme ovplyvniť&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>amygdala
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>emočná časť&lt;/li>
&lt;li>počas vyjednávania vplývame na amygdalu.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>reaguje na dva typy informácii:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>slovne obrazy (preto mame radi prirovnania)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>emoce.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>dokáže zosilňovať alebo zoslabovať emócie&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Pomenovanie zvyšuje emóciu
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>pomenovanie negatívnej emócie - zníži sa, úľava (psychoterapia).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>negatívne emócie sú niekoľkokrát silnejšie (3:1)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nepriatelia Netflixu:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>porno&lt;/li>
&lt;li>voľný obsah (youtube)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>spánok. mozog potrebuje vyriesenu vec, preto serial ktory nekonci. zapletka.
argumenty nefunguju v vyjednavani, reklame ci marketingu&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Zhrnutie 4 piliere vyjednavania:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Príprava&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Naplánovať ako vstúpiť do vyjednávania&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vedieť naspamäť prvú vetu&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vedieť riadiť vyjednávanie, nie argumentami ale hovorením, čo sa stane&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Naplánovať eskaláciu, aby ťa neprekvapila&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Stratégie:
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Giving-in:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Stratégia ústupu.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Niečo dávate a nič za to nedostane&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Vedie k frustrácii&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Môže otvárať nové možnosti do budúcnosti&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Competing:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Buduje vyjednávajúcu môc a silu. Opak k Giving-In&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Avoiding:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Napr. záujem o náprotivok s vyhýbaním sa kontaktu. Naťahovanie.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Frustrujete ľudí. Nebudujete vzťah.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Cooperating:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>niečo dávam a za to niečo dostávam.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Najideálnejší model.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nie je to win-win ani to nie je kompromis.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Compromis:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Oslava lenivosti.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Dostanete polovicu toho, čo chcete a polovicu toho, čo nechcete.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Nikdy neponúkajte kompromis. Vždy môžete dosiahnuť lepší výsledok.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Win-Win nie je stratégia, ale drahá chyba. Môže fungovať v 95% prípadoch&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Sila vs. vzťah.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Za 60 sekúnd vieme akú stratégiu ide náprotivok a vieme sa tomu prispôsobiť.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Budeme hlboký vzťah aby sme mali dôveru. Bez dôvery a vzťahu druhá strana nepristúpi na to, čo chceme.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Taktiky:
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Low-Hanging-Fruits
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>V poslednej tretine sa venujete najväčšiemu problému&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Put the Fish on the Table
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>najväčší konflikt na začiatku&lt;/li>
&lt;li>vyžaduje veľkú prípravu - dobré naplánovanie eskalácie&lt;/li>
&lt;li>pre 85% prípadov&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Hnedý flak
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>nikdy nevyjednávajte s strachom, ani z strachu&lt;/li>
&lt;li>konflikt treba vždy otvoriť a vyriešiť spoločne&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Misc:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bad infinity</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-02-25-bad_infinity/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2024-02-25-bad_infinity/</guid><description>&lt;p>Descriptions of modern hell. Inspired by Ted Goia&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.honest-broker.com/p/13-observations-on-ritual">13 Observations on Ritual&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Slow traditional culture -&amp;gt; Fast modern culture -&amp;gt; Dopamine culture&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The smartphone cannot be a ritualistic object.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Genuine ritual is always embedded in time and place.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Memes are rituals drained of transcendence.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The largest companies today are obsessed with generating content in a completely de-ritualized context.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Internet businesses feel this void, and try to fill it with pseudo-rituals&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In an overly digitized world, people embrace with intensity the few remaining ritualistic activities available to them.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Ritual is a source of stability, especially in our moments of greatest vulnerability&lt;/li>
&lt;li>If you created a community but eliminated all rituals of politeness and sociability, it would look like Twitter. Social media is the dark twin of ritual. It never achieves wholeness or closure.
&amp;gt; * &lt;strong>Scroller has no closure -&amp;gt; &amp;ldquo;bad infinity&amp;rdquo; (Hegel)&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Economic interests fear genuine ritual, because it is not about consumption&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When deprived of rituals, people are driven to create their own&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Artistic performances originated as rituals&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Even science originates as ritual.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When technology truly empowers life and promotes human flourishing, the results are ritualistic.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>So rituals ground us as a human being in time and space. They allocate our place in the bigger whole - in the cosmic order, which after all is the source of its name. Sanskritic &amp;ldquo;rta&amp;rdquo; means &amp;ldquo;cosmic order&amp;rdquo;. The smartphone allows us to do what we want and when we want. Instead of being allotted a role in the grand whole we become the centre of our own personal hell. And that&amp;rsquo;s the price of liberty - the freedom to do what I please in order to fool me that I can escape the limits of the person by doing so&amp;hellip;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Genesis</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-12-16-genezis/</link><pubDate>Sat, 16 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-12-16-genezis/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="stvorenie-sveta">Stvorenie sveta&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>1 Na počiatku stvoril Boh nebo a zem. 2 Zem bola pustá a prázdna, tma bola nad prahlbinou a Boží duch sa vznášal nad vodami. 3 Boh povedal: „Nech je svetlo!“ A bolo svetlo. 4 Boh videl, že svetlo je &lt;strong>dobré&lt;/strong>, a oddelil svetlo od tmy. 5 Boh nazval svetlo dňom a tmu nazval nocou. Bol večer, bolo ráno, prvý deň.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>6 Boh povedal: „Nech je obloha uprostred vôd a nech oddeľuje vody od vôd!“ 7 Boh utvoril oblohu a oddelil vody pod oblohou od vôd nad oblohou. Tak sa aj stalo. 8 Boh nazval oblohu nebom. Bol večer a bolo ráno, druhý deň.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Game of Life</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-11-16-game_of_life/</link><pubDate>Thu, 16 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-11-16-game_of_life/</guid><description>&lt;ol>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Career:&lt;/strong> Get a life. Learn something and do it well. Become financially independent. If you fail to do so, you even haven&amp;rsquo;t started to play.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Wisdom&lt;/strong>: Get frustrated with life. Start the search. This is the &amp;ldquo;wheel of fortune&amp;rdquo; tarot card. Philosophy. If you fail so, you&amp;rsquo;ll be trapped in running towards the ephemeral.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Death:&lt;/strong> Die, like Jesus did. Congrats, you made it. Liberation, freedom is yours. If you don&amp;rsquo;t, you&amp;rsquo;ll end up like an academic.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Paradise:&lt;/strong> (Wander and) Wonder until you&amp;rsquo;re ready for a new round. There is no failure.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --></description></item><item><title>Rýchlo, lacno a kvalitne</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-07-23-r%C3%BDchlo_lacno_a_kvalitne/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-07-23-r%C3%BDchlo_lacno_a_kvalitne/</guid><description>&lt;p>Vraj je možné mať len dve z týchto troch. K čomu to vedie?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="rýchlo-lacno-a-nekvalitne">Rýchlo, lacno a nekvalitne&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Výsledkom bude &amp;ldquo;šmejd&amp;rdquo;, resp. snaha vybehnúť s niekým resp. niečím. Na druhú stranu tento prístup bude &lt;strong>budovať inteligenciu&lt;/strong> niekoho, kto sa oň snaží. A tiež funguje proti inercii - lenivosti. Rýchlosťou človek unikne zemi.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="rýchlo-draho-a-kvalitne">Rýchlo, draho a kvalitne&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Nepozerať sa na cenu a požadovať prvotriedne výsledky buduje &lt;strong>sebadôležitosť&lt;/strong>. Z človeka stane elitista / snob / egoista &amp;hellip; indivíduum. Ale taktiež kvalita, krása, právo &amp;hellip; tie svetské hodnoty získajú svoju patričnú dôležitosť. Bude záležať na detailoch, ale už nie tých zemských ale mesačných. Človek unikne z pozemskej do mentálnej reality.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Mind of Napoleon</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-06-18-the_mind_of_napoleon/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-06-18-the_mind_of_napoleon/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://blas.com/the-mind-of-napoleon/">src&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>There are only two powers in the world – the power of the sword and the spirit…In the long run, the sword is always beaten by the spirit.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>How can there be a state without any religion? Society cannot exist without inequality of fortune, and inequality of fortune cannot exist without religion&lt;/li>
&lt;li>In Spinoza, each thought is a step to another thought; in Napoleon, each thought is a step to an action&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Luck is the ability to exploit accidents. A series of great actions is never the result of chance and luck, always the product of planning and genius&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Work, I was built for work. I have known the limitations of my legs, I have known the limitations of my eyes, I have never known the limitations of my working capacity&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Tirelessness, concentration, and speed – these were the characteristics of his mechanism&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Destiny is carried out, fate is suffered&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I am a poet in action&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I was sure of being understood by the last drummer boy&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Each looks through his own prism, which often misleads him&lt;/li>
&lt;li>There is little merit in copying or imitating&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Silence often produces the same effect as wisdom&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I start out by believing the worst&lt;/li>
&lt;li>One must have the will to live and be willing to die&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I had few really definite ideas, and the reason for this was that, instead of obstinately seeking to control circumstances, I obeyed them, and they forced me to change my mind all the time. Thus it happened that most of the time, to tell the truth, I had no definite plans but only projects&lt;/li>
&lt;li>He who fears to lose his reputation is sure to lose it&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When custom and reason are at odds, custom always wins out&lt;/li>
&lt;li>One should never attempt to forbid what one lacks the power to prevent&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Absolute power has no need to lie: it is silent. Responsible government, on the other hand, being obliged to speak, dissimulates and lies shamelessly&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>This famous division of labor, which in our age has brought mechanical pursuits to perfection, is absolutely fatal to the perfection of intellectual production. The quality of a production of the mind is in direct ratio to the universality of its creator&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>My policies are frank and open, because they are the results of long meditations of strength&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Great men are never cruel without necessity&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You must know that I am not in the least afraid of committing an act of cowardice if it were useful to me&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A true man never hates. A man made for public life and authority never takes account of personalities; he only takes account of things, of their weight and of their consequences&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Force is the law of animals; men are ruled by conviction&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Men who have changed the world never achieved their success by winning the chief citizens to their side, but always by stirring the masses&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Between meditating an action and carrying it out, you must put an interval of 3 years&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The great art of governing consists in not letting men grow old in their jobs&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The art of choosing men is not nearly so difficult as the art of enabling those one has chosen to attain their full worth&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The art consists in making others work rather than in wearing oneself out&lt;/li>
&lt;li>When an enemy army is in flight, you must either build a golden bridge for it or stop it with a wall of steel&lt;/li>
&lt;li>My great and most distinctive talent is to see everything in a clear light&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Greatness has its beauties, but only in retrospect and in the imagination&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I had a taste for founding, not for owning&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="masses">Masses&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Liberty is a need felt by a small class of people whom nature has endowed with nobler minds than the mass of men. Consequently, it may be repressed with impunity. Equality, on the other hand, pleases the masses.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What is a theory? Mere nonsense if you want to apply it to human masses&lt;/li>
&lt;li>I always went along with the opinion of the masses and with events. I always paid little attention to individual opinions and a great deal to public opinion&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Men who have changed the world never achieved their success by winning the chief citizens to their side, but always by stirring the masses&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --></description></item><item><title>AI and the Illusion of Intelligence</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-04-27-ai_and_the_illusion_of_intelligence/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-04-27-ai_and_the_illusion_of_intelligence/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.coursera.org/learn/ai-and-the-illusion-of-intelligence">src&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="week-1">Week 1&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Some Curious Experiments
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>In early 1600 William Harvey examined the heart and understood it&amp;rsquo;s a pump.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>A few years after Rene Descartes this concluded that machines cannot think - arrange it&amp;rsquo;s speech so it makes sense - what even the lowest type of man can do.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Alan Turing and the Imitation Game&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Illusion of Intelligence&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Explosion of Big Data&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="week-2">Week 2&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The Chomskyan Revolution
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Generative Gramar.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Descarte&amp;rsquo;s Miracle&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The Fatal Flaw of the Chomskyan Revolution&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Doing Violence to Language: the Ngram&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="week-3">Week 3&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="moores-law-does-not-make-the-singularity-likely">Moore&amp;rsquo;s Law Does Not Make the Singularity Likely&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>in the film 2001, the main character was the computer HAL, &lt;strong>solution to all the&lt;/strong> main (AI) &lt;strong>challenges&lt;/strong>. Along with these skills came human failings including paranoia and jealousy.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Singularity - computers will have far surpassed the humans. It will be an event impossible to understand. Our current understanding about world will not help us thinking what comes next and why.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Kurzweil predicts that Singularity will come 2045.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="week-4">Week 4&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="we-are-not-computers">We are not Computers&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Turing asked: what is computation?&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Turing: Halting Problem - some mathematically well-defined problems cannot be solved by computation.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We&amp;rsquo;ve been creating algorithms since the dawn of civilization.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Turing: computing is whatever a Turing machine can do.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Halting problem&lt;/li>
&lt;li>We&amp;rsquo;ve no reason our brains are computers.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>HAL is an entity capable of making decisions, having beliefs and pursuing goals. In short HAL is conscious.&lt;/strong>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Having (rich) internal life -&amp;gt; being conscious.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="an-engine-the-parts-of-which-are-men">An Engine, the Parts of which are Men&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Marx: Factory is engine parts of which are men.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Adam Smith: the man whose whole life is spent in performing a few simple operations &amp;hellip; becomes as stupid and ignorant as it is possible for a human creature to become&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Jaron Lenier and Sean Parker: social media is making is stupider. Technology can profoundly effect human mental ability and behaviours.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Marx&amp;rsquo;s factory can be thought of as a computer: from input it produces output. Marx: working in a factory is also reprogramming the workers into slightly changed mass of workers day by day.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>As we develop the technological world, we&amp;rsquo;re able to reprogram out own mentali live in profound ways. This was always true and the process is beginning to accelerate.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="from-gilligans-island-to-lost">From Gilligan&amp;rsquo;s Island to Lost&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Simple vs. complex (challenging plots and storytelling of 2004&amp;rsquo;s Lost)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Creators of Gilligan&amp;rsquo;s Island (show from &amp;rsquo;60s) were concerned the show would be too complex for the people to follow.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="a-new-kind-of-being">A New Kind of Being&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>The more AI develops the more it will develop changes in human intelligence and abilities.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>John McCarthy: Intelligence: &amp;ldquo;the computational part of the ability to achieve goals in the world&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>What people are able to do very much depends on what technological tools they&amp;rsquo;re able to use.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Not AI, but &lt;strong>IA - intelligence augmentation&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="re-wiring-the-human-parts">Re-wiring the Human Parts&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>While &lt;strong>all technologies change user, current tech platforms make it much more effectively&lt;/strong>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Computer technology becomes more tightly integrated with the human uiser.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="a-new-kind-of-being-1">A New Kind of Being&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Can AI reach the human level of intelligence? Wrong question!&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Development of AI is development of human intelligence.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --></description></item><item><title>Science</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-03-10-science/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-03-10-science/</guid><description>&lt;p>What does &amp;ldquo;science&amp;rdquo; actually mean? What does it encompass?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="slavic">Slavic&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Slovak or Czech word &amp;ldquo;veda&amp;rdquo; refers to the ancient &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vedas">Vedas&lt;/a>. These are the holy scriptures of ancient India. The name probably means &amp;ldquo;giving (da) knowledge (ve)&amp;rdquo;. The Vedas consist of two parts. The first is about the worldly knowledge and the later part (Upanishads) are about the sacred knowledge of the non-changing God.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The original meaning refers to the compendium of knowledge known as Vedas. Alas this is mostly unknown to the present speakers of the languages. The current meaning of the word is the modern, worldly science only.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Review whole codebase easily</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-26-review_whole_codebase/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-26-review_whole_codebase/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recently, a student asked me to review a small project hosted on GitHub. Initially, I assumed I would use the Pull Request/Code Review functionality of GitHub to do so. I found an easy &lt;a href="https://www.exasol.com/resource/how-to-do-a-full-review-of-your-repository-contents-on-github/">way&lt;/a> to perform it on the whole codebase.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>However, I eventually decided that I wanted to have a broader view, rather than just looking at a small portion of the changes through the Code Review&amp;rsquo;s microscope. Utilizing an IDE that could visualize the connections in the code and show how things were being used and defined also helped me a lot.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Slobodná vôľa</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-06-slobodna_vola/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-06-slobodna_vola/</guid><description>&lt;p>Existuje, či neexistuje? Čo to vlastne je?&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Slobodná vôľa hovorí, že agent, napr. človek sa môže slobodne rozhodnúť. Teda, že nie je determinovaný, ale sám sebe pánom svojho osudu. Na základe čoho si ale vyberá?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="existuje">Existuje?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Aby slobodná vôľa existovala musí platiť, že pri rozhodovaní v presne tej situácii, sa NE-rozhodneme presne rovnako. Lebo ináč by platilo, že voľba je podmienená situáciou a nie v rukách agentom. Situáciou chápem celý stav vesmíru. Všetky dostupné informácie včetne myšlienok a pocitov agenta.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>pra-vda: Reflexia inšpirovaná Murlim</title><link>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-03-pravda/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://uzak.github.io/post/2023-01-03-pravda/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="pravda">Pravda&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Čo je pravda? Aby niečo mohlo byť pravdou, nesmie sa to meniť. Ináč by to po zmene prestalo byť pravdou. Takže pravda je to, čo je stále tým istým.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="vnímanie">Vnímanie&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Ako funguje vnímanie? Vnímame na základe rozdielu. Vnímame iba veci premenlivé. Nemôžem vnímať veci konštantné, pretože by sme sme stratili rozdiel medzi teraz a vtedy/potom a tu a tam. Všetko by to bolo jedno.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="hľadanie-pravdy">Hľadanie pravdy&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Čo je aktivita? Aktivitou sa snažím docieliť niečoho. Mením. Konám. A tým pádom produkujem rozdiel.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>